<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="key-spaces">
  <title>Constructing key spaces</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>key space<indexterm>constructing</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>constructing key spaces</indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>In the simplest case, a given root map does not include any submaps, and every key name is
      defined by exactly one key-defining topicref. However, this is neither the only case nor the
      typical case.</p>
    <p>Most non-trivial publications involve maps and submaps, and it will often be the case that
            the same key name is defined more than once within the context of a given root map and
            its submaps. The processing challenge is to determine which key definition is the
            correct one.</p>
    <p>The general design intent of the DITA 1.2 key reference facility is that a given root map
      establishes a <i>global</i> key space within which a given key name has at most one binding
      and where earlier and <q>higher</q> definitions take precedence over later and <q>lower</q>
      definitions.</p>
    <p>By <q>higher</q> and <q>lower</q> I mean the position of a map within the tree of maps
            descending from the root map. Maps that are closer to the root map (<q>higher</q>) take
            precedence over maps that are farther from root map (<q>lower</q>). Within a map, maps
            referenced earlier take precedence over maps referenced later. This design allows maps
            to override the key definitions in the maps they reference. If the key definition
            facility were not defined in this way it would be impossible for higher-level maps to
            control key values.</p>
    <p>Note that because the key space defined by the root map is global, you cannot have different
      bindings for the same key active at different places within a map tree. This is a limitation
      to be sure, but without it, we would not have had time to get any indirection facility into
      DITA 1.2. It is likely that future versions of DITA will extend the key definition facility to
      provide other key scopes.</p>
    <p>At the same time, it is likely that additional <q>variable</q> facilities will be defined to
            satisfy requirements for locally-scoped, dynamically-resolved values that the key
            reference facility cannot satisfy today. In addition, there are processing techniques
            that allow you to get the effect of locally-scoped keys without changing the base key
            processing semantics. Many of these have been discussed on the Yahoo DITA Users
                group.<fn>If you have any question about the necessity of a global key space,
                consider the case of a topic referenced from one submap that references a key that
                is defined in two other submaps but not in the root map. If the key space was not
                global, then which of the two possible bindings to use would be undefined, and there
                would be no way for authors to indicate which they meant. Likewise, if keys were
                scoped by submaps, it would be impossible for topics in one submap to refer to a key
                defined in both its map scope and a different map scope. Thus, without a way of
                establishing the scope (key space), the only option is to have a global key space so
                all key references are unambiguous.</fn></p>
    <p>The formal definition of key space construction says that within a given map the first key
      definition in <q>document order</q> is the effective definition. Within the map tree, the
      first definition within a <i>breadth-first</i> traversal of the map tree takes precedence.</p>
    <p><q>Document order</q> means the order the start tags of each element in the XML document tree
            are encountered, technically a <term>depth-first</term> traversal of the element tree. A
            depth-first traversal goes from parent to child until a leaf node is reached, and only
            then goes to the next sibling of that leaf (or the next sibling of its nearest ancestor
            with a sibling) and so on down the tree. A <term>breadth first</term> traversal goes
            from one node to its siblings before then going to each of the siblings’ children. See
                <xref href="#key-spaces/fig-map-tree" format="dita"/>.</p>
    <p>Because the rule is <q>first in map document in document order then first in map tree in
        breadth-first order,</q> when the map tree consists of exactly one map, the first definition
      in document order wins. When the map tree consists of two or more maps, the first definition
      within the map nearest the root map in breadth-first order takes precedence, with the root map
      always being first.</p>
    <p>Consider a system of four maps: a root (Root Map 1), two submaps, Submap 1 and Submap 2, both
            referenced from the root map in the order Submap 1 followed by Submap 2, and submap
            Submap 3, referenced from Submap 1. </p>
    <fig
      id="fig-map-tree">
      <title>Map Tree of Four Maps</title>
      <image
        href="graphics/keys-and-keyrefs/map-tree.png"
        width="3.8in">
        <alt>Shows a tree of four boxes. "Root Map 1" points to "Submap 1" and "Submap 2". Submap 1 points to "Submap 3". The breadth-first ordering goes from Root Map 1 to Submap 1 to Submap 2 to Submap 3. The depth-first ordering goes from Root Map 1 to Submap 1 to Submap 3 to Submap 2.</alt>
      </image>
    </fig>
    <p>Any key defined in the root map will take precedence over the same key defined in any of the submaps. A key defined in Submap 1 will take precedence over the same key defined in Submap 2 because Submap 1 occurs before Submap 2 in the map tree. Finally any key defined in Submap 2 will take precedence over the same key defined in Submap 3 because Submap 2 occurs before Submap 3 in a breadth-first traversal of the map tree.</p>
    <p>Note that the position of key references is not important: the key space is global and must
      be determined before any key references can be resolved.</p>
    <p>Consider this set of key definitions in the root map:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Root Map 1&lt;/title>
  &lt;topicgroup>
     <b>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1A.dita"/></b>
     <b>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1B.dita"/></b>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
  <b>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1C.dita"/></b>
&lt;/map></codeblock>
    <p>Here there are three key-defining topicrefs for the key name <q>key-01.</q> The effective
      definition is the binding to topic-1A.dita, because that is the first definition in document
      order (depth-first traversal of the element tree within the map document). The breadth-first
      rule only applies to the tree of maps, not to the tree of elements within a document.</p>
    <p>Now consider the root map with a reference to Submap 1 added:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Root Map 1&lt;/title>
  &lt;topicgroup>
    &lt;mapref href="submap-01.ditamap"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
  &lt;topicgroup>
     &lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1A.dita"/>
     &lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1B.dita"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
  &lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1C.dita"/>
&lt;/map></codeblock>
    <p>If Submap 1 also defines a binding for key name <q>key-01</q> it cannot be effective because,
      by the breadth-first map tree traversal rule, any definition in the root map takes precedence
      over any definitions in submaps, even though the reference to the submap happens to occur
      before any of the key definitions in the root map.</p>
    <p>If we now add the reference to Submap 2 we establish the order of those maps in the map tree:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Root Map 1&lt;/title>
  &lt;topicgroup>
    &lt;mapref href="submap-01.ditamap"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
  &lt;mapref href="submap-02.ditamap"/>
  &lt;topicgroup>
     &lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1A.dita"/>
     &lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1B.dita"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
  &lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1C.dita"/>
&lt;/map></codeblock>
    <p>Again, it is the document (depth-first) order of the references to the maps that determines their ordering in the map tree. Thus, even though in this example the reference to Submap 2 comes first in a <i>breadth</i>-first traversal of the elements within the root map, that is not relevant because it is the document (depth-first) order that is important. Thus this markup produces the map tree shown in <xref
      href="#key-spaces/fig-map-tree"
      format="dita"/>.</p>
    <p>To complete the map tree Submap 1 must include Submap 3:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Submap 1&lt;/title>
  &lt;mapref href="submap-03.ditamap"/>
  &lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1D.dita"/>
&lt;/map></codeblock>
    <p>And let Submap 3 look like this:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Submap 3&lt;/title>
  &lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1E.dita"/>
  &lt;keydef keys="key-02" href="topic-2B.dita"/>
&lt;/map></codeblock>
    <p>Finally, Submap 2 looks like this:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Submap 2&lt;/title>
  &lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1F.dita"/>
  &lt;keydef keys="key-02" href="topic-2A.dita"/>
&lt;/map></codeblock>
    <p>The effective value of key <q>key-01</q> is set in the root map because the root map has at
      least one definition for that key.</p>
    <p>The effective value of the key <q>key-02</q> is determined by its first position within the
      map tree because it is not defined in the root map.</p>
    <p>In this case, key-02 is defined in two maps: Submap 2 and Submap 3. The effective definition is the definition in Submap 2 (topic-2A.dita) because Submap 2 comes first in the map tree in a breadth-first traversal.</p>
    <p>The key space defined by this map tree can be represented by a table that has one row for each unique key and indicates at least the effective definition, as shown in <xref
      href="#key-spaces/keyspace-table-01"
      format="dita"/>.</p>
    <table
      frame="all"
      id="keyspace-table-01">
      <title>Key space table for Root Map 1</title>
      <tgroup
        cols="3">
        <colspec
          colname="c1"
          colnum="1"
          colwidth="1.0*"/>
        <colspec
          colname="c2"
          colnum="2"
          colwidth="4.13*"/>
        <colspec
          colname="c3"
          colnum="3"
          colwidth="2.56*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Key Name</entry>
            <entry>Key Definitions 
              (In precedence order)</entry>
            <entry>Containing Map</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry
              morerows="5">key-01</entry>
            <entry><codeph><b>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1A.dita"/></b></codeph></entry>
            <entry>rootmap.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1B.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>rootmap.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1C.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>rootmap.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1D.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-01.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1F.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-02.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1E.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-03.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry
              morerows="1">key-02</entry>
            <entry><codeph><b>&lt;keydef keys="key-02" href="topic-2A.dita"/></b></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-02.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-02" href="topic-2B.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-03.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <p>In this table, the key definitions for a given key are listed in precedence order, first by document order within a single map and then by breadth-first order within the map tree. The first key definition for each key is therefore the effective one, as shown by the highlighting.</p>
    <p>Note that the root map serves as the identifier of the key space because it is the root map that ultimately determines the effective bindings of all the keys. Different root maps represent distinct key spaces.</p>
    <p>By the same token, you cannot resolve any key until you have established the active key space for the resolution attempt. This has important implications for authoring and component management, about which more later.</p>
    <p>To more clearly demonstrate the fact that different root maps establish different key spaces, let us now create Root Map 2, which omits the definitions of key-01 in the root and includes Submap 1 and Submap 2, but in the reverse order from Root Map 1:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Root Map 2&lt;/title>
  &lt;topicgroup>
    &lt;mapref href="submap-02.ditamap"/>
    &lt;mapref href="submap-01.ditamap"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
&lt;/map></codeblock>
    <p>Now Submap 2 comes before Submap 1 in the map tree and that makes the effective value of
      key-01 the binding defined in Submap 2, namely <q>topic-1F.ditamap.</q> The key space table
      for key space Root Map 2 looks like this:</p>
    <table
      frame="all"
      id="keyspace-table-02">
      <title>Key space table for Root Map 2</title>
      <tgroup
        cols="3">
        <colspec
          colname="c1"
          colnum="1"
          colwidth="1.0*"/>
        <colspec
          colname="c2"
          colnum="2"
          colwidth="4.13*"/>
        <colspec
          colname="c3"
          colnum="3"
          colwidth="2.56*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Key Name</entry>
            <entry>Key Definitions (In precedence order)</entry>
            <entry>Containing Map</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry
              morerows="1">key-01</entry>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1F.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-02.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1E.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-03.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry
              morerows="1">key-02</entry>
            <entry><codeph><b>&lt;keydef keys="key-02" href="topic-2A.dita"/></b></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-02.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-02" href="topic-2B.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-03.ditamap</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <p>Any topic that has a link to key <q>key-01</q> will link to different target topics when
      processed in the context of Root Map 1 than when processed in the context of Root Map 2.</p>
    <p>You might wonder why the key space table shows all the bindings even though only one can be effective within a given key space. There are several reasons:<ul>
      <li>For this example it makes it clear what the precedence order of the different definitions
                    is.</li>
      <li>For analysis and debugging it can be useful to know all the definitions of a given key in
          a given keyspace. Thus, key space constructing processors should build this sort of table
          so users can see it on request.</li>
      <li>In a CMS system it may be useful to maintain repository-wide knowledge of all the key
          definitions in all the maps, then determine effective key spaces dynamically. A <q>key
            database,</q> where you use the key for lookup, would resemble this table.</li>
      <li>When applicability (conditional processing) is in play, it may be necessary to hold all
          potentially effective bindings for a key and determine the effective binding in the
          context of a specific set of conditions. This is especially important in authoring support
          systems where authors may want to see a dynamic, in-editor view of the data as determined
          by some set of conditions. Unless the key space table includes at least all
          potentially-applicable key definitions, this type of dynamic view cannot be provided.</li>
      <li>In the future it is likely there will be a way to define the resolution scope for specific
          key references, which means that any definition of a key could potentially be effective
          based on specific processing-time or resolution-time scope settings.</li>
    </ul></p>
    <p>Finally, note that the map tree is constructed using only directly-addressed maps. This is
            because you can’t resolve any key-based map references until you construct the key space
            and you can’t construct the key space until you have constructed the map tree.</p>
    <p>This implies that there are conceptually at least two passes in the processing of the map: a first pass to construct the map tree and  key space and a second pass to construct the full map tree, taking any indirect map references into account. The output of the second step would then be the input to any additional processing applied to the map.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
