<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="ss2">
  <title>DITA’s Direct Addressing Syntax</title>
  <shortdesc>DITA uses URIs and a DITA-specific fragment identifier syntax to directly address components of DITA documents.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>addressing<indexterm>direct</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>direct addressing syntax</indexterm>
        <indexterm>URI<indexterm>fragment identifier for</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>fragment identifier<indexterm>DITA syntax for</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>DITA<indexterm>fragment identifier
          syntax</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>DITA<indexterm>addressing syntax</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>XML is a Web application and as such uses URIs for addressing. As an XML application, DITA
      uses URIs as well. All direct references in DITA are URI references, usually URLs. Almost
      without exception any element that can make a direct reference does so using the
        <xmlatt>href</xmlatt> attribute.</p>
    <p>To oversimplify, a URI reference consists of two basic parts: the resource part and the
            fragment identifier. Both are optional, but at least one or the other must be specified.
            The fragment identifier is separated from the resource part by a hash sign (#), for
            example,
            "<codeph>http://example.com/mydocs/doc-01/topic-01.dita#some-topic-id</codeph>", where
                <codeph>http://example.com/mydocs/doc-01/topic-01.dita</codeph> is the resource part
            and <codeph>some-topic-id</codeph> is the fragment identifier. For a complete definition
            of URIs see <cite>RFC 2396: Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax</cite>
                (<xref href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2396.txt" format="html" scope="external"
                >http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2396.txt</xref>). </p>
    <p>The resource part can be a uniform resource name (URN) or a uniform
      resource locator (URL). In most applications you will use URLs since those
      are, by definition, directly resolvable, while URNs are indirect and
      require another layer of processing to be resolved.</p>
    <p>URLs can be absolute or relative. Relative URLs are relative to the
      location of the XML document that contains the reference.<fn>Technically,
      they are relative to the effective base URL, which can be set by the
      <xmlatt>xml:base</xmlatt> attribute. DITA cannot prevent the use of
      <xmlatt>xml:base</xmlatt> but its use in an authoring system would be rare
      since it would cause all sorts of havoc in most situations. The main
      reason to use <xmlatt>xml:base</xmlatt> in an authoring environment would
      be to make authoring URLs of things outside the scope of the DITA content
      more convenient by moving the common part of the URL into a single
      location. Note that per the applicable standards for XML processing and
      URL resolution, the processing and application of
      <xmlatt>xml:base</xmlatt> when it is present is mandatory and
      unconditional for all URI references. This means that processors are not
      free to apply their own processing semantics for <xmlatt>xml:base</xmlatt>
      as regards the resolution of URI references.</fn></p>
    <p> Note that URLs use <q>/</q> (forward slash) as the path separator, not <q>\</q> (backward
      slash). Any use of <q>\</q> in DITA documents is wrong and should not be supported by any
      processor. Some processors will interpret these as Windows filenames, but they should not
      since the value is not a valid URL (at least not without escaping the backslash), and other
      processors are not likely to honor it.</p>
    <p>DITA fragment identifiers take one of two forms:<ul
      id="ul_uru_dys_gb">
      <li>For topic elements and elements within maps, the fragment identifier is the value of the
                    target element’s <xmlatt>id</xmlatt> attribute:
                        <codeph>href="#some-topic-id"</codeph> where <codeph>some-topic-id</codeph>
                    is the fragment identifier.</li>
      <li>For non-topic elements within topics, the fragment identifier is the topic ID, a forward
          slash (<q>/</q>), and the element ID:
            <codeph>href="#some-topic-id/some-element-id"</codeph>.<p>The element ID part must be an
            element within the non-topic children of the topic. That is, each topic establishes a
            separate ID namespace for all of its non-topic descendants. When you have nested topics
            each nested topic establishes its own ID namespace, which means that a parent topic and
            a nested topic may both have descendant non-topic elements with the same
              <xmlatt>id</xmlatt> value.</p></li>
    </ul></p>
    <p>Note that while the fragment identifier syntax for non-topic elements looks like a path, it is not path, it is always a topic-id/element-id pair. If you want to address an element within a nested topic you simply use the ID of the nested topic—you do not specify the ID of the ancestor topics. For example, given this topic with a nested topic:<codeblock>&lt;topic id="parent-topic">
  ...
  &lt;topic id="child-topic-01">
    &lt;title>Child Topic 1&lt;/title>
    &lt;body>
     &lt;p id="p-01">Paragraph one&lt;/p>
    &lt;/body>
  &lt;/topic>
&lt;/topic></codeblock></p>
    <p>The fragment identifier for the paragraph <q>p-01</q> is
        <codeph>#child-topic-01/p-01</codeph>
      <i>not</i>
      <codeph>#parent-topic/child-topic-01/p-01</codeph>.</p>
    <p>Likewise, the parent topic could also have a paragraph with the ID <q>p-01</q>:</p>
    <p>
      <codeblock>&lt;topic id="parent-topic">
    &lt;body>
     &lt;p id="p-01">Paragraph one in parent.&lt;/p>
    &lt;/body>
  &lt;topic id="child-topic-01">
    &lt;title>Child Topic 1&lt;/title>
    &lt;body>
     &lt;p id="p-01">Paragraph one in child.&lt;/p>
    &lt;/body>
  &lt;/topic>
&lt;/topic></codeblock>
    </p>
    <p>The fragment identifier for the parent’s paragraph would be
                <codeph>parent-topic/p-01</codeph>.</p>
    <p>You can, of course, refer to non-DITA content from DITA documents. In that case the fragment
      identifier syntax is determined by the target resource and is not defined or constrained by
      DITA. </p>
  </body>
</topic>
