<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="keyref-using-elements">
  <title>Elements that can make key references</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>key reference</indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>Key references can be used in a number of ways:<ul
      id="ul_ouq_vhp_eb">
      <li>For topic references (<xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>)</li>
      <li>For cross-references (<xmlelement>xref</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>longquoteref</xmlelement>, etc.)</li>
      <li>For image references (image)</li>
      <li>For inline elements to <xmlelement>make</xmlelement> them into links, including
            <xmlelement>ph</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement>, and <xmlelement>term</xmlelement>.</li>
      <li>For content references from any element that allows the <codeph>@conref</codeph> attribute
          (most elements except a few like <xmlelement>title</xmlelement>).</li>
    </ul></p>
    <p>Topic reference elements can use key references in place of URI references to point
      indirectly to topics, maps, or non-DITA resources. A key-defining topicref can itself use a
      key reference, which means there can be any number of levels of indirection between a key
      definition and its bound resource. This can be useful for example for imposing your own set of
      keys onto content that already uses a different set of keys, essentially creating new aliases
      for the pre-existing keys. It is a basic tenet of computer science that any problem can be
      solved with another layer of indirection, and the key reference facility lets you add as much
      indirection as your tools and authors will tolerate.</p>
    <p>When elements allow both <xmlatt>href</xmlatt> and <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt>,
        <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt> is used, unless the key reference cannot be resolved, in which case
        <xmlatt>href</xmlatt> is used. This can happen if the key is not defined or the resource it
      points to cannot be retrieved.</p>
    <p>Elements that allow <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt> but not <xmlatt>href</xmlatt>, such as
                <xmlelement>ph</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement>, and <xmlelement>term</xmlelement>,
            become links when they specify <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt> and the key is bound to a
            resource. If the element’s content is empty then the <q>link text</q> (that is, the text
            rendered for the element) is taken from a <xmlelement>linktext</xmlelement> or
                <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> element contained within the <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>
            element that defined the key. This mechanism makes it easier to author links that will
            work in different map contexts. </p>
    <p>If there are multiple levels of indirection (that is, a key definition points to another key
      definition and so forth, creating a chain of key definitions), the first definition in the
      chain that has link text is used for the link text. For example, consider this chain of key
      definitions:<codeblock>&lt;keydef keys="term-x" 
  keyref="term-x-gloss-01"/>
&lt;keydef keys="term-x-gloss-01
  keyref="term-x-gloss-02">
  &lt;topicmeta>
   &lt;linktext>Term X&lt;/linktext>
  &lt;/topicmeta>
&lt;/keydef>
&lt;keydef keys="term-x-gloss-02
  href="topics/gloss-term-x.dita">
  &lt;topicmeta>
   &lt;linktext>Term Echs&lt;/linktext>
  &lt;/topicmeta>
&lt;/keydef> </codeblock></p>
    <p>In this case, the keyword <codeph>&lt;keyword keyref="term-x"/></codeph> will get the link
      text <q>Term X,</q> not <q>Term Echs,</q> because the first key definition in the chain from
      term-x to term-x-gloss-01 to term-x-gloss-02 with link text is the one that contains a
        <xmlelement>linktext</xmlelement> element with the contents<q>Term X.</q>
    </p>
    <p>First mentions of technical terms are often linked to their glossary definitions. You can do
            this using <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt> from <xmlelement>term</xmlelement> or
                <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> rather than a separate cross-reference. In addition, the
            key definition can provide the actual text of the term so you don’t have to change the
            reference if the term changes.</p>
    <p>For example, in the printer example it would make sense to have the printer model number
            defined in the map, since we know that each publication will be specific to a single
            printer model. Within the task you would have something like
            this:<codeblock>&lt;task id="changing-toner-cartridge">
  ...
  &lt;context>
    &lt;figure>
      &lt;title><b>&lt;keyword keyref="printer-model-number"/></b> 
Toner Cartridge Access Panel&lt;/title>
      &lt;image keyref="illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel"/>
    &lt;/figure>
    &lt;p>For toner cartridge specifications see
    &lt;href keyref="printer-specs-topic/toner-cartridge-specs-table" 
          type="table"/>.
  &lt;/context>
  ...
&lt;/task></codeblock></p>
    <p>This example adds a <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> element with a <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt>
      attribute containing the key name <q>printer-model-number.</q> Note that the
        <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> element is empty.</p>
    <p>Within the printer-specific maps we add a definition for the key name
                <q>printer-model-number</q>:<codeblock>&lt;bookmap>
  &lt;title>Printer PR3604 Operator Manual&lt;/title>
  ...
  <b>&lt;keydef keys="printer-model-number"></b>
    &lt;topicmeta>
      <b>&lt;linktext>PR3604&lt;/linktext></b>
    &lt;/topicmeta>
  <b>&lt;/keydef></b>
  &lt;topicref
    keys="illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel"
    href="graphics/PR3604-toner-cartridge-access-panel.svg"
    format="svg"
    processing-role="resource-only"
  />
  ...
  &lt;chapter <b>keys="maintenance-chapter"</b> href="maintenance.dita">
    ...
    &lt;topicref 
       <b>keys="changing-printer-cartridge-task"</b>
       href="common/changing-the-printer-cartridge.dita"/>
    ...
  &lt;/chapter>
  ...
&lt;/bookmap></codeblock></p>
    <p>When the task topic is processed, the <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> element will be rendered as
            though the text of the <xmlelement>linktext</xmlelement> element in the key definition was its
            content. Because the key definition does not also point to a resource the
                <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> element will not be a link, since there’s nothing to link
            to.</p>
    <p>For navigation links, content references can use key references in place of, or in addition
      to, URI references. This allows you to have re-useable content references without having to
      know in advance what topic will provide the specific element referenced.</p>
    <p>For example, say the changing-the-toner-cartridge task is generic except for one step which
      must be model-specific for some reason. For the illustration and the model number, you can use
      a <xmlatt>conkeyref</xmlatt> attribute to establish the requirement for a model-specific step
      and let each model-specific map hook up the appropriate topic.</p>
    <p>The conkeyref in the task topic would look like
            this:<codeblock>&lt;task id="changing-toner-cartridge">
 ...
 &lt;context>
   &lt;figure>
     &lt;title>&lt;keyword keyref="printer-model-number"/> 
Toner Cartridge Access Panel&lt;/title>
     &lt;image keyref="illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel"/>
   &lt;/figure>
   &lt;p>For toner cartridge specifications see
&lt;href keyref="printer-specs-topic/toner-cartridge-specs-table" 
      type="table"/>.
 &lt;/context>
 &lt;steps>
   <b>&lt;step conkeyref="model-specific-steps/changing-toner-cartridge-step-one"/></b>
   &lt;step>
     &lt;cmd>...&lt;/cmd>
   &lt;/step>
    ...
 &lt;/steps>
  ...
&lt;/task></codeblock></p>
    <p>Here the <xmlelement>step</xmlelement> element uses the <xmlatt>conkeyref</xmlatt> attribute rather
      than <xmlatt>conref</xmlatt>. The semantic is the same (content use by reference) but the
      pointer is indirect rather than direct.</p>
    <p>The topic that provides the step would be a <q>resource</q> topic, intended only as a
      container of steps and other elements to be used by reference. It could look something like
      this:<codeblock>&lt;task id="reusable-steps">
  &lt;title>Task Component Resource Topic for Printer Model PR3604&lt;/title>
  &lt;taskbody>
    &lt;steps>
      <b>&lt;step id="changing-toner-cartridge-step-one">
        &lt;cmd>Lift the handle...&lt;/cmd>
      &lt;/step></b>
      ...
    &lt;/steps>
  &lt;/taskbody>
&lt;/task></codeblock></p>
    <p>Each model-specific version of this topic would need to use the <xmlatt>id</xmlatt> value
        <q>changing-toner-cartridge-step-one</q> for its version of that step.</p>
    <p>Within each product-specific map you would have a key definition that binds the key name
        <q>model-specific-steps</q> to the appropriate resource topic:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;bookmap>
  &lt;title>Printer PR3604 Operator Manual&lt;/title>
  ...
  &lt;keydef keys="printer-model-number">
    &lt;topicmeta>
      &lt;linktext>PR3604&lt;/linktext>
    &lt;/topicmeta>
  &lt;/keydef>
  <b>&lt;keydef keys="model-specific-steps"
          href="resources/PR3604/PR3604-reusable-steps.dita"
  /></b>
  &lt;keydef
    keys="illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel"
    href="graphics/PR3604-toner-cartridge-access-panel.svg"
    format="svg"
  />
  ...
  &lt;chapter 
     keys="maintenance-chapter"
     href="maintenance.dita">
    ...
    &lt;topicref 
       <b>keys="changing-printer-cartridge-task"</b>
       href="common/changing-the-printer-cartridge.dita"/>
    ...
  &lt;/chapter>
  ...
&lt;/bookmap></codeblock>
    <p>Note that this example uses <xmlelement>keydef</xmlelement> rather than <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>
      because <xmlelement>keydef</xmlelement> sets the <xmlatt>processing-role</xmlatt> attribute to
        <q>resource-only</q> by default, which is what we want for our reusable steps topic, since
      it is literally a resource used from other topics. Because keys are global you can only use this technique for root maps that reflect a
      single model. You cannot have two different models in the same publication and use a single
      key to get different results in different parts of the publication, at least not in DITA
      1.2.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
