<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="keys-and-applicability">
  <title>Key definitions and applicability (conditional processing)</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>key definition<indexterm>conditional processing of</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>key definition<indexterm>applicability of</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>conditional processing<indexterm>of key definitions</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>When all key definitions are unconditional, constructing the key space is relatively easy. However, when key definitions or map references are conditional, things can get complicated very quickly.</p>
    <p>The issue is that the DITA specification allows processors to choose when
      conditional processing is applied: before or after key space construction.
      In addition, some processors may need to apply conditional processing as
      late as possible, for example, editors and component management
      systems<indexterm>component management system<indexterm>condition
      awareness of</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>conditional
      processing<indexterm>in component management
      systems</indexterm></indexterm> that need to provide different views of
      the source documents reflecting different sets of active conditions.</p>
    <p>Note that only the filtering aspect of conditional processing is relevant
      here—flagging is a rendition issue and does not affect key space
      construction in any way.<indexterm>key
      space<indexterm>constructing</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>key
      space<indexterm>conditional processing implications
      for</indexterm></indexterm></p>
    <p>Flagging is the process of indicating in the presented content what it applies to, for
            example, "For Windows" or "For OSX". See <xref href="applicability.xml#topic-id"
                format="dita"/> for more information on flagging.</p>
    <p>When filtering is applied before key space construction, then the key space is fixed, meaning
      that any excluded key definitions are eliminated before key space construction and therefore
      cannot be represented in the final key space.</p>
    <p>When filtering is applied after key space construction, then the effective value for a given
      key cannot be completely determined except in the context of a specific set of active
      conditions.</p>
    <p>For example, let’s take the Root Map 1 example and define key-01 for different conditions
            using the <xmlatt>platform</xmlatt> property. That gives us the following markup:</p>
    <p>For example, say that the definitions of key-01 in the Root Map 1 example actually reflect the bindings appropriate for different conditions, resulting in this markup:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Root Map 1&lt;/title>
  &lt;topicgroup>
    &lt;mapref href="submap-01.ditamap"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
  &lt;topicgroup>
     &lt;keydef 
        <b>platform="platform-A"</b>
        keys="key-01" 
        href="topic-1A.dita"/>
     &lt;keydef 
        <b>platform="platform-B"</b>
        keys="key-01" 
        href="topic-1B.dita"/>
     &lt;keydef 
        <b>platform="platform-C"</b>
        keys="key-01" 
        href="topic-1C.dita"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
&lt;/map></codeblock>
    <p>Now, each definition of the key <q>key-01</q> has a different value for the
        <xmlatt>platform</xmlatt> property. The effective binding will depend on the setting for the
      platform property either at the time the key space is constructed (filtering applied first) or
      at the time the key reference is resolved (filtering applied after key space
      construction).</p>
    <p>In serial batch processors like the Open Toolkit or DITA2Go, the result is the same either
      way. But for interactive systems like editors and component management systems the difference
      is important.</p>
    <p>To make the example a little more interesting, let’s add an unconditional definition for the
            key as well as a duplicate conditional definition:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Root Map 1&lt;/title>
  &lt;topicgroup>
    &lt;mapref href="submap-01.ditamap"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
  &lt;topicgroup>
     &lt;keydef 
        <b>platform="platform-A"</b>
        keys="key-01" 
        href="topic-1A.dita"/>
     &lt;keydef 
        <b>platform="platform-A"</b>
        keys="key-01" 
        href="topic-1H.dita"/>
     &lt;keydef 
        <b>platform="platform-B"</b>
        keys="key-01" 
        href="topic-1B.dita"/>
     &lt;keydef 
        <b>platform="platform-C"</b>
        keys="key-01" 
        href="topic-1C.dita"/>
     &lt;keydef 
        keys="key-01" 
        href="topic-1G.dita"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
&lt;/map></codeblock>
    <p>Now there are four possible bindings, any one of which could be effective depending on the
      active value for the platform property. The binding to topic <q>topic-1H.dita</q> cannot ever
      be effective because it comes after a definition for the same key name with the same set of
      conditions (<codeph>platform = "platform-A"</codeph>). But the remaining four definitions
      could each be active under different sets of conditions.</p>
    <p>Thus, if a processor needs to provide resolution-time determination of key bindings based on
      conditions, it needs to add a <q>conditions</q> column to the key space table, as shown in
        <xref href="#keys-and-applicability/keyspace-table-03" format="dita"/>.</p>
    <table
      frame="all"
      id="keyspace-table-03">
      <title>Key space table for Root Map 1 with applicability conditions</title>
      <tgroup
        cols="4">
        <colspec
          colname="c1"
          colnum="1"
          colwidth="1.0*"/>
        <colspec
          colname="c2"
          colnum="2"
          colwidth="3.34*"/>
        <colspec
          colname="c3"
          colnum="3"
          colwidth="2.49*"/>
        <colspec
          colname="newCol4"
          colnum="4"
          colwidth="2.46*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Key Name</entry>
            <entry>Key Definitions (In precedence order)</entry>
            <entry>Containing Map</entry>
            <entry>Applicable Conditions</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry
              morerows="6">key-01</entry>
            <entry><codeph><b>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1A.dita"/></b></codeph></entry>
            <entry>rootmap.ditamap</entry>
            <entry>platform = platform-A</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph><b>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1B.dita"/></b></codeph></entry>
            <entry>rootmap.ditamap</entry>
            <entry>platform = platform-B</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph><b>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1C.dita"/></b></codeph></entry>
            <entry>rootmap.ditamap</entry>
            <entry>platform = platform-C</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph><b>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1D.dita"/></b></codeph></entry>
            <entry>rootmap.ditamap</entry>
            <entry>None</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1D.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-01.ditamap</entry>
            <entry>None</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1F.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-02.ditamap</entry>
            <entry>None</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-01" href="topic-1E.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-03.ditamap</entry>
            <entry>None</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry
              morerows="1">key-02</entry>
            <entry><codeph><b>&lt;keydef keys="key-02" href="topic-2A.dita"/></b></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-02.ditamap</entry>
            <entry>None</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><codeph>&lt;keydef keys="key-02" href="topic-2B.dita"/></codeph></entry>
            <entry>submap-03.ditamap</entry>
            <entry>None</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <p>Now a processor resolving <q>key-01</q> sees four potentially effective definitions, and to
      resolve the key reference, it needs to know the value of the <xmlatt>platform</xmlatt>
      condition.</p>
    <p>The implications for dynamic resolution are:<ol
      id="ol_eqz_pqw_cb">
      <li>Processors must inspect the set of conditions on each key definition to determine the set
          of potentially applicable key definitions. For a given key, the first definition with a
          unique set of conditions is potentially effective, second and subsequent definitions with
          the same condition set cannot be potentially effective (by the precedence rules for key
          definitions).</li>
      <li>Processors must maintain knowledge of the applicable conditions for each potentially-effective key definition.</li>
      <li>Resolution requests must allow users to specify active conditions as parameters to the
          request. That is, given an API method like <apiname>resolveKeyReference()</apiname>, the
          parameters must include a set of active conditions in addition to the key space (or the
          identifier of the root map that establishes the key space) and the key to be resolved.
          Likewise, user interfaces that allow users to see the effect of resolved references must
          provide a way to specify active conditions. This could be either through direct
          specification or through prior configuration.</li>
      </ol></p>
  </body>
</topic>
