<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="keys-and-keyrefs">
  <title>Keys and key references</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>key</indexterm>
        <indexterm>key reference</indexterm>
        <indexterm>key space</indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>Key references are indirect because the reference is just a key name. The key name is bound
      to a resource by a separate key definition within a map. In order to resolve the initial
      reference to the ultimate target resource, the processor must first find the correct key
      definition and then resolve that to a resource, which then becomes the resource to which the
      initial key reference resolves. The resource bound to the key name be a topic, a map, or a
      non-DITA resource, such as a graphic or Web page.</p>
    <p>Indirect addressing allows you to author links that will resolve to
      different resources (topics, maps, graphics, or other non-DITA things)
      depending on the root maps that use them. </p>
    <p>A typical example is a generic task that applies to many products but
      which refers to product-specific details. For example, printers often use
      the same print engine and toner cartridge but have different covers. The
      task of changing the toner cartridge is the same for all applications of
      the print engine but the illustrations of the specific printers that use
      it will be different for each printer model.</p>
    <p>If the <q>change the toner cartridge</q> task included a reference to a printer-specific
      illustration you would need a separate copy of the task for each printer model, even though
      the text of the task is identical for all printers. By contrast, if the task could refer
      abstractly to the <q>changing the toner cartridge</q> illustration and let some other part of
      the system figure out which illustration to use for each instance, then you would only need
      one copy of the task.</p>
    <p>The <q>other part of the system</q> binds key names to specific resources using key
      definition topicrefs within maps. In particular, the root map for a publication determines the
      binding of keys to resources. Different root maps can define different bindings for the same
      key.</p>
    <p>Key bindings create a <i>global</i> key space for a given root map. This means that, within
      the context of a given root map, all references to a given key name will resolve to the same
      resource. When a root map includes other maps it forms a <term>map tree</term>. Key
      definitions may occur within any map in the map tree, and there may be multiple definitions
      for the same key name. When there are multiple definitions for the same key, only one can be
      the <q>effective</q> binding within the scope of a given root map. The rules for determining
      which definition of a key is the effective one are explained in <xref
        href="constructing-key-spaces.xml#key-spaces" format="dita"/>. </p>
    <p>For authors, the important (dare I say key) concept is that key bindings are global, not
            scoped by the map they are defined in. Thus it doesn’t matter where a given key
            reference is, relative to where the effective key binding happens to be in the map tree:
            the binding is global and therefore all references to the key will resolve to the same
            resource for a given root map. This behavior is designed to allow higher maps in the map
            tree to determine the effective bindings for specific keys. While you might intuitively
            expect that key definitions within a submap would override those defined in an ancestor
            map, keys don’t, and can’t, work that way. The discussion of key space construction
                <xref href="constructing-key-spaces.xml#key-spaces" format="dita"/> discusses the
            global aspect of keys in more detail.</p>
    <p>In the case of our toner cartridge replacement task we know that we need to always have an
      illustration of the printer that shows where the toner access panel is. We can assign a key
      name to this illustration and use it to indirectly point to the graphic. For example we could
      assign the key <q>illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel</q> and then use it from an
        <codeph>&lt;image></codeph> element, like
      so:<codeblock>&lt;task id="changing-toner-cartridge">
  ...
  &lt;context>
    &lt;figure>
      &lt;title>Toner Cartridge Access Panel&lt;/title>
      <b>&lt;image keyref="illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel"/></b>
    &lt;/figure>
  &lt;/context>
  ...
&lt;/task></codeblock></p>
    <p>Note that the <xmlelement>image</xmlelement> element uses a <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt> attribute,
            rather than an <xmlatt>href</xmlatt> attribute. The value of the <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt>
            attribute is a <term>key name</term>. As the author of this task we only need to know
            the key name for the graphic, we don’t need to know where the graphic is. In fact,
            because we know that this key will resolve to many different graphics in different
            printer-specific publications, we <i>can’t</i> know for sure what graphic it will
            resolve to. Of course, while we’re authoring we might have a particular version of this
            graphic, for example, the illustration for the first printer model this task is used
            for, or maybe a representative graphic that serves as guidance to illustrators who will
            create the printer-specific versions. But, as the author of this task, we don’t care
            what graphic the key <q>illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel</q> resolves to as
            long as it resolves to something in each publication.</p>
    <p>Using the key establishes a requirement for the illustration but it’s up to the author of
            each model-specific publication’s map to bind key to the appropriate illustration.</p>
    <p>Within a map, you create a key definition using the <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> element or
      any specialization of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>. The <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> element
      uses the <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt> attribute to specify the key or keys to be defined and then
      either points to a resource (a topic, another map, or a non-DITA resource such as a graphic)
      or uses subelements within <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement> to define text to use as the resource
      (or both).</p>
    <p>For our task example, we need to bind the key
        <q>illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel</q> to the appropriate printer-specific
      illustration. This means that we must have a separate root map for each different printer
      model and then within each map, create the appropriate key definition. For example, for
      printer model <q>PR2105</q> you might have a root map like this:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;bookmap>
  &lt;title>Printer PR2105 Operator Manual&lt;/title>
  ...
  &lt;topicref
    keys="illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel"
    <b>href="graphics/PR2105-toner-cartridge-access-panel.svg"</b>
    format="svg"
    processing-role="resource-only"
  />
  ...
  &lt;chapter href="maintenance.dita">
    ...
    &lt;topicref href="common/changing-the-printer-cartridge.dita"/>
    ...
  &lt;/chapter>
  ...
&lt;/bookmap></codeblock>
    <p>The highlighted <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> element represents a key definition that binds
      the key name <q>illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel</q> to the graphic file
        <filepath>graphics/PR2105-toner-cartridge-access-panel.svg</filepath>, which is the
      illustration for the PR2105 model.<fn>You could of course have model-specific key definitions
        that use selection (conditional) attributes reflecting the models to which they apply, but
        not for this example. However, because key bindings are global, you would still only be able
        to reflect a single model in given publication using conditional key definitions.</fn>
    </p>
    <p>Note the <xmlatt>processing-role</xmlatt> attribute on the <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>
      element. This attribute, new in DITA 1.2, indicates whether the topicref contributes to the
      main navigation tree of the map (the value <q>normal,</q> which is the default) or serves only
      as a resource used by reference from elsewhere (<q>resource-only</q>). Because this graphic is
      not intended to be included in the result publication at this point in the map we must specify
      a processing role of <q>resource-only</q> to tell the processor not to do anything with the
      graphic other than remember that there is a key associated with it.</p>
    <p>The example map also refers to the changing-the-printer-cartridge task topic, representing a
      specific use of the topic, a topic we know will be used from many different printer-specific
      publications.</p>
    <p>When the task topic is processed <i>in the context of the PR2105 map</i> the effective
      binding of the key name <q>illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel</q> will be to the PR2105
      graphic. But when the same topic is used in different maps the binding may be different. For
      example, the map for the printer model PR3604 would look like this:</p>
    <codeblock>&lt;bookmap>
  &lt;title>Printer PR3604 Operator Manual&lt;/title>
  ...
  &lt;topicref
    keys="illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel"
    <b>href="graphics/PR3604-toner-cartridge-access-panel.svg"</b>
    format="svg"
    processing-role="resource-only"
  />
  ...
  &lt;chapter href="maintenance.dita">
    ...
    &lt;topicref href="common/changing-the-printer-cartridge.dita"/>
    ...
  &lt;/chapter>
  ...
&lt;/bookmap></codeblock>
    <p>Note that the only difference between the two model-specific maps is the filename of the illustration to use. The key name is the same and the task topic is the same.</p>
    <p>Thus, the indirection provided by the key reference mechanism allows a single task to be used
      unchanged in different maps and be associated with the appropriate linked resources.</p>
    <p>Note that this indirection separates the concern of information content (what information is
      required to support a specific topic) from the concern of content configuration management.
      The author of the topic says, as the content designer, <q>this topic requires an illustration
        that shows the toner cartridge access panel</q> and expresses that general requirement by
      using a key reference rather than a direct reference to a specific graphic. It is up to the
      author of the map to define the key binding to the appropriate graphic. This makes the content
      more flexible, but it means there have to be appropriate business processes and communication
      in place so the topic author and map author coordinate appropriately (and of course, somebody
      has to make sure the illustrations get drawn).</p>
    <p>The example above uses <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> elements to define the key bindings so
            that it’s clear that key definitions are done with topicrefs. Any topic reference can
            define keys. However, in most cases, you want to define keys as resource-only topicrefs
            and then use those keys from elsewhere. To make that easier, DITA 1.2 provides the
                <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> specialization <xmlelement>keydef</xmlelement>, which simply
            sets the default value for the <xmlatt>processing-role</xmlatt> attribute to
                <q>resource-only.</q> But it can also be useful to associate keys with normal (non
            resource-only) topicrefs, for example, to enable key-based linking to specific parts of
            a publication.</p>
    <p>For example, in our printer operator guide publications it could make sense to put keys on the chapters and subsection topicrefs too, resulting in a map like this: </p>
    <codeblock>&lt;bookmap>
  &lt;title>Printer PR3604 Operator Manual&lt;/title>
  ...
  &lt;topicref
    keys="illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel"
    href="graphics/PR3604-toner-cartridge-access-panel.svg"
    format="svg"
    processing-role="resource-only"
  />
  ...
  &lt;chapter 
     <b>keys="maintenance-chapter"</b>
     href="maintenance.dita">
    ...
    &lt;topicref 
       <b>keys="changing-printer-cartridge-task"</b>
       href="common/changing-the-printer-cartridge.dita"/>
    ...
  &lt;/chapter>
  ...
&lt;/bookmap></codeblock>
    <p>Here the navigation topicrefs now have keys that allow references to those topics by key
      reference. For example, you could have cross-references to the changing-the-printer-cartridge
      task that use the key rather than a direct href to the topic
      file:<codeblock>&lt;concept id="indicator-codes">
  &lt;title>Indicator codes and response&lt;/title>
  &lt;conbody>
    ...
    &lt;dl>
      ...
      &lt;dlentry>
        &lt;dt>Toner low&lt;/dt>
        &lt;dd>Change the toner cartridge.
See <b>&lt;xref keyref="changing-printer-cartridge-task"/></b>.
        &lt;/dd>
      &lt;/dlentry>
      ...
    &lt;/dl>
    ...
   &lt;/conbody>
&lt;/concept></codeblock></p>
    <p>Here the author of the topic has indicated a requirement for a changing the printer cartridge
            task, but by using a key doesn’t have to worry about the specific task topic. As for the
            image reference above, the key will be resolved to whatever resource is ultimately bound
            to the key <q>changing-printer-cartridge-task</q> in the context of a specific map. That
            might be the generic task or, for some printers, it might be a printer-specific task.
            The author of the indicator codes topic doesn’t have to know or care.</p>
    <p>Note too that a key reference to a normal-processing-role topicref
      establishes a link to a specific use of the target topic, not just to the
      topic in general. This allows you to have the same topic used multiple
      times in a map and have unambiguous references to a specific use of that
      topic, allowing processors to do the right thing.</p>
    <p>A topicref that specifies the <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt> attribute is said to be a <q>key-defining
        topicref.</q> A key-defining topicref binds a key to a <q>resource,</q> which can be any of
      the following:<ul>
        <li>A topic</li>
        <li>A map</li>
        <li>A non-DITA object (technically, anything that can be addressed by URL that is not itself
          a DITA document)</li>
        <li>Subelements within the topicref element that provide replacement text for elements like
                        <xmlelement>term</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement>, and
                        <xmlelement>xref</xmlelement> (See <xref href="keys-as-variables.xml#topic-id"
                        format="dita"/> for more on this use of keys).</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>Note that a key cannot be bound directly to a non-topic element within a topic, it can only
            be bound to the topic. Key-based references to elements within topics still require you
            to specify the ID of the target element within the topic. This has the side effect that
            key-based references to specific elements require that the same element ID be used in
            all topics bound to the key in different maps. </p>
    <p>For example, if you needed to create a cross-reference from the changing-the-toner-cartridge
            task to a table in another topic that must exist for each printer, but will be different
            for each model, that table would need to have the same <xmlatt>id</xmlatt> value in each
            version of the topic that provides the table. This turns out not to be a problem in
            practice because these types of topics are usually cloned from a template or an original
            starting topic, but it does mean that there has to be some coordination of IDs used in
            these circumstances because there is no separate indirection mechanism for pointing to
            elements within topics (at least not in DITA 1.2—there’s no technical barrier to such a
            facility, just a concern about complexity in order to satisfy a relatively rare use
            case, one for which there is a workaround).</p>
    <p>Key-based references to elements within topics use the syntax
          <codeph><varname>key-name</varname>/<varname>element-id</varname></codeph>. For example,
      to create a cross-reference to a specific table in another topic you would do
      this:<codeblock>&lt;task id="changing-toner-cartridge">
  ...
  &lt;context>
    &lt;figure>
      &lt;title>Toner Cartridge Access Panel&lt;/title>
      &lt;image keyref="illustration-toner-cartridge-access-panel"/>
    &lt;p>For toner cartridge specifications see
    &lt;/figure>
<b>&lt;href keyref="printer-specs-topic/toner-cartridge-specs-table" 
   type="table"/></b>.
  &lt;/context>
  ...
&lt;/task></codeblock></p>
    <p>The topics that get bound to the key <q>printer-specs-topic</q> must each have a
        <xmlelement>table</xmlelement> element with the ID <q>toner-cartridge-specs-table.</q>
    </p>
  </body>
</topic>
