<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Pointing to Things: Linking and Addressing in DITA</title>
  <shortdesc>DITA relies heavily on the use of different kinds of links. DITA links may use direct addresses (URI references) or indirect addresses (key references).</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>addressing</indexterm>
        <indexterm>key reference<indexterm>for linking</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>href</indexterm>
        <indexterm>linking</indexterm>
        <indexterm>hyperlink <index-see-also>link</index-see-also></indexterm>
        <indexterm>DITA<indexterm>linking</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>DITA<indexterm>addressing</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>DITA’s linking and addressing capabilities are heavily influenced by IBM IDDoc, the HyTime
            standard, and other formal models of hyperlinking and hypertext, but they also reflect
            the practical recognition that linking is essential for reuse and for optimizing the
            usability of information. While DITA was not originally designed primarily as a
            hypertext application, in fact it has become a sophisticated hypertext application with
            a reasonably consistent linking and addressing architecture.</p>
    <p>To talk about the hyperlinking and addressing features of DITA it is
      necessary to use some jargon. The following sections first explain general
      linking and addressing concepts and then discuss how those concepts are
      implemented in DITA.</p>
  </body>
  <topic
    id="sidebar_zrq_szq_1f">
    <title>Hypertext Jargon: A Twisty Maze of Passages</title>
    <body>
      <p>There is no single accepted vocabulary for talking about links. However, there is a fairly
                well-established vocabulary that comes out of work done on computer hypertext
                systems in the 1980s and early 1990s and is reflected in things like the HyTime
                standard. The terminology used here is the terminology I have used for the last 20
                years or so in my work both applying hypertext and hyperlinking to large-scale
                systems of documents and as a co-editor of the HyTime standard. I can’t claim that
                it is universally understood, but I think it’s well enough established that anyone
                already well versed in hypertext formalisms would understand the jargon. I have
                presented the terminology I use as received, without bothering to qualify it, since
                I consider it to be common vocabulary and not jargon specific to this book. As
                relatively few people today give much thought to the formalisms behind hyperlinking
                systems, I figure both that my jargon is as good as anyone’s and that you’re not
                likely to run into anyone with a competing set of jargon and a reason to argue with
                my particular use of terms.</p>
      <p>However, the jargon I use will not necessarily be reflected in other
        applications that do hyperlinking so you may need to work out the
        mapping between the general concepts and abstractions presented here and
        the details of any particular application or markup design. One purpose
        of presenting this abstract model of linking is to separate the general
        from the specifics of markup and implementation details so that it is in
        fact possible to meaningfully compare and analyze how different
        applications handle linking, which can be very important for generating
        specific interactive renditions of DITA content from DITA source. </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
