<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Maps and Topics</title>
  <shortdesc>DITA’s markup design is based on an approach to content authored characterized by
        standalone units (<q>topics</q>) organized into different structures by separate documents
            (<q>maps</q>).</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>map<indexterm>overview</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>topic<indexterm>overview</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>In most traditional XML applications for documents, a <q>publication</q> is represented by a
            single XML document that contains all the content and defines the hierarchical
            organization of the publication. With few exceptions, before the publication of the
            XInclude specification, there was no standard way to do anything else. XInclude allows
            for a weak form of separation of structure from content but does not really do more than
            you could always do with external parsed entities. </p>
    <p>Neither external parsed entities nor XInclude are useful for re-use because they are both
            use-by-copy, not use-by-reference. For example, the XInclude specification does not
            provide for rewriting IDs and references to them in included content. That means that an
            XInclude is equivalent to copying the content referenced literally, which is no
            different from using external parsed entities. In addition, XInclude only supports
            direct URI references and does not support indirect addressing. That makes it
            inappropriate for authoring in a re-use context. Thus, for DITA’s purposes, where re-use
            and modularity are primary driving requirements, external parsed entities and XInclude
            have no value.</p>
    <p>DITA’s design was driven by the need to have a clear and complete separation between the
            content used in a publication and the structure of that publication. The idea was that
            content should be organizable into reusable chunks that could then be organized into
            structures for different purposes. Because, in this environment, content would
            necessarily have no knowledge of where it was or how it might be used, it would be
            necessary for the users to impose information onto the content: titles, metadata,
            additional content, and so on.</p>
    <p>Because DITA was designed initially to support the technical documentation practice of
      modular writing, the content chunks are called <q>topics,</q> meaning roughly a <q>a single
        rhetorical topic or subject</q> This implies that the content more or less stands alone and
      is thus inherently reusable. This idea makes general sense in a technical documentation
      context, though it cannot always be achieved in that context. Divorced from any particular
      writing practice or editorial policy, topics are simply titled units of content.</p>
    <p>Because the primary use of the content is to produce published information for human use, and
      those publications usually need some sort of navigation structure, the publication structuring
      component was called a <q>map,</q> meaning roughly a map of navigation structures onto
      content.</p>
    <p>Thus in DITA there are two types of XML document:<fn>In fact there are really four types
                defined by the DITA specification: map, topic, ditabase, and DITAVAL. However,
                ditabase and DITAVAL do not directly apply to the DITA architecture.</fn> map
            documents and topic documents. Map documents are documents whose root element is
                <xmlelement>map</xmlelement> or a specialization of <xmlelement>map</xmlelement>. Topic
            documents are documents whose root element is <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> or a
            specialization of <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement>. No document with any other element type as
            its root can be a conforming DITA document. Thus, even though XML allows any element
            type defined within a DTD or any global type defined in an XSD schema to be the root of
            a document governed by that DTD or schema, the DITA standard requires all conforming
            DITA documents to be either map documents or topic documents.</p>
    <p>For practitioners used to more freedom in how content is organized for storage, this may seem
      like a bit of a severe restriction. However, there are good reasons for this design approach.
        <ul id="ul_cyf_smr_vf">
        <li>It ensures, in part, that all DITA documents have a consistent structure and are
          consistently described in terms of their structural requirements (that is, their DITA
          document types).</li>
        <li>It ensures that all DITA documents are objects in the general computer science
          sense.</li>
        <li>It means that DITA-aware component management systems only need to know about two
                    things: maps and topics—they don’t need to manage elements below the topic or
                    map level as storage objects.</li>
        <li>It means you can practically manage DITA content on a file system or in a simple code
                    control system.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>One practical implication of this requirement is that you may have topic documents that serve
      only to hold elements intended for use by reference from other topics. For example, you might
      have a topic that contains nothing but warnings used by reference or phrase elements that
      contain product-specific terms or whatever. This is perfectly natural in DITA and should not
      bother you at all.</p>
    <p>While DITA does not require the use of maps—you could represent an entire publication as a
      single XML document containing a tree of topics—it definitely rewards it and in most cases
      there is no reason not to use maps and many reasons to use them. Many people (and tools)
      assume that maps are required.</p>
  </body>
  <topic
    id="subsection_1f16405e-0128-4c5a-aefa-a1972c51c798">
    <title>Topics</title>
    <titlealts>
      <searchtitle>Architectural overview of DITA topics</searchtitle>
    </titlealts>
    <shortdesc>The <q>topic</q> is the primary unit of content in DITA—all content must be in a
      document whose root element is, or is specialized from, <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement>.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
      <metadata>
        <keywords>
          <indexterm>topic<indexterm>overview of</indexterm></indexterm>
        </keywords>
      </metadata>
    </prolog>
    <body>
      <p>A topic is a titled unit of content. A topic must have a title (<xmlelement>title</xmlelement>)
        and topics that consist of only titles are perfectly fine (these are referred to as
          <q>title-only topics</q>). A topic may have a separate navigation title, a separate search
        title, a short description (<xmlelement>shortdesc)</xmlelement>, an abstract
          (<xmlelement>abstract</xmlelement>), a prolog (<xmlelement>prolog</xmlelement>) (containing metadata
        for the topic), and a body (<xmlelement>body</xmlelement>). A topic may have child topics
        following the body.</p>
      <p>The topic’s body contains the direct content of the topic: paragraphs, lists, figures, and
                tables. The body may contain one level of arbitrarily-titled containers
                    (<q>sections</q>) or any level of untitled containers (<q>body divisions</q>).
                See <xref keyref="sections-and-divs"/>.</p>
      <p>A topic may have alternate titles (<xmlelement>titlealts</xmlelement>): one
        for use in navigation contexts (<xmlelement>navtitle</xmlelement>) and one for
        searching (<xmlelement>searchtitle</xmlelement>). </p>
      <p>Navigation titles are intended to be used in tables of contexts or other navigation aids.
        When specified within the topic itself, navigation titles usually provide a shorter version
        of the title. Because navigation is necessarily a function of where a topic is used,
        navigation titles are usually imposed by maps rather than being specified by the topic
        itself. A topic reference to a topic may specify the navigation title to use for that
        reference to the topic (see <xref href="#subsection_9830d280-ec0c-49b9-a27d-9cb028d4b665"
          format="dita"/>).</p>
      <p>Search titles are intended to provide a form of the title for use in search results,
                usually because the topic’s main title would not be distinct in isolation. For
                example, this topic’s title, <q>Topics</q> is clear in the context of this chapter ,
                but would be ambiguous in a list of search results. A better search title would be
                    <q>Architectural overview of DITA topics.</q></p>
      <p>A topic element must have an <xmlatt>id</xmlatt> attribute. The <xmlatt>id</xmlatt> attribute on topic elements is an XML ID, meaning that it must be unique within the XML document that contains the topic. This means that if you have nested topics within the root topic, they must all have unique IDs within the scope of that XML document.</p>
      <p>There is no general requirement that topic IDs be unique beyond the scope of the XML
                document that contains them. However, some tools assume global ID uniqueness or
                impose that requirement. They should not and any that do are, I assert, broken. The
                identity of a topic is established by the identity of the XML document that contains
                it, that is, the storage location of that document. Making topic IDs globally unique
                doesn’t add anything. It just complicates authoring and implementation and adds an
                opportunity for error that you don’t need.</p>
      <p>DITA provides, through maps, more than sufficient facilities for naming topics uniquely.
        There is no need for globally-unique IDs on topic elements.</p>
      <p>See <xref
        keyref="topic-structural-pattern"/> for a deeper discussion of topic markup.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic
    id="subsection_9830d280-ec0c-49b9-a27d-9cb028d4b665">
    <title>Maps</title>
    <shortdesc>Maps use hyperlinks (topic references) to organize topics into arbitrary structures.
      Maps may impose titles and metadata onto topics. Maps bind names (<q>keys</q>) to topics to
      enable indirect addressing.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
      <metadata>
        <keywords>
          <indexterm>DITA map<index-see>map</index-see></indexterm>
          <indexterm>map<indexterm>overview of</indexterm></indexterm>
          <indexterm><xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement></indexterm>
          <indexterm><xmlelement>anchorref</xmlelement></indexterm>
          <indexterm><xmlelement>navref</xmlelement></indexterm>
          <indexterm><xmlelement>reltable</xmlelement></indexterm>
        </keywords>
      </metadata>
    </prolog>
    <body>
      <p>A DITA map is nothing more than a set of hyperlinks pointing to topics (or non-DITA
        things). The base hyperlink element type is <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>. The name
          <q>topicref</q> is a slight misnomer because <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> elements may
        point to things that are not topics, including DITA maps, graphics, and non-DITA resources
        such as websites, PDF documents, and so on, or they may not point to anything. A more
        accurate name would be something like <q>map component link,</q> but <q>topicref</q> is the
        name DITA uses.<fn>There are many places where a more complete abstraction of DITA markup
          could be defined. That activity will have to wait for DITA 2.0, where the need for
          backward compatibility with DITA 1.x is removed.</fn></p>
      <p>A map may also have a title (<xmlelement>title</xmlelement>) and metadata
        (<xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement>). It may also include three other element
        types that are not specializations of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>:
        <xmlelement>anchor</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>navref</xmlelement>, and
        <xmlelement>reltable</xmlelement>. </p>
      <p>We usually think of maps as representing complete publications or as defining a
        subcomponent of a publication, such as a complete chapter or part or set of related tasks
        and supporting concept and reference topics. However, maps may be used to collect topics or
        non-DITA resources for any reason, including simply to define a related set of content
        objects or to organize content objects by topic, product, subsystem, or whatever.</p>
      <p>A DITA map does not necessarily represent a thing to be published. So when we talk about
                maps and their processing we have to be careful to specify the type of thing a given
                map represents. The DITA map mechanism is very general, so you should plan to use
                specializations of maps and topic references to represent specific uses of maps.
                DITA’s built-in BookMap type is a typical example of a map specialization that
                reflects a specific purpose, in this case, book publications.</p>
      <p>The simplest map for a publication will have a <xmlelement>title</xmlelement> element that
        contains the title for the overall publication and one or more <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>
        elements that link to the topics that provide the content of the
        publication:<codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>An Introduction to Aikido&lt;/title>
  &lt;topicref href="topics/chapter-01.dita"/>
  &lt;topicref href="topics/chapter-02.dita"/>
  &lt;topicref href="topics/chapter-03.dita"/>  
  &lt;topicref href="topics/chapter-04.dita"/>
&lt;/map></codeblock></p>
      <p>In practice, your maps will usually be much more sophisticated, taking
        advantage of some or all of the features of DITA maps.</p>
      <p>Nominally, a map defines a <q>navigation tree</q> for a set of topics, that is a table of
        contents (ToC) or similar hierarchical navigation structure. However, maps can also organize
        topics non-hierarchically through sets of extended links defined in relationship tables or
        even simply collect a set of topics with no particular relationship among any of the
        topics.</p>
      <p>One map may include other maps, forming a <q>map tree.</q> The root of such a map tree is
        the <q>root map</q> and has some special processing considerations. The input to DITA
        processing is generally a root map and, conversely, a map used as the input to some process
        is, by definition, the root map for that processing instance. There is no specific property
        of a map that makes it be or not be a root map. However, most maps are intended to
        exclusively be root maps or subordinate maps. While it is possible for a map intended to be
        a root map to also be used as a subordinate map, usually a map is only useful as root or a
        subordinate map but not both. In particular, by the rules of DITA, the titles of subordinate
        maps are ignored by output processors and do not contribute to the navigation tree defined
        by the root map.</p>
    </body>
    <topic
      id="subsection_p3f_pwl_3f">
      <title>Map Components</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>map<indexterm>components of</indexterm></indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>The base map content model allows an optional
          <xmlelement>title</xmlelement>, an optional <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement>,
          and then any combination of the following base element types:<ul
          id="ul_lpz_jxl_3f">
          <li><xmlelement>anchor</xmlelement></li>
          <li><xmlelement>data</xmlelement> or <xmlelement>data-about</xmlelement></li>
          <li><xmlelement>navref</xmlelement></li>
          <li><xmlelement>reltable</xmlelement></li>
          <li><xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement></li>
          </ul></p>
        <p>In practice, <xmlelement>data</xmlelement> elements are not used within
          maps except within <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement> elements. That is, it
          is not general practice to mix topic references and
          <xmlelement>data</xmlelement> elements directly.</p>
        <p>The <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> element is the primary base element type used to
                    construct maps. Topicrefs have a processing role of either <q>normal</q> or
                        <q>resource only</q> and are <q>normal</q> by default. Normal-role topicrefs
                    that point to topics or maps establish the main <q>navigation tree</q> for the
                    map. Resource-only topicrefs do not contribute to the navigation tree. If
                    resource-only topicrefs point to topics or other resources, they establish
                    dependencies on those resources, for example, topics that contain elements to be
                    used by reference.</p>
        <p>The <xmlelement>anchor</xmlelement> element identifies points within a map
          where another map can impose additional topic references, similar to
          the conref push feature of content references.</p>
        <p>The <xmlelement>navref</xmlelement> element creates a reference to another map where the
          reference is intended to be resolved as late possible, such as by a browser or online
          delivery system, rather than during the base map processing. A typical use is in Eclipse
          InfoCenters, where the Eclipse system resolves and combines maps using
            <xmlelement>navref</xmlelement> elements in compiled InfoCenters.</p>
        <p>The <xmlelement>reltable</xmlelement> element defines sets of links among topics, effectively
          defining a <q>relationship graph</q> over some or all of the topics used by a map.</p>
        <p>The DITA vocabulary includes a map domain, <q>map group,</q> that defines a number of
                    specializations of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> that support common uses of
                        <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>. These elements are so convenient that most
                    people don’t even realize that their use is optional. Therefore, you will see
                    them in nearly all map documents.</p>
        <p>The <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement> element contains metadata. <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement>
          within <xmlelement>map</xmlelement> defines the metadata for the map as a whole and, for root
          maps, the publication as a whole (when the map is treated as a publication).
            <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement> within <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> defines the metadata for
          the topicref and, depending on the rules that apply, to any resource referenced by the
          topicref.</p>
        <p>The rules for maps include rules for propagating metadata down the map tree, down the
          topicref tree, and from topicrefs to the topics they reference.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic
      id="subsection_jtj_21m_3f">
      <title>Topic references</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>topic references<indexterm>overview
              of</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement></indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>The primary use of topic references is to point to <term>resources</term>, where a
          resource may be a DITA topic, a map, or a non-DITA object of any type, including graphics,
          websites, PDF files, etc. </p>
        <p>A topicref may point directly to a resource using the <xmlatt>href</xmlatt> attribute, or
                    indirectly using the <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt> attribute. See <xref
                        href="linking-and-addressing.xml#topic-id" format="dita"/> for details. From
                    the standpoint of the overall meaning of a given topic reference, it doesn’t
                    matter whether it uses <xmlatt>href</xmlatt> or <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt>, the
                    meaning and processing results should always be the same.</p>
        <p>The type of resource pointed to is indicated by the
          <xmlatt>format</xmlatt> attribute of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>. </p>
        <p>The value of <xmlatt>format</xmlatt> depends on the data type of the resource. For DITA
          resources, the required values are:<dl>
            <dlentry>
              <dt>dita</dt>
              <dd>DITA topics. This is the default value for <xmlatt>format</xmlatt>, since pointing
                to topics is the main use of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
              <dt>ditamap</dt>
              <dd>DITA maps.</dd>
            </dlentry>
          </dl></p>
        <p>For non-DITA resources, the convention is to use the extension or common name of the
          format, e.g., <q>html</q> for HTML pages, <q>jpg</q> or <q>JPEG</q> for JPEG graphics,
          etc. The processing of non-DITA resources is necessarily processor-specific, but most
          DITA-aware processors will understand this convention.</p>
        <p>All topicrefs have a processing role determined by the value of the
                        <xmlatt>processing-role</xmlatt> attribute. The value is either
                        <q>normal</q> or <q>resource-only,</q> with the default being <q>normal.</q>
                    A topicref with a processing-role of normal contributes to the map’s navigation
                    tree or relationship graph. A topicref with a processing-role of resource-only
                    points to a resource that is not directly part of the navigation tree. For
                    example, topics that only contain elements used by conref would be resource-only
                    topics.</p>
        <p>Another use for resource-only topicrefs is to define keys used for indirect addressing.
          The resource-only processing role allows a map to point to all the resources it requires,
          removing the need to process every topic just to determine the set of topics needed by the
          map. This is especially useful if you need to package maps for interchange, provide
          content to translators, or import or export content from a component management
          system.</p>
        <p>Finally, as with other DITA links, a topic reference has a <q>scope</q>
                        (<xmlatt>scope</xmlatt>), which indicates whether the referenced resource is
                    part of map’s direct content (<q>local</q>), is part of a closely-related map
                        (<q>peer</q>), or is a completely separate resource (<q>external</q>). The
                    default value of <xmlatt>scope</xmlatt> is <q>local.</q>
                </p>
        <p>You use <q>external</q> for things like Web pages or PDF documents that you’re linking to
                    but that you don’t produce as part of your general DITA processing. </p>
        <p>You use <q>peer</q> for documents that are part of your environment but that are
          published as separate publications. For example, the installation and operation manuals
          for a product would likely be peers. The <q>peer</q> value generally implies that
          processors should know about the peer resources and might be able to do things like
          creating working links to those resources in generated output (for example, because they
          are all published to the same website or produced as PDFs intended to be delivered
          together). The <q>local</q> and <q>external</q> scopes are pretty easy to handle: the
          resources are either part of your map or completely separate from it. The <q>peer</q>
          scope is more complicated because it brings in processor-specific processing that is
          outside the scope of the DITA specification.</p>
        <p>A scope value of <q>external</q> would normally not be used on direct topic references,
                    as it wouldn’t make much sense to include an external resource into a map. The
                    value of <q>external</q> is normally used for things like cross-references
                    inside a topic to external websites, for example, the
                    following:<codeblock>&lt;p>See <b>&lt;xref href="http://dita-ot.sourceforge.net"</b> 
<b>scope="external"></b>The DITA Open Toolkit project page&lt;/xref>
for more on the DITA Open Toolkit.&lt;/p></codeblock></p>
        <p>However, it can make sense to use <q>external</q> for key definitions that bind keys to
          external resources, such as Web
          sites:<codeblock>&lt;keydef keys="dita-ot-site"
   href="http://dita-ot.sourceforge.net"
   <b>scope="external"</b>
   format="html"
/></codeblock></p>
        <p>With a key of this form, the cross-reference could be reworked to use a key reference
                    rather than a direct URI
                    reference:<codeblock>&lt;p>See <b>&lt;xref keyref="dita-ot-site"></b> The DITA Open Toolkit project page&lt;/xref>
for more on the DITA Open Toolkit.&lt;/p></codeblock></p>
        <p>Topicrefs may contain nested topic references, by which you can
          create a structural
          hierarchy:<codeblock>&lt;topicref keyref="topic-01">
  &lt;topicref keyref="topic-02">
    &lt;topicref keyref="topic-03"/>
    &lt;topicref keyref="topic-04"/>
  &lt;/topicref>
  &lt;topicref keyref="topic-05">
    &lt;topicref keyref="topic-06"/>
    &lt;topicref keyref="topic-07"/>
  &lt;/topicref>
&lt;/topicref>  </codeblock></p>
        <p>A topicref may specify a navigation title. While
          <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> provides a <xmlatt>navtitle</xmlatt>
          attribute, it is deprecated in favor of the
          <xmlelement>navtitle</xmlelement> subelement, which goes in the
          <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement> child of topicref.  The
          <xmlatt>navtitle</xmlatt> attribute, being an attribute, cannot
          contain any markup and many translation tools do not allow, or make it
          difficult, to modify the contents of attributes.</p>
        <p>A topicref with a navigation title looks
          like:<codeblock>&lt;topicref>
  &lt;topicmeta>
    <b>&lt;navtitle>Some Topic Heading&lt;/navtitle></b>
  &lt;/topicmeta>
  ...
&lt;/topicref></codeblock></p>
        <p>If you want to impose a navigation title onto a topic you must specify the
                        <xmlatt>locktitle</xmlatt> attribute, otherwise the navigation title
                    specified in the map is ignored in preference to the title or navigation title
                    defined by the
                    topic:<codeblock>&lt;topicref href="some-topic.dita"
   <b>locktitle="yes"</b>>
  &lt;topicmeta>
    <b>&lt;navtitle>Some Topic&lt;/navtitle></b>
  &lt;/topicmeta>
&lt;/topicref></codeblock></p>
        <p>Here the navigation tree will use the value <q>Some Topic</q> as the title of the
                    referenced topic rather than the value of the <xmlelement>title</xmlelement> element
                    in that topic. The title of the topic as presented in the main content
                    presentation will reflect the value of the <xmlelement>title</xmlelement> element in
                    the topic.</p>
        <p>In addition to linking to topics, maps, or non-DITA resources,
          topicrefs can do the following things:<ul
          id="ul_44n_jkn_3f">
          <li>Create titled groups of topicrefs (<q>topic heads</q>)</li>
          <li>Create untitled groups of topicrefs (<q>topic groups</q>)</li>
          <li>Define sets of topicrefs intended to be used by reference from
            other maps (<xmlelement>topicset</xmlelement>)</li>
          <li>Impose sets of topicrefs onto maps
            (<xmlelement>anchorref</xmlelement>)</li>
          <li>Bind keys used for indirect addressing to resources (<q>key definitions</q>)</li>
          </ul></p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic
      id="subsection_zkz_312_kf">
      <title>Topicref Configuration Attributes</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>attributes<indexterm>topicref
              configuration</indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>format</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>keys</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>href</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>linking</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>scope</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>type</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>audience</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>importance</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>otherprops</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>platform</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>print</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>product</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>props</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>rev</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>status</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>collection-type</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>locktitle</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>processing-role</xmlatt></indexterm><indexterm><xmlatt>toc</xmlatt></indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>topic references<indexterm>configuration attributes
              of</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement></indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>Topicref elements take a number of attributes. These can be
          classified as follows:<ul
          id="ul_23p_k12_kf">
          <li>Linking and addressing attributes: <xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt>,
            <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt>, <xmlatt>format</xmlatt>,
            <xmlatt>href</xmlatt>, <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt>,
            <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt>, <xmlatt>linking</xmlatt>,
            <xmlatt>scope</xmlatt>, and <xmlatt>type</xmlatt>. These attributes
            serve to define or characterize the resource the topicref links to,
            if any.</li>
          <li>Selection attributes: <xmlatt>audience</xmlatt>,
            <xmlatt>importance</xmlatt>, <xmlatt>otherprops</xmlatt>,
            <xmlatt>platform</xmlatt>, <xmlatt>print</xmlatt>,
            <xmlatt>product</xmlatt>, <xmlatt>props</xmlatt> and its
            specializations, <xmlatt>rev</xmlatt>, and
            <xmlatt>status</xmlatt>.</li>
          <li>Topicref configuration attributes: <xmlatt>collection-type</xmlatt>,
                                <xmlatt>locktitle</xmlatt>, <xmlatt>processing-role</xmlatt>, and
                                <xmlatt>toc</xmlatt>. These configure how the topicref behaves
                            either with respect to its peer topicrefs and the map it’s part of or
                            with respect to the resource it references.</li>
          </ul></p>
        <p>The linking and addressing attributes are covered in the sections on linking and
          addressing. The selection attributes are covered in the sections on conditional
          processing. The <xmlatt>locktitle</xmlatt> attribute is covered in the section on metadata
          cascade.</p>
        <p>The <xmlatt>processing-role</xmlatt> attribute indicates whether the resource pointed to
          by the topicref is part of the main navigation tree or navigation graph (<q>normal</q>) or
          if it acts as a resource used by other topics or topicrefs via key reference
            (<q>resource-only</q>). See <xref href="#subsection_sgl_z2n_3f" format="dita"/>.</p>
        <p>The <xmlatt>collection-type</xmlatt> attribute indicates what, if any, relationship
          exists among topics referenced directly by the topicref that contains the
            <xmlatt>collection-type</xmlatt> attribute or any included topicrefs.<dl>
            <dlentry>
              <dt>unordered</dt>
              <dd>There is no significance to the order of the topics and no implicit relationship
                among them. In particular, there is no expectation or requirement to generate
                previous and next topic links between the topics. This is the default value.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
              <dt> sequence </dt>
              <dd>The order of the topics is significant and they explicitly represent a sequence or
                reading order. Processors usually generate previous and next links or otherwise
                ensure that the sequence is apparent and navigable.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
              <dt>choice</dt>
              <dd>Indicates that one of the topics out of the set should be chosen. The way this
                                choice is made is processor dependent. For example, you might match
                                selection attributes, such as experience level, with values
                                specified by the reader. The main point of <q>choice</q> is to
                                indicate that only one of the set should be presented to a given
                                reader.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
              <dt>family</dt>
              <dd>Indicates that each of the referenced topics is closely related to each of the
                others. This is usually represented by having <q>related links</q> from each member
                of the set to every other member of the set.</dd>
            </dlentry>
          </dl></p>
        <p>Note that the meaning of <xmlatt>collection-type</xmlatt> when
          specified on <xmlatt>reltable</xmlatt> and <xmlatt>relcolspec</xmlatt>
          is undefined and should not be taken as cascading to topicrefs within
          relationship table cells.</p>
        <p>The <xmlatt>toc</xmlatt> attribute indicates whether or not the topicref should
          contribute to the navigation table of contents. A value of <q>no</q> indicates it should
          not contribute, a value of <q>yes</q> that it should. The default is yes.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic
      id="subsection_1bg_1fn_3f">
      <title>Specializations of Topicref</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>topic references<indexterm>specializations
              of</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicsetref</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicset</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>mapref</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topichead</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicgroup</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>keydef</xmlelement></indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>Most of the different uses of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> have a
          corresponding specialization provided by the DITA-defined map group
          domain<indexterm>vocabulary module<indexterm>map group
          domain</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>map<indexterm>map group
          domain</indexterm></indexterm> vocabulary module:<ul
          id="ul_3dv_v1m_3f">
          <li><xmlelement>topicsetref</xmlelement>: References a
            <xmlelement>topicset</xmlelement> in order to use the topic set by
            reference.</li>
          <li><xmlelement>mapref</xmlelement>: References another map. Sets the
            default value for the <xmlatt>format</xmlatt> attribute to
            <q>ditamap.</q></li>
          <li><xmlelement>topichead</xmlelement>: Represents a titled group of
            topicrefs within the map. Requires a title but does not allow a
            reference to a resource. Topic heads contribute to the navigation
            tree of the map. Any normal-role <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> element
            that has a title but no resource reference acts as a topic
            head.</li>
          <li><xmlelement>topicgroup</xmlelement>: Represents an untitled group of
            topicrefs. Topic groups never contribute to the navigation tree,
            even if they have titles. Any topicref with no resource reference
            and no title acts as a topic group. The specialized element type
            <xmlelement>topicgroup</xmlelement> has the additional rule that even if
            it does have a title, it still acts as a topic group and not a topic
            head. This lets you use the <xmlelement>topicgroup</xmlelement> element to
            organize topicrefs for whatever purpose and give those groups titles
            that are meaningful for authors, without affecting the navigation
            tree. For example, I often use <xmlelement>topicgroup</xmlelement> in this
            way to organize groups of key definitions.</li>
          <li><xmlelement>keydef</xmlelement>: Defines a key definition. Requires the
            <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt> attribute and sets the default value for the
            <xmlatt>processing-role</xmlatt> attribute to <q>resource-only.</q>
            (See <xref
            href="linking-and-addressing.xml#topic-id"
            format="dita"/>).</li>
          </ul></p>
        <p>A common use of specialization is to define new topicref types that reflect specific
          publication structures. For example, the DITA BookMap map type defines topicref types like
            <q>chapter</q> and <q>part</q> and the DITA for Publishers publication map domain
          defines topicref types like <q>dedication,</q>
          <q>article,</q> and <q>front-cover.</q></p>
        <p>The use of specialized topicrefs lets you impose publication-specific
          semantics onto otherwise generic
          topics<indexterm>topic<indexterm>generic</indexterm></indexterm>. For
          example, if you use a <xmlelement>chapter</xmlelement> topicref to point to
          a generic <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> topic or to a
          <xmlelement>concept</xmlelement> topic, you are saying explicitly that, in
          the context of this publication, the generic topic is playing the role
          of <q>chapter.</q> Processors can then apply chapter style and
          processing to the topic.</p>
        <p>This is an important use of topicrefs because it creates a clear and complete separation
                    between the concern of information typing—for example, concept, task, and
                    reference—and publication structure—part, chapter, subsection, appendix, etc. In
                    particular, you don’t necessarily have to change the element type of a topic
                    simply to use it in an new context where it is playing a different structural
                    role. For example, the same concept might be a chapter in one publication, an
                    appendix in another, and subsection in yet another. The topic itself doesn’t
                    change, only the way it is used.</p>
        <p>Because the processing and presentation implications of a given topicref or topic are
                    necessarily a matter of style and details of a particular output type, the
                    precise implications of the combination of topicref type and topic type are, of
                    course, processor specific. However, in general, you should expect the tagname
                    of the topicref element to take precedence over the topic type when determining
                    structural role within a publication, except for generic
                        <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> elements. </p>
        <p>In the purest use of DITA, topics always reflect an information type that says nothing
          about its possible structural role (e.g., <q>concept,</q>
          <q>task,</q> and <q>reference</q>), leaving it to maps to define structural roles. In
          practice, not all topics are quite so pure. For example, the DITA for Publishers
          vocabulary includes topic types like <q>chapter</q> and <q>part</q> largely because
          Publishing users coming to XML for the first time or coming from non-DITA XML applications
          expect to find those topic types. Over time, as their sophistication grows, they would
          likely move to topic types that are more descriptive of the content and less descriptive
          of their original structural roles. DITA for Publishers also provides the topic type
            <q>division,</q> which represents a titled publication component with no inherent
          structural role.</p>
        <p>Specializations of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> are fairly easy to define because usually
                    all you’re doing is changing the tagname and not modifying the base content
                    model or attributes at all.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic
      id="subsection_sgl_z2n_3f">
      <title>Topicrefs, Navigation Trees, and Navigation Graphs</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>topic references<indexterm>as navigation
              trees</indexterm><indexterm>as navigation
              graphs</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm>navigation tree</indexterm>
            <indexterm>navigation graph</indexterm>
            <indexterm>relationship table</indexterm>
            <indexterm>map<indexterm>navigation tree in</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>map<indexterm>navigation graph in</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>map<indexterm>relationship table
              in</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>extended links</indexterm>
            <indexterm>link<indexterm>extended</indexterm></indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>The concepts of <q>navigation tree</q> and <q>navigation graph</q> are not formally
          defined in the DITA specification through DITA 1.2, but they are inherent in the
          distinction between normal and resource-only topic references and between topicrefs
          outside of relationship tables and inside relationship tables. The DITA 1.2 specification
          uses the term <q>navigation tree</q> but does not formally define it. The term
            <q>navigation graph</q> is not used in the DITA 1.2 specification.</p>
        <p>Before DITA 1.2, when the <xmlatt>processing-role</xmlatt> attribute was introduced, all
          topicrefs contributed to the navigation tree or relationship graph, meaning that a map
          existed primarily to define a navigation tree. Therefore, there was no need to formally
          define the concept of navigation tree. Because relationship tables required distinct
          markup, there was no need to define the abstraction of navigation graph.</p>
        <p>However, with the introduction of resource-only topicrefs there is now a need to talk
          about the difference between normal-role topicrefs and resource-only topicrefs and
          describe what they do. That leads to the need to distinguish the navigation tree and
          navigation graph from resource-only topicrefs.</p>
        <p>The <term>navigation tree</term> is the table-of-contents structure defined by the
          normal-role topicrefs in the map (and not within relationship tables). While DITA provides
          some markup control over how the normal-role topicrefs translate into a literal table of
          contents or equivalent navigation structure, in general there is a one-to-one
          correspondence between the normal-role topicrefs and the navigation structure produced
          from the map for maps used to produce some sort of navigable output. I have to be vague
          here because the variety of possible uses for maps is unbounded. But in practice, maps are
          mostly used to generate things like books, websites, and online help with familiar
          TOC-like navigation trees. More generally, maps are a form of <q>virtual document,</q>
          such as provided by many content and component management systems.</p>
        <p>The <term>navigation graph</term> is the set of links among topics defined in any
          relationship tables in the map. Each row of a relationship table is effectively an
          extended link (in the XLink sense), where each cell of the row represents one anchor or
          end of the link. Each cell of a row contains one or more normal-role topicrefs that link
          to the resources that act as that anchor of the link. Each column in the relationship
          table has an associated role. A typical example is a relationship table with the columns
            <q>concept</q> and <q>reference,</q> which relate concept topics linked from cells in
          the <q>concept</q> column to reference topics linked from cells in the <q>reference</q>
          column. (See <xref href="relationship-tables.xml#topic-id" format="dita"/>.) A
          relationship table may have any number of columns.</p>
        <p>The typical rendition effect of relationship table links is to generate <q>See also</q>
          links at the ends of the topics linked.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic
      id="subsection_wtz_lkn_3f">
      <title>Creating Compound Maps</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>map<indexterm>compound</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>compound maps</indexterm>
            <indexterm/>
            <indexterm><xmlatt>format</xmlatt></indexterm>
            <indexterm>topic reference<indexterm>to maps</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>anchor</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>anchorref</xmlelement></indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>The simplest map is a single XML document that contains all the topic
          references and relationship tables that define a single
          publication.</p>
        <p>But in practice, most publications are constructed from multiple maps, creating a
            <q>compound map.</q></p>
        <p>DITA defines several ways to combine maps and topicrefs together to
          construct a compound map and an effective navigation tree.</p>
        <p>The most direct way to combine maps is a map-to-map reference using a topicref with a
            <xmlatt>format</xmlatt> value of
          <q>ditamap</q>:<codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>My Publication&lt;/title>
  &lt;topicref href="chap-01.ditamap"
   <b>format="ditamap"</b>
  />
  &lt;topicref href="chap-02.ditamap"
   <b>format="ditamap"</b>
  />
&lt;/map></codeblock></p>
        <p>The referenced maps are usually referred to as <q>submaps</q> or <q>subordinate maps.</q>
          All the topic references and relationship tables in the subordinate maps are combined with
          the root map and processed together. This processing results in an effective map that can
          be represented as a new single map document. The <q>map pull</q> processing stage of the
          DITA Open Toolkit does exactly this: it processes the root map to pull in all referenced
          maps, applies the DITA rules for combining maps, and produces a single map document as a
          temporary file.</p>
        <p>You can also pull in separately-marked sets of topicrefs from a
          larger map using the <xmlelement>topicset</xmlelement> and
          <xmlelement>topicsetref</xmlelement> elements, which are both
          specializations of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>.</p>
        <p>For example, you might have a map that organizes the content for a
          number of re-usable tasks and associated concept and task topics. Each
          group of topics forms a reusable unit of structure, but for whatever
          reason it was easier or more effective to define these in a single map
          document rather than as individual maps. Such a map would look
          something
          like:<codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>Task and Related Content Topic Sets&lt;/title>
  <b>&lt;topicset id="task-01-topicset></b>
    &lt;topicref href="task-01.dita">
      &lt;topicref href="concept-01.dita"/>
      &lt;topicref href="ref-01.dita"/>
      &lt;topicref href="ref-02.dita"/>
    &lt;/topicref>
  <b>&lt;/topicset></b>
  <b>&lt;topicset id="task-02-topicset></b>
    &lt;topicref href="task-02.dita">
      &lt;topicref href="concept-02.dita"/>
      &lt;topicref href="ref-03.dita"/>
      &lt;topicref href="ref-04.dita"/>
    &lt;/topicref>
  <b>&lt;/topicset></b>
&lt;/map></codeblock></p>
        <p>From another map you can use individual topic sets using the
          <xmlelement>topicsetref</xmlelement>
          element:<codeblock>&lt;map>
  &lt;title>My Publication&lt;/title>
  ...
  &lt;topicsetref href="topicsets.ditamap#task-02-topicset"/>
  ...
&lt;/map></codeblock></p>
        <p>The processed result is that the referenced topicset is included in the referencing map.
                    Note, however, that it is not a content reference, so this map processing is
                    performed <i>after</i> any content reference processing or filtering. Processors
                    may delay resolution of topicset references if appropriate, doing the resolution
                    in the rendition system rather than as part of the output processing. Processors
                    can also treat topicset references as equivalent to referencing a map with a
                        <xmlatt>format</xmlatt> value of <q>ditamap.</q> By <q>rendition system</q>
                    I mean interactive presentation systems like Eclipse InfoCenters or online help
                    systems, where the final rendering of the content to a reader is done by the
                    rendition system, so there is opportunity for additional processing beyond that
                    applied to the DITA source.</p>
        <p>You can also <q>push</q> subordinate maps onto another map through the use of anchors and
                    anchor references. The <xmlelement>anchor</xmlelement> element defines a potential
                        <q>push</q> target within a map. </p>
        <p>You can use the <xmlatt>anchorref</xmlatt> attribute of a map or an
                        <xmlelement>anchorref</xmlelement> element to point to an anchor and impose the
                    contents of the map or <xmlelement>anchorref</xmlelement> onto the anchor. The intent
                    is that the imposition be processed as late as possible, ideally in the delivery
                    system.</p>
        <p>Finally, you can use content references with map elements just as you can with topic
                    elements. You can use pull conrefs to pull topicrefs into a map and push conrefs
                    to impose additional topicrefs into a map. However, since you can include maps
                    or individual topicrefs in maps and you have the anchor/anchorref facility, the
                    use of content references within maps is fairly rare. And because content
                    references are always processed before any semantic processing, conref offers
                    much less flexibility in controlling when map composition is done. In
                    particular, it doesn’t allow it to be done in the delivery system.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic
      id="subsection_jww_jqn_3f">
      <title>Chunking and Copy-To</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>chunking</indexterm>
            <indexterm/>
            <indexterm><xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm>attributes<indexterm><xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt></indexterm></indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>You can generate two broad classes of output from a map: monolithic single-file output
          like PDF and modular, multi-file output like HTML and online help.</p>
        <p>For multi-file outputs there is normally a one-to-one relationship between input topic
                    files and result files. That’s the obvious way to produce multi-file outputs,
                    but the DITA specification doesn't require it.</p>
        <p>Generating output files from input topics presents two potential challenges:<ol
          id="ol_cfw_35n_3f">
          <li>Using the same topic in different places in the map to result in different result
                            files.</li>
          <li>Combining multiple topics into one output file or splitting one topic into multiple
                            output files.</li>
          </ol></p>
        <p>For the first challenge, you can use the <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt> attribute of
            <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> to specify the effective topic filename for that use of the
          topic.</p>
        <p>For example, say you use a common subtask twice in the same map under different main
                    tasks, but you want each use of the task to result in a different HTML file in
                    HTML outputs. You can force this by specifying <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt> on each
                    topicref:<codeblock>&lt;map>
  ...
  &lt;topicref href="main-task-A.dita">
    &lt;topicref href="subtask-01.dita"
      <b>copy-to="task-a-subtask-01.dita"</b>/>
    ...
  &lt;/topicref>
  &lt;topicref href="main-task-B.dita">
    &lt;topicref href="subtask-01.dita"
      <b>copy-to="task-b-subtask-01.dita"</b>/>
    ...
  &lt;/topicref>
  ...
&lt;/map></codeblock></p>
        <p>Note that the value of <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt> specifies the effective <i>source</i>
                    filename, not the effective <i>output</i> filename. That’s because the mapping
                    from source files to output files is still processor dependent. The only
                    knowable thing at authoring time is the source filenames.</p>
        <p>You can use <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt> in this way to enable cross
                        references<indexterm>cross references<indexterm>using
                                <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt></indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>cross
                            references<indexterm>to specific uses of a
                            topic</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>topic<indexterm>cross references
                            to uses of</indexterm></indexterm> to specific uses of a topic by
                    putting a key on the topicref that specifies <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt>.
                    References to that key will then be reliably associated to that specific use of
                    the referenced topic and not to any other, as though you had a made a literal
                    copy of the topic in your source repository. For example, the preceding example
                    can be extended to add
                    keys:<codeblock>&lt;map>
  ...
  &lt;topicref keys="main-task-A" href="main-task-A.dita">
    &lt;topicref <b>keys="task-a-subtask-01"</b>
      href="subtask-01.dita"
      copy-to="task-a-subtask-01.dita"/>
    ...
  &lt;/topicref>
  &lt;topicref <b>keys="main-task-B"</b> href="main-task-B.dita">
    &lt;topicref keys="task-b-subtask-01"
      href="subtask-01.dita"
      copy-to="task-b-subtask-01.dita"/>
    ...
  &lt;/topicref>
  ...
&lt;/map></codeblock></p>
        <note>When you specify <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt>, you can also specify a
          short description (<xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement>) in
          <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement> within the topicref to set the short
          description of the topic as copied. Implementation of this behavior is
          optional for processors.</note>
        <p>For the second challenge, you can use the <xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt> attribute of
            <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> to indicate how the input should map to output files, and
          the <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt> attribute to specify the effective filename to use when
          constructing the output result. The <xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt> attribute can also be specified
          on <xmlelement>map</xmlelement>. When specified on a map, the <xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt> applies to
          all the normal-role topicrefs in the map.</p>
        <p>The value of the <xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt> attribute is a list of blank-delimited tokens
                    that indicate the topics to be chunked, how those topics should be split or
                    combined, and whether the result affects navigation or content.</p>
        <p>The selection options are:<parml>
                        <plentry>
                            <pt>select-topic</pt>
                            <pd>Selects just the topic referenced by the topicref, but not any of
                                its ancestor, peer, or descendant topics. This allows you to treat
                                topics that are part of larger topic documents as though they were
                                stand-alone topic documents.</pd>
                        </plentry>
                        <plentry>
                            <pt>select-document</pt>
                            <pd>Selects the entire document that contains the referenced topic.</pd>
                        </plentry>
                        <plentry>
                            <pt>select-branch</pt>
                            <pd>Selects the referenced topic and all of its descendant topics.</pd>
                        </plentry>
                    </parml></p>
        <p>The combination and split options are:<parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt>by-topic</pt>
            <pd>Splits each topic in the set of selected topics into a separate result file. This
                                lets you create multiple output files from topics that are authored
                                in the same XML document. You don’t have direct control over the
                                output filenames because <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt> only applies to
                                the result of a single-file effective chunk.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>by-document</pt>
            <pd>Combines the topics in the selected set into a single result document. This lets you
                                create a single output file from topics are authored in separate XML
                                documents. Here, <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt> should determine the
                                effective source filename of the chunk.</pd>
          </plentry>
          </parml></p>
        <p>The rendering options are:<parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt>to-content</pt>
            <pd>Indicates that the result should be rendered as a new content object in the output,
                                e.g., a new HTML file for HTML-based outputs. When the topicref is a
                                topic head, it means that the output should be as though the
                                topichead had referenced a title-only topic with the topic head’s
                                title.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>to-navigation</pt>
            <pd>Indicates that a new chunk of navigation should be created to reference the
                                specified chunk, such as a separate table of contents or set of
                                related links. If a topichead has a <xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt> value of
                                to-navigation and that topichead is the target of a cross-reference,
                                then the cross reference should go to the navigation structure
                                itself, whatever that might be in a given rendition (for example, an
                                entry in a table of contents or a node in a tree control reflecting
                                the navigation structure). The exact meaning of to-navigation is
                                necessarily highly dependent on the details of the rendition.</pd>
          </plentry>
          </parml></p>
        <p>You can use <xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt> in combination with
          <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt> to control the effective filename of
          chunks.</p>
        <p>See the section <q>Chunking</q> in the <cite>DITA Architectural Specification</cite> for
          a full explanation of chunking.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic
      id="subsection_fgv_v5d_kf">
      <title>Metadata Cascade In Maps</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>metadata<indexterm>cascade in
              maps</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>cascade of metadata in maps</indexterm>
            <indexterm>map<indexterm>metadata cascade
              in</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlelement>topicgroup</xmlelement></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlatt>outputclass</xmlatt></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlatt>href</xmlatt></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt></indexterm>
            <indexterm><xmlatt>keys</xmlatt></indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>Maps and topics may have metadata, which can be stored in attributes on those elements or
                    in a <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement> child element.Some of the metadata defined on
                    maps and topicrefs cascades or propagates down the map hierarchy to descendant
                    topicrefs and maps and, for topicrefs that point to DITA topics, to the topics
                    themselves.</p>
        <p>The rules for metadata cascade are necessarily complex. See the topic
          "Cascading of attributes and metadata in a DITA map" in the <cite>DITA
          Architectural Specification</cite> for complete details.</p>
        <p>Here is a summary of the rules:<ul id="ul_14t_rwd_kf">
            <li>Directly-specified values always take precedence over cascaded values for
              propagation within map documents and from map-to-map. For example, if an ancestor
              topicref specifies <codeph>toc="yes"</codeph> and a descendant topicref specifies
                <codeph>toc="no"</codeph>, the value specified on the descendant topicref takes
              precedence and sets the value cascaded down to its descendants, if any.</li>
            <li>Metadata on topicrefs cascades to referenced topics unless the
                                <xmlatt>lockmeta</xmlatt> attribute on <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement>
                            is set to <q>no.</q> The default value for <xmlatt>lockmeta</xmlatt> is
                                <q>yes,</q> meaning that the topicref’s metadata overrides or
                            extends the referenced topic’s metadata.</li>
            <li>All the selection attributes and topicref-configuring attributes
                                (<xmlatt>toc</xmlatt>, <xmlatt>type</xmlatt>,
                                <xmlatt>format</xmlatt>, etc.) cascade from <xmlelement>map</xmlelement>
                            to <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> and from <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> to
                                <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> within the map document.</li>
            <li>The metadata elements <xmlelement>author</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>source</xmlelement>,
                <xmlelement>publisher</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>copyright</xmlelement>,
                <xmlelement>critdates</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>permissions</xmlelement>,
                <xmlelement>audience</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>category</xmlelement>,
                <xmlelement>prodinfo</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>othermeta</xmlelement> all cascade from
                <xmlelement>map</xmlelement> to <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>, from
                <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> to <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> within the map document,
              and from <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> to referenced topic. </li>
            <li>Cascading is additive for attributes and metadata elements that allow multiple
              values. For attributes and elements that allow a single value, the value defined on
              the nearest ancestor element takes precedence. </li>
            <li>Notable attributes that do not cascade are <xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt>,
                                <xmlatt>copy-to</xmlatt>, and <xmlatt>outputclass</xmlatt>, along
                            with the addressing attributes <xmlatt>href</xmlatt>,
                                <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt>, and <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt>.</li>
          </ul></p>
        <p>In general, the metadata cascade behavior gives you the results you would expect.
                    However, sometimes you get surprising results. For example, in a publication
                    that consists of chapters or articles authored by different people, if you
                    specified author metadata in the map and did not also specify
                        <codeph>lockmeta="no"</codeph> on the map’s <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement>
                    element, the publication-level authors would also become, effectively, the
                    authors of each chapter, which may not be what you want.</p>
        <p>Another important implication of metadata cascade is in component management systems and
          search and retrieval systems, where the system may need to create a special DITA-aware
          index or <q>materialized view</q> of the maps and topics in order to provide accurate and
          fast searching on metadata imposed by maps onto topics. It also implies that you may need
          to select a specific root map before performing a cascade-aware search in order to
          establish the correct metadata context. Or search results may need to indicate which map
          imposes a specific bit of cascaded metadata onto a topic.</p>
        <p>Finally, note the utility of <xmlelement>topicgroup</xmlelement> as way to set default values
          for descendant topicrefs. For example, if you want to set the default value of the
            <xmlatt>collection-type</xmlatt> attribute to <q>sequence,</q> you can do it with a
          topic
          group:<codeblock>  ...
  <b>&lt;topicgroup collection-type="sequence"></b>
    &lt;topicref keyref="topic-345"/>
    &lt;topicref keyref="topic-143"/>
    &lt;topicref keyref="topic-261"/>
  &lt;/topicgroup>
  ...</codeblock>
        </p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</topic>
