<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Mention Elements: Term and Keyword</title>
  <shortdesc>DITA provides a general set of element types for capturing mentions of things that are often defined elsewhere in the information set and to which the mention may be implicitly or explicitly linked.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>mention<indexterm>elements for</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm><xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> element</indexterm>
        <indexterm>keywords<indexterm>as mentions</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm><keyword>term</keyword> element</indexterm>
        <indexterm>terms<indexterm>as mentions</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>In pretty much all writing, but in technical documentation especially, clearly identifying
      the mentions of things can be very important.</p>
    <p>By a <q>mentions of a thing</q> I mean an occurrence in the content of the name or other
            identifier of a specific thing, such as a person, place, part number, API construct, or
            any other abstract or real-world thing to which a name is or can be associated. For
            example, in the sentence <q>Use the ant command to run build scripts,</q>
            <q>ant</q> is a mention of a thing. A human can tell from context that it must be a
            command, but a computer can’t necessarily make that inference. Thus, you often need to
            tag mentions to indicate the kind of thing the mention is of, for example, <q>Use the
                    <codeph>&lt;cmdname>ant&lt;/cmdname></codeph> command to run build scripts.</q>
            The <xmlelement>cmdname</xmlelement> element identifies the string <q>ant</q> as a mention of
            a command name and not, for example, the name of a family of insects.</p>
    <p>DITA provides specific markup for tagging such mentions. The main DITA
      elements for tagging mentions are <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> and
      <xmlelement>term</xmlelement> and their specializations, such as
      <xmlelement>cmdname</xmlelement> and <xmlelement>apiname</xmlelement>.<fn>Meta note:
      The markup that produces the typographic distinction for the element types
      in this paragraph is an example of a specialized mention element, the
      element type <xmlelement>xmlelem</xmlelement> from the DITA for Publishers XML
      domain (and this footnote just used that element to mark a mention of
      itself. Dude. That is so wild).</fn></p>
    <p>The primary reasons for using mention elements include:<ul
      id="ul_egf_ixp_mb">
      <li>Creating typographic distinctions. For example, the XML domain used in this book’s source
                    defines the <xmlelement>xmlelem</xmlelement> element, a specialization of
                        <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement>. It enables generation of the appropriate font
                    and, in most renderings, the left and right angle brackets.</li>
      <li>Enabling you to find mentions by the type of thing mentioned. If I want to find (or more
          likely, index) all of the different element types mentioned in this document I can simply
          search for all occurrences of <xmlelement>xmlelem</xmlelement>, group them by string value, and
          report the list.</li>
      <li>Enabling implicit association between things mentioned and the definitions of those
          things. For example, in the documentation for a document type, you could implement
          automatic linking between <xmlelement>xmlelem</xmlelement> elements and their reference entries.
          This technique works when the names of the things mentioned are reliably unique or
          otherwise discriminated, but it breaks down when you can have different base names in
          different contexts, such as the same class name (<q>Element</q>) in different Java
          libraries. In that type of case, a simple name is not sufficient to determine the correct
          link target (this is one reason DITA has the keyref facility).</li>
      <li>Enabling explicit association between things mentioned and their definitions. In DITA this
          is through the use of <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt> on <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> and
            <xmlelement>term</xmlelement>.</li>
      <li>Acting as classifying metadata when used in an explicit metadata context, such as within <xmlelement>topicmeta</xmlelement>.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>Mention elements are very useful, and therefore you are likely to specialize new mention
            elements sooner rather than later (along with creating custom conditional attributes).
            If you’re writing about wangdoodlers, hornswagglers, and vermitious knids you probably
            need corresponding specialized mention elements to distinguish mentions of specific
            wangdoodler instances from specific knid instances.</p>
    <p>Fortunately, defining specialized mention elements is the second-easiest form of specialization, after attribute specialization. See <xref
      keyref="element-domain-specialization-tutorial"/>.</p>
    <p>Within the DITA vocabulary, the <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> element is the more general
            mention element, meaning essentially any mention that isn’t a term. The
                <xmlelement>term</xmlelement> element is intended for words that have, or could be
            expected to have, a glossary definition. The distinction is essentially,
                <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> is for mentions of things that could or should have
            corresponding reference topics and <xmlelement>term</xmlelement> is for things that are
            defined terms. If you are creating specialized mention element domains you will usually
            specialize from <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> unless you are explicitly creating distinct
            forms of <xmlelement>term</xmlelement>, for example, to indicate different target glossaries.
            For example, you might specialize term into <xmlelement>common-term</xmlelement> and
                <xmlelement>jargon-term</xmlelement> to distinguish terms that are defined in common
            dictionaries (and thus not in your glossary) and terms that are specific jargon that are
            in your glossary. Or you might specialize <xmlelement>term</xmlelement> to reflect the
            taxonomy or ontology the term is defined in (see the footnote on taxonomies and
            ontologies in <xref keyref="data-and-metadata" format="dita"/>).</p>
    <p>Note that the mention element for keywords in programming languages and command line interfaces is the <xmlelement>kwd</xmlelement> element defined in the Technical Content software domain. Do not confuse with <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement>.</p>
    <p>I use the term <q>mention</q> because it is general to all documentation-related information
            structuring systems, XML and non-XML. That is, all computer-based systems for authoring
            and storing content with even a modicum of semantic identification have the notion of
            mentions, or at least the ability to represent them. Think of Microsoft Word and similar
            word processing systems that are limited to essentially paragraphs and inlines. As long
            as you can have named inline styles you have what you need to create
            semantically-distinct mentions, and most people who use tools like Word for anything at
            all sophisticated will have created mention styles in exactly the way I mean here, even
            if they didn’t realize that was what they were doing. Thus mentions are a fundamental
            concept in markup design and it’s useful to have a generic term for them. The DITA
            architecture doesn’t (or didn’t before DITA 1.2) use the term <q>mention</q> in a formal
            way, but what DITA means by <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> and <xmlelement>term</xmlelement> is
            exactly what I mean by <q>mention.</q></p>
  </body>
</topic>
