<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Relationship Tables</title>
  <shortdesc>Relationship tables create extended links among topics. These links are usually
    rendered as <q>See also</q> links. Relationship tables are defined in maps.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm><xmlelement>reltable</xmlelement><indexterm>discussion
          of</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>extended links</indexterm>
        <indexterm>link<indexterm>extended</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>When a topic is authored it is impossible to know all the possible contexts in which it might
      be used. Thus, it is impossible to define within a topic all the possible links it might have
      to other topics. Likewise, a topic used in different maps may need to link to different topics
      in the context of different maps.</p>
    <p>To do this you need a link that works without modifying the topics themselves. Such a link is
      usually called an <q>extended link</q> to distinguish it from inline or <q>embedded</q> links
      like cross-references and topicrefs.</p>
    <p>An extended link consists of two or more <q>anchors,</q> where each anchor points to one or
            more resources. The link represents a relationship among the anchors and thus among the
            resources anchored. The link itself usually has a type reflecting the meaning of the
            relationship, for example, <q>married-to</q> or <q>more-information-for.</q> Each anchor
            usually has a role reflecting the role it plays within the relationship, for example,
                <q>husband,</q>
            <q>wife,</q>
            <q>spouse,</q>
            <q>base topic,</q>
            <q>supporting topic,</q> etc. Link types and roles may be more or less precise as
            needed. <xref href="#topic-id/fig-abstract-link-01" format="dita"/> shows the general
            model for extended links.</p>
    <fig
      id="fig-abstract-link-01">
      <title>Abstract Extended Link</title>
      <image
        href="graphics/abstract-extended-link.png"
        id="image_mkd_djd_kf"
        width="4in">
        <alt>Schematic diagram of an extended link showing a link object pointing to two Anchor
          objects that then each point to topic documents. The dashed arrow shows that the topics
          are related to each other.</alt>
      </image>
    </fig>
    <p>There are many ways that extended links can be modeled in XML. The DITA approach is the
            relationship table, which contains one or more extended links of the same type. Each row
            is an extended link. Each column represents one anchor role. Each cell represents an
            anchor for that row’s extended link. </p>
    <p>Each cell contains zero or more topicrefs that point to the resource(s) for that anchor. All
      the resources linked from one anchor are then linked to the resources linked from the other
      anchors in that row.</p>
    <p>A typical relationship table looks like
      this:<codeblock>  &lt;reltable >
    &lt;relheader>
      &lt;relcolspec>
        &lt;topichead>
          &lt;topicmeta>
            &lt;navtitle>Concept&lt;/navtitle>
          &lt;/topicmeta>
        &lt;/topichead>
      &lt;/relcolspec>
      &lt;relcolspec>
        &lt;topichead>
          &lt;topicmeta>
            &lt;navtitle>Reference&lt;/navtitle>
          &lt;/topicmeta>
        &lt;/topichead>
      &lt;/relcolspec>
    &lt;/relheader>
    &lt;relrow>
      &lt;relcell>
        &lt;topicref
          href="concept-01.dita"/>
      &lt;/relcell>
      &lt;relcell>
        &lt;topicref
          href="reference-01.dita"/>
      &lt;/relcell>
    &lt;/relrow>
    &lt;relrow>
      &lt;relcell>
        &lt;topicref
          href="concept-01.dita"/>
        &lt;topicref
          href="concept-02.dita"/>
      &lt;/relcell>
      &lt;relcell>
        &lt;topicref
          href="reference-02.dita"/>
      &lt;/relcell>
    &lt;/relrow>
  &lt;/reltable></codeblock></p>
    <p>This relationship table defines two extended links. The anchor roles are <q>Concept</q> and
        <q>Reference,</q> as defined by the navigation titles of the <xmlelement>relcolspec</xmlelement>
      elements in the <xmlelement>relheader</xmlelement>. In the first link, the concept anchor points to
        <q>concept-01.dita,</q> and the reference anchor points to <q>reference-01.dita.</q> In the
      second, the concept anchor points to the two concept topics <q>concept-01.dita</q> and
        <q>concept-02.dita,</q> and the reference anchor points to the <q>reference-02.dita.</q> The
      link type in this case is unspecified and is therefore the very generic <q>related-to</q> link
      type.</p>
    <p>Through DITA 1.2, relationship tables do not provide a direct way to indicate the link type
      other than by specializing the <xmlelement>reltable</xmlelement> element to indicate the link type.
      Thus, if you need to indicate different link types, you may need to establish a convention for
      using the relationship table title or metadata to indicate the link type or choose roles that
      clearly imply the link type.</p>
    <p>The relationship table establishes the links among the topics, creating a
      graph of relationships, as shown in <xref
      href="#topic-id/rel-table-graph-01"
      format="dita"/>.</p>
    <fig
      id="rel-table-graph-01">
      <title>Link Graph for A Relationship Table</title>
      <image
        keyref="link-graph-01.gv"
        id="image_ffc_yrd_kf"
        width="4in"
        >
        <alt>Shows a graph of nodes where concept-01 has two-way relationships with nodes
          "reference-01" and "reference-02", and node "reference-02" also has a two-way relationship
          with node "concept-02".</alt>
      </image>
    </fig>
    <p>There are many ways that the links could be used for navigation and information presentation.
      By default, the Open Toolkit renders relationship table links as <q>related links</q> at the
      end of each topic to which a link applies. So in this example, <q>concept-01</q> would have
      two related links, one to <q>reference-01</q> and one to <q>reference-02.</q> Topic
        <q>reference-01</q> would have one related link to <q>concept-01.</q> Topic
        <q>reference-02</q> would have two related links, one to <q>concept-01</q> and one to
        <q>concept-02.</q> And topic <q>concept-02</q> would have links to <q>concept-01</q> and
        <q>reference-01.</q></p>
    <p>Note that there is no relationship between topics <q>concept-01</q> and <q>concept-02,</q>
      even though they are both members of the same reltable cell. This is because there is no
      implicit relationship among topics referenced from the same cell in a relationship table.</p>
    <p>Another possible presentation effect would be to present the table itself
      as a set of navigable links, perhaps as an alternative to the normal table
      of contents usually associated with a map.</p>
    <p>In short, relationship tables can drive the same kinds of link-based interactions as
      technologies like RDF and XLink.</p>
    <p>If you are familiar with RDF, for example, it should be clear that a DITA
      relationship table can be restated as a set of  RDF relations. Likewise,
      it could be restated as a set of XLink extended links. </p>
    <p>Authoring relationship tables can be a challenge simply because it’s a lot of fiddly work to
            create the rows and then create the topicrefs for each cell. Most DITA-aware editing
            tools provide some support for creating the tables and links, but they may not provide
            maximum convenience. But for data sets where you need extensive interlinking and there
            is a lot of topic reuse, relationship tables are usually the only way to practically
            create and manage the links.</p>
    <p>It may also be possible to auto-generate relationship tables based on knowledge held
      elsewhere. For example, you might be able to use a product bill of materials to generate
      relationship tables among the topics that reflect the individual product subcomponents. Or you
      might be able to use associations between metadata items or full-text queries to generate
      relationship tables. There are many possibilities.</p>
    <p>Finally, note that there is no built-in way to  have relationship table
      links generate embedded links as though they were directly-authored cross
      references. There are possibly ways in which that could be done, but it
      would depend entirely on writing and editorial conventions that will be
      specific to your data sets and processing tools, so DITA does not attempt
      to standardize such a facility, at least not today.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
