<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Sections and Divisions: Organizing Topic Body Content</title>
  <shortdesc>Topic bodies may be organized into a single level of titled containers (sections) or contain hierarchies of untitled containers (body divisions). Sections may also contain hierarchies of untitled containers (section divisions).</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm><xmlelement>section</xmlelement></indexterm>
        <indexterm><xmlelement>bodydiv</xmlelement></indexterm>
        <indexterm><indexterm><xmlelement>sectiondiv</xmlelement></indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>A fundamental design rule for DITA is that hierarchies of arbitrarily titled components are
      represented using hierarchies of topics created either through maps or by directly nesting
      topics within topics in a single XML document. By <q>arbitrarily titled</q> we mean the title
      is defined in the instance by the author, rather than being an invariant title generated
      automatically.</p>
    <p>Thus, within the body of a single topic it would be wrong to have more than one level of
      arbitrarily-titled things.</p>
    <p>This rule is reflected in DITA by the <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> element.</p>
    <p>The <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> element allows <xmlelement>title</xmlelement> as a direct child,
            meaning that authors can create sections with arbitrary titles. However,
                <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> does not allow <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> as a
            descendant. This is specifically so that authors cannot create a hierarchy of
            arbitrarily titled things within a topic’s body.</p>
    <p>If authors need to create arbitrary hierarchies of titled things, they must use topics to do
      so. (General discussion of designing topic and map markup hierarchies is in Volume 2 of
        <cite>DITA for Practitioners</cite>.)</p>
    <p>Many practitioners with background in other document types often react negatively to this
            aspect of DITA when they first come to understand it. I certainly did—you can find in
            the archives of the DITA Technical Committee’s mailing list a fairly long discussion
            between me and others as to whether sections should or should not be allowed to
            nest.</p>
    <p>However, once you understand that topics are the fundamental unit of content aggregation you
      see that it is not only correct but necessary that sections do not nest.</p>
    <p>The <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> element was intended primarily for use in reference topic
            types where you have a consistent set of titled containers where the titles are
            generated (invariant). The <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> element takes an attribute,
                <xmlatt>spectitle</xmlatt>, which let’s you specify fixed or default title text
            (using a text lookup key) as part of a specialization of <xmlelement>section</xmlelement>, so
            authors don’t have to deal with titles if you don’t want them to.</p>
    <p>The <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> element was not really intended to be used in its
            unspecialized form by authors, and unspecialized use should be discouraged. In short,
            authors who use unspecialized <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> elements will soon realize that
            it doesn’t nest and become frustrated when they realize that they should have been using
            subordinate topics all along. Then, they will have to rework their content. Don’t let
            that happen.</p>
    <p>DITA also provides for arbitrarily nested <i>untitled</i> structures, which serve as the
      specialization base for defining organizational wrapper elements or modeling complex content
      structures. These structures are called <q>divisions</q> and are represented by the
        <xmlelement>bodydiv</xmlelement> and <xmlelement>sectiondiv</xmlelement> elements. The two element types
      are required to ensure that you cannot indirectly put sections within sections:
        <xmlelement>bodydiv</xmlelement> allows <xmlelement>section</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>sectiondiv</xmlelement>
      does not.</p>
    <p>Divisions are explicitly not titled, meaning they do not allow <xmlelement>title</xmlelement> in
      their content and are not intended to allow author-defined titles. They may have the
      processing effect of generating titles, but they may not have arbitrary titles, as that would
      violate the principle that <q>only topics may define title hierarchies.</q></p>
  </body>
</topic>
