<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Value Lists, Taxonomies, and Ontologies: SubjectScheme Maps</title>
  <shortdesc>The SubjectScheme map specialization provides general facilities
    for defining enumerated lists for attribute values, classification
    taxonomies, and ontologies.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>maps<indexterm>subject scheme</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>subject scheme map</indexterm>
        <indexterm>value lists</indexterm>
        <indexterm>enumerated values<indexterm>defining with subject scheme
          maps</indexterm><indexterm/></indexterm>
        <indexterm>ontology<indexterm>defining with subject scheme
          maps</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>taxonomy<indexterm>defining with subject scheme
          maps</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>RDF</indexterm>
        <indexterm>topic maps</indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>A general challenge in XML is the management of enumerated lists of values, usually for use
      in attributes. While it is possible to declare attributes with enumerated value lists, often
      the lists of values either change frequently or need to be different for different authors or
      uses of the XML. For example, for conditional processing attributes, such as
        <xmlatt>product</xmlatt>, the set of possible values is both specific to your local set of
      products and may be different for different groups within the same enterprise or even
      department. Likewise, the set of products changes constantly over time. It would be impossible
      to have a single DTD that provided value lists for different sets of users and difficult at
      best to keep the DTD up to date as the set of products changed over time.</p>
    <p>The general solution is to have a separate definition of the values and a means to use that
      definition within editors. DITA provides the subject scheme map specialization for defining
      enumerated value lists and associating them with attributes. DITA-aware editors may use such
      maps to provide value lists for attribute editing. A typical use is to define the values for
      conditional attributes. Subject scheme maps can also define taxonomies and ontologies. The
      subject scheme map vocabulary is documented in the <q>Classification elements</q> section of
      the <cite>DITA Language Reference</cite>. Please read that for a complete discussion of
      subject scheme maps with many more examples than I can provide here.</p>
    <p>For this discussion I define <term>taxonomy</term> as a hierarchical organization of subjects
      from general to specific, usually used for classification, and <term>ontology</term> as a
      graph of relationships among subjects. These are not universally-accepted definitions, but
      this is not a treatise on knowledge representation, so these definitions will work for our
      purposes here. </p>
    <p>The Linnaean taxonomy for biological classification is the textbook example of a taxonomy.
      Taxonomies are often used in documentation as subject classification schemes, website
      structures for online stores, or for faceted searching within a website. For example, an
      online bookstore may have an organizing taxonomy to classify the books they sell.</p>
    <p>An example of an ontology would be the sort of graphs popular in knowledge representation
      where you have entities like <q>Shakespeare,</q>
      <q>Richard III,</q> and <q>Play</q> and then use associations to say Richard III is a Play
      written by Shakespeare.</p>
    <p>Subject scheme maps can represent simple enumeration definitions, strict taxonomies, and
            ontologies. Although subject scheme maps can represent ontologies, the DITA architects
            are not trying to replicate or compete with other ontology and knowledge representation
            schemes such as RDF and topic maps. There is nothing that prevents you from using RDF,
            topic maps, or any other scheme for your knowledge representation needs. By the same
            token, it is possible to generate RDF assertions or topic maps from subject scheme maps,
            for example, to serve websites or other information systems. </p>
  </body>
  <topic
    id="subsection_nwb_424_lf">
    <title>Defining and Using Attribute Value Lists</title>
    <prolog>
      <metadata>
        <keywords>
          <indexterm><xmlelement>enumerationdef</xmlelement></indexterm>
          <indexterm><xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement></indexterm>
          <indexterm><xmlelement>schemaref</xmlelement></indexterm>
          <indexterm><xmlelement>attributedef</xmlelement></indexterm>
          <indexterm>attribute value lists<indexterm>defining with subject
            scheme maps</indexterm></indexterm>
        </keywords>
      </metadata>
    </prolog>
    <body>
      <p>To define attribute value lists you create a subject scheme map and use the
                    <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> element to define the values to use. You bind
                lists of values to attributes using <xmlelement>enumerationdef</xmlelement> within the
                subject scheme map. You can define the values for an attribute globally or for a
                specific element type.</p>
      <p>Editors provide different ways for authors to indicate which subject scheme to use. For
                example, the oXygenXML editor uses the currently-selected map as the source for
                values used in the attribute editor. This means you could either have a standalone
                subject scheme map or include the subject scheme map into a publication’s map,
                whichever makes more sense.</p>
      <p>You define the set of values as a subject definition and point to the subject set from
                    <xmlelement>enumerationdef</xmlelement> to bind the list to a specific attribute or
                element/attribute pair. A set of values is represented by a single
                    <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> element that contains zero or more child
                    <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> elements, one for each value. The
                    <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt> value used on each child <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement>
                defines the value to use in
                attributes:<codeblock>&lt;subjectScheme>
  &lt;title>Product Attribute Value Lists&lt;/title>
  &lt;subjectdef keys="product-set-01">
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-A"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-B"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-C"/>
  &lt;/subjectdef>
  &lt;enumerationdef>
    &lt;attributedef name="product"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keyref="product-set-01"/>
  &lt;/enumerationdef>
&lt;/subjectScheme></codeblock></p>
      <p>The values of the <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt> attributes on the <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement>
                elements are used as the allowed values for the attribute <xmlatt>product</xmlatt>,
                for example, <q>prod-A,</q>
                <q>prod-B,</q> and <q>prod-C.</q> The key associated with the parent
                    <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> is used to refer to the list as a unit from the
                    <xmlelement>enumerationdef</xmlelement> element.</p>
      <p>This is a very simple example but it demonstrates the principle. If a
                    <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> has no child <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement>
                elements, then it defines an empty list, meaning that attributes that use that list
                do not allow any value to be specified.</p>
      <p>In practice you would likely have one map that defines sets of values for different
                purposes and other maps that use <xmlelement>enumerationdef</xmlelement> to bind
                attributes to value sets as needed. For example, the example above could be
                refactored into two
                maps:<codeblock><b>Value-list-defining map value-lists.ditamap:</b>

&lt;subjectScheme>
  &lt;title>Product Attribute Value Lists&lt;/title>
  &lt;subjectdef keys="product-set-01">
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-A"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-B"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-C"/>
  &lt;/subjectdef>
  &lt;subjectdef keys="product-set-02">
    &lt;subjectdef keyref="prod-A"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-D"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-E"/>
  &lt;/subjectdef>
&lt;/subjectScheme></codeblock><codeblock><b>Enumeration-defining map:</b>

&lt;subjectScheme>
  &lt;title>My Product List Bindings&lt;/title>
  &lt;schemaref href="value-lists.ditamap"/>
  &lt;enumerationdef>
    &lt;attributedef name="product"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keyref="product-set-01"/>
  &lt;/enumerationdef>
&lt;/subjectScheme></codeblock></p>
      <p>The value-lists.ditamap now defines two different value lists from which separate subject
                scheme maps can choose as needed. Note that the second set, product-set-02, reuses
                the subject <q>prod-A</q> by making a key reference to the key <q>prod-A.</q> You
                have to do this because if you had a second <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> element
                with the key <q>prod-A,</q> that key would never be effective because the first
                definition of key within a map always wins. So the second
                    <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> would effectively be invisible. Thus, you must use
                    <xmlatt>keyref</xmlatt> to point to any subject already defined elsewhere in the
                map.</p>
      <p>That is, for a given subject identified by a given key name, that subject definition can
                occur exactly once in the subject scheme map and must be used by reference in all
                the other places where it is needed.</p>
      <p>You can define the default value for an attribute using <xmlelement>defaultSubject</xmlelement>
                within
                <xmlelement>enumerationdef</xmlelement>:<codeblock>&lt;subjectScheme>
  &lt;title>My Product List Bindings&lt;/title>
  &lt;schemaref href="value-lists.ditamap"/>
  &lt;enumerationdef>
    &lt;attributedef name="product"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keyref="product-set-01"/>
    <b>&lt;defaultSubject href="prod-B"/></b>
  &lt;/enumerationdef>
&lt;/subjectScheme></codeblock></p>
      <p>The default specified in a subject scheme enumeration is used if there
        is no default specified in the governing DTD or schema and there is no
        value specified in the document instance. In DITA, most
        potentially-enumerable attributes, such as the selection attributes, do
        not have DTD- or schema-defined defaults, meaning that defaults defined
        in subject-scheme maps should take effect in processors that support the
        use of subject scheme maps.</p>
      <p>The enumeration definition shown above applies to all uses of the
        <xmlatt>product</xmlatt> attribute. However, you can limit it to a
        specific element type by using <xmlelement>elementdef</xmlelement> within
        <xmlelement>enumerationdef</xmlelement>. For example, to use the list
        product-set-01 only on <xmlelement>table</xmlelement> elements, you would do
        this:<codeblock>&lt;subjectScheme>
  &lt;title>My Product List Bindings&lt;/title>
  &lt;schemaref href="value-lists.ditamap"/>
  &lt;enumerationdef>
    <b>&lt;elementdef name="table"/></b>
    &lt;attributedef name="product"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keyref="product-set-01"/>
    &lt;defaultSubject href="prod-B"/>
  &lt;/enumerationdef>
&lt;/subjectScheme></codeblock></p>
      <p>Note that <xmlelement>elementdef</xmlelement> only applies to the element type named, not to
                specializations of it.</p>
      <p>When defining sets of subjects to use as values, you can nest
        <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> elements to create a hierarchy. At least
        for the purposes of doing DITA-defined filtering, the implication of the
        hierarchy is that lower (more-specific) values match to higher
        (more-general) values as specified in a DITAVAL document or similar
        run-time conditional processing specification.</p>
      <p>For example, you might have products and variants within a given main product, where
                anything that applies to a product’s variant also applies to the product. You could
                model that like
                so:<codeblock>  ...
  &lt;subjectdef keys="product-set-01">
    <b>&lt;subjectdef keys="prod-A"></b>
      <b>&lt;subjectdef keys="prod-A-community"/></b>
      <b>&lt;subjectdef keys="prod-A-enterprise"/></b>
      <b>&lt;subjectdef keys="prod-A-pro"/></b>
    <b>&lt;/subjectdef></b>      
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-B"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="prod-C"/>
  &lt;/subjectdef>
  ...</codeblock></p>
      <p>For the purposes of setting attribute values, the hierarchy is treated as a flat list, for
                example, <q>prod-A,</q>
                <q>prod-A-community,</q>
                <q>prod-A-enterprise,</q> etc.</p>
      <p>For conditional processing, if the <xmlatt>product</xmlatt> value <q>prod-A</q> is set to
                    <q>include</q> and <q>prod-B</q> and <q>prod-C</q> are set to <q>exclude,</q>
                then you would expect a subject-scheme-aware processor to include elements with a
                    <xmlatt>product</xmlatt> value of <q>prod-A-community,
                    </q><q>prod-A-enterprise,</q> or <q>prod-A-pro</q> in addition to those with a
                value of <q>prod-A.</q> Or said another way, by explicitly setting <q>prod-A</q> to
                    <q>include</q> you implicitly set all the subordinate values of subject
                    <q>prod-A</q> to <q>include.</q> This ability to have hierarchical subject lists
                can make it much easier to manage and use complex conditional processing values.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic
    id="subsection_txm_gw4_lf">
    <title>Defining General Taxonomies</title>
    <prolog>
      <metadata>
        <keywords>
          <indexterm>taxonomy<indexterm>defining with subject scheme
            maps</indexterm></indexterm>
          <indexterm>subject scheme map<indexterm>defining taxonomies
            with</indexterm></indexterm>
        </keywords>
      </metadata>
    </prolog>
    <body>
      <p>Subject scheme maps are not limited to defining enumerated attribute values. They can be
                used to represent general taxonomies, whether for use with DITA-based content or as
                a convenient XML markup for taxonomies. Because <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement>
                elements are specializations of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>, they can point to
                topics or other resources. This lets you bind the definition of a subject within the
                taxonomy to supporting information, such as the documentation of the subject itself.
                For example, you might have a set of glossary entry topics that define the terms
                within a given classification taxonomy. You can create a subject scheme map to
                define the taxonomy and link each <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> to its corresponding
                glossary entry. </p>
      <p>In the case of the DITA language itself, there are reference entries for each topic type
                defined by the DITA standard. These topic types exist in a specialization hierarchy
                that reflects the taxonomic relationships of the topic types as they apply to
                technical documentation or instructional design practice. This means we can define a
                subject scheme map that formally defines the topic type hierarchy and literally
                links to the reference entries for each
                topic:<codeblock>&lt;subjectScheme>
  &lt;title>DITA Topic Type Taxonomy&lt;/title>
  &lt;subjectHead>
    &lt;subjectHeadMeta>
      &lt;navtitle>DITA Topic Types&lt;/navtitle>
    &lt;/subjectHeadMeta>
  &lt;/subjectHead>
  &lt;mapref href="urn:dita:language-reference:key-definitions"/>
  &lt;subjectdef keys="topic" keyref="topic-refentry">
    &lt;subjectdef keys="concept" keyref="concept-refentry">
      &lt;subjectdef keys="glossentry" keyref="glossentry-refentry"/>
    &lt;/subjectdef>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="reference" keyref="reference-refentry"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="task" keyref="task-refentry">
    &lt;/subjectdef>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="learningBase" keyref="learningBase-refentry">
      &lt;subjectdef keys="learningAssessment"
                  keyref="learningAssessment-refentry"/>
      &lt;subjectdef keys="learningContent"
                  keyref="learningContent-refentry"/>
      &lt;subjectdef keys="learningOverview"
                  keyref="learningOverview-refentry"/>
      &lt;subjectdef keys="learningPlan"
                  keyref="learningPlan-refentry"/>
      &lt;subjectdef keys="learningOverview"
                  keyref="learningOverview-refentry"/>
    &lt;/subjectdef>
  &lt;/subjectdef>
&lt;/subjectScheme></codeblock></p>
      <p>Note the <xmlelement>mapref</xmlelement> element that represents inclusion of the key definitions
                for the DITA language reference. Here I’m using a URN to make the point that these
                are coming from somewhere else and I’m avoiding the issue of where that is for this
                example.</p>
      <p>In this example, each <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> defines the subjects <q>topic,</q>
        <q>reference,</q>
        <q>task,</q> etc., and also pointing to the reference entry topics for the topic types.
        Given the correct key bindings for the reference entries, this map can be processed like any
        other map, and the result will be those topics formatted the same as a generic map.</p>
      <p>Note that, by default, <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> topic references have a processing
        role of <q>normal,</q> so normal map processing applied to this map will treat the
          <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> elements as if they were generic <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>
        elements.</p>
      <p>Because the <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> elements are normal topicrefs, they can have the
        usual topicref metadata, including a navigation title and a short description. For many
        taxonomies the <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt> value will be some more-or-less opaque ID, so you can
        include navigation titles to provide a human-understandable representation of the taxonomy
        item.</p>
      <p>For example, the <cite> HIPAA Health Care Provider Taxonomy Codes </cite> (<xref
                    href="http://www.adldata.com/Downloads/Provider-Taxonomy.html" format="html"
                    scope="external">http://www.adldata.com/Downloads/Provider-Taxonomy.html</xref>)
                is a taxonomy with opaque codes and human-readable values. A bit of that taxonomy
                could be represented in a subject scheme map like
                so:<codeblock>&lt;subjectScheme>
  &lt;title>HIPAA Health Care Provider Taxonomy Codes&lt;/title>
  &lt;topicmeta>
    &lt;source>http://www.adldata.com/Downloads/Glossaries/taxonomy_80.pdf&lt;/source>
  &lt;/topicmeta>
  &lt;subjectdef keys="193000000X">
    &lt;topicmeta>
      &lt;navtitle>Group&lt;/navtitle>
      &lt;shortdesc>A business entity under which one or more 
individuals practice.&lt;/shortdesc>
    &lt;/topicmeta>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="193200000X">
      &lt;topicmeta>
        &lt;navtitle>Multi-Specialty&lt;/navtitle>
        &lt;shortdesc>A business group of one or more
individual practitioners, who practice with different
areas of specialization.&lt;/shortdesc>
      &lt;/topicmeta>
    &lt;/subjectdef>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="193400000X">
      &lt;topicmeta>
        &lt;navtitle>Single-Specialty&lt;/navtitle>
        &lt;shortdesc>A business group of one or more
individual practitioners, who all practice with the same
area of specialization.&lt;/shortdesc>
      &lt;/topicmeta>
    &lt;/subjectdef>
  &lt;/subjectdef>
  &lt;subjectdef keys="201000000X">
    &lt;topicmeta>
      &lt;navtitle>Allopathic &amp;amp; Osteopathic Physicians&lt;/navtitle>
      &lt;shortdesc>A broad category grouping state licensed providers
in allopathic or osteopathic medicine whose scope of practice is
determined by education.&lt;/shortdesc>
    &lt;/topicmeta>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="207K00000X">
      &lt;topicmeta>
        &lt;navtitle>Allergy &amp;amp; Immunology&lt;/navtitle>
        &lt;shortdesc>An allergist-immunologist is....&lt;/shortdesc>
      &lt;/topicmeta>
    &lt;/subjectdef>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="207L00000X">
      &lt;topicmeta>
        &lt;navtitle>Anesthesiology&lt;/navtitle>
        &lt;shortdesc>An anesthesiologist is trained....&lt;/shortdesc>
      &lt;/topicmeta>
    &lt;/subjectdef>
    ...
  &lt;/subjectdef>
  ...
&lt;/subjectScheme></codeblock></p>
      <p>Here, each <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt> value is the taxonomic code value, the navigation title is
                the label, and the short description is the formal definition of the code. It’s hard
                to see it by just looking at the raw markup, but the taxonomy defined is:<ul
                    id="ul_mdg_kbp_lf">
                    <li>Group<ul id="ul_c2m_kbp_lf">
                            <li>Multi-specialty</li>
                            <li>Single-specialty</li>
                        </ul></li>
                    <li>Allopathic &amp; Osteopathic Physicians<ul id="ul_nqr_mbp_lf">
                            <li>Allergy &amp; Immunology</li>
                            <li>Anesthesiology</li>
                        </ul></li>
                </ul></p>
      <p>Because each subject in the taxonomy has a key, you can use references to those keys to
        build up a complete taxonomy from separate taxonomies. For example, one subject scheme map
        can include another map and augment existing subjects by adding additional subjects to them
        or by including them in new subjects.</p>
      <p>The DITA specification’s discussion of the subject scheme map type has many good examples
                and much more detail on the subject of combining schemas.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic
    id="subsection_fkr_zdv_lf">
    <title>Defining Ontologies with Subject Scheme Maps</title>
    <prolog>
      <metadata>
        <keywords>
          <indexterm>ontology<indexterm>defining with subject scheme
            maps</indexterm></indexterm>
          <indexterm>subject scheme map<indexterm>defining ontologies
            with</indexterm></indexterm>
          <indexterm>knowledge representation</indexterm>
        </keywords>
      </metadata>
    </prolog>
    <body>
      <p>For this discussion I define <term>ontology</term> as a graph of typed relationships among
                subjects. That is, more generally, the representation of knowledge about things
                using typed relationships. Subject scheme maps are capable of representing graphs of
                relationships of typed links and therefore of representing ontologies.</p>
            <p>This is not to say that subject scheme maps are necessarily capable of complete
                knowledge representation, whatever that might mean. Knowledge representation was not
                the main design goal for subject scheme maps, and they are not an attempt to
                replicate or replace other knowledge representation approaches such as RDF/OWL or
                topic maps.</p>
      <p>However, subject scheme maps do provide a DITA-specific and convenient format for
                reasonably complete knowledge representation that can be processed using the normal
                DITA processing infrastructure. So if you don’t already have some other knowledge
                representation system in place, subject scheme maps may be just the thing. At a
                minimum, they provide a way to bring knowledge represented in other ways into a DITA
                context, for example, to enable navigation of topics through associations using
                normal DITA navigation and presentation tools.</p>
      <p>If we take <xmlelement>subjectdef</xmlelement> elements as defining <q>subjects</q> in the
                knowledge representation sense, that is, named things we want to talk about, such as
                people, places, ideas, or components of a product, then a subject scheme map does
                two things: <ul id="ul_yxj_11j_yf">
                    <li>it defines a set of subjects, and</li>
                    <li>it establishes relationships among those subjects. </li>
                </ul></p>
      <p>In the taxonomy examples shown in <xref href="#subsection_txm_gw4_lf" format="dita"/>, the
                relationships among subjects are all implicitly <q>is-a</q> relationships, as
                taxonomies define type or class hierarchies where each child subject is implicitly a
                more specialized instance of its parent type (for example, <q>concept</q> is a
                    <q>topic</q>). But of course there is an unbounded set of possible relationship
                types that might exist between any two subjects.</p>
      <p>For the purposes of general data modeling there is a well-understood set of relationship
        types, and the subject scheme map vocabulary provides markup for them. Each of these
        elements represents a relationship type that applies down the hierarchy of subjects it
        contains, such that the relationship type applies to each parent/child pair in the subject
        tree descending from the relationship-defining element. This markup approach avoids the need
        to explicitly state each relationship among a large number of subjects. </p>
      <p>For example, the topic-type taxonomy example can be refined by adding the
                    <xmlelement>hasKind</xmlelement> relationship-type-defining element as a wrapper
                around the original taxonomy-defining
                subjects:<codeblock>&lt;subjectScheme>
  &lt;title>DITA Topic Type Taxonomy&lt;/title>
  &lt;subjectHead>
    &lt;subjectHeadMeta>
      &lt;navtitle>DITA Topic Types&lt;/navtitle>
    &lt;/subjectHeadMeta>
  &lt;/subjectHead>
  &lt;mapref href="urn:dita:language-reference:key-definitions"/>
  <b>&lt;hasKind></b>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="topic" keyref="topic-refentry">
      &lt;subjectdef keys="concept" keyref="concept-refentry">
        &lt;subjectdef keys="glossentry" keyref="glossentry-refentry"/>
      &lt;/subjectdef>
      &lt;subjectdef keys="reference" keyref="reference-refentry"/>
      &lt;subjectdef keys="task" keyref="task-refentry">
      &lt;/subjectdef>
      &lt;subjectdef keys="learningBase" keyref="learningBase-refentry">
        &lt;subjectdef keys="learningAssessment"
                    keyref="learningAssessment-refentry"/>
        &lt;subjectdef keys="learningContent"
                    keyref="learningContent-refentry"/>
        &lt;subjectdef keys="learningOverview"
                    keyref="learningOverview-refentry"/>
        &lt;subjectdef keys="learningPlan"
                    keyref="learningPlan-refentry"/>
        &lt;subjectdef keys="learningOverview"
                    keyref="learningOverview-refentry"/>
      &lt;/subjectdef>
    &lt;/subjectdef>
  <b>&lt;/hasKind></b>
&lt;/subjectScheme></codeblock></p>
      <p>The addition of the <xmlelement>hasKind</xmlelement> element makes it explicit that each
        descendant of the <q>topic</q> subject is a specialization of (is a kind of) topic.</p>
      <p>The relationship type elements are:<dl>
          <dlentry>
              <dt><xmlelement>hasKind</xmlelement></dt>
              <dd>Indicates that the child subjects of the containing subjects are types of (kinds of)
                  the containing subject, as shown in the topic type taxonomy example
                  above, for example, <q>topic</q> has-kind <q>concept.</q> The has-kind
                  relationship is transitive and the inverse is <q>is a, </q>that is, for
                  a has-kind hierarchy you can read up the tree as <q>is-a</q>
                  relationships, for example, <q>concept</q> is a <q>topic.</q></dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
          <dt><xmlelement>hasInstance</xmlelement></dt>
          <dd>Indicates that the child subjects of the containing subjects are instances of the
                            containing subject. For
                                example:<codeblock>&lt;hasInstance>
  &lt;subjectdef keys="vampire">
    &lt;subjectdef keys="Lestat"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="Dracula"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="Mr-Burns"/>
  &lt;/subjectdef>
  &lt;subjectdef keys="werewolf">
    &lt;subjectdef keys="LonChaney"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="EddieMuster"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="DavidNaughton"/>
    &lt;subjectdef keys="DelphineAngua"/>
  &lt;/subjectdef>
&lt;/hasInstance></codeblock><p>That
                                is, Dracula is a vampire and Delphine Angua is a werewolf.</p></dd>
        </dlentry>
        
        <dlentry>
          <dt><xmlelement>hasNarrower</xmlelement></dt>
          <dd>The contained subjects are <q>narrower</q> than the containing subjects. The DITA
              standard does not say what <q>narrower</q> means. One use might be to indicate that a
              topic about Shakespeare plays is narrower than a subject on plays in general.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt><xmlelement>hasPart</xmlelement></dt>
          <dd>Indicates that the child subjects are parts of the containing subjects. The has-part
              relationship is transitive and the inverse is <q>is part of.</q> For example, the
              structural rules for topics could be expressed
              as:<codeblock>&lt;hasPart>
  &lt;subject keys="topic">
    &lt;subject keyref="title"/>
    &lt;subject keyref="titlealts"/>
    &lt;subject keyref="abstract"/>
    &lt;subject keyref="shortdesc"/>
    &lt;subject keyref="prolog"/>
    &lt;subject keyref="body"/>
    &lt;subject keyref="related-links"/>
    &lt;subject keyref="topic"/>
  &lt;/subject>
&lt;/hasPart></codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt><xmlelement>hasRelated</xmlelement></dt>
          <dd>Represents a typed relationship among the containing and contained subjects. The
                            relationship type is defined by the <xmlatt>keys</xmlatt> attribute
                            value or the subject referenced via key reference. You can use
                                <xmlelement>hasRelated</xmlelement> to establish any relationships you
                            might need. For example, you could define marriage relationships like
                                so:<codeblock>...
 &lt;hasKind>
  &lt;subjectdef keys="relationship-type">
   &lt;subjectdef keys="married-to">
     &lt;topicmeta>
      &lt;navtitle>is-married-to&lt;/navtitle>
      &lt;shortdesc>A transitive relationship between two parties, each of which plays the
role "spouse".&lt;/shortdesc>
     &lt;/topicmeta>
   &lt;/subjectdef>
  &lt;/subjectdef>
 &lt;/hasKind>
...
 <b>&lt;hasRelated keyref="married-to"></b>
   &lt;subjectdef keyref="SamuelVimes">
    &lt;subjectdef keyref="SybilDeidreOlgivannaVimes"/>
   &lt;/subjectdef>
 <b>&lt;/hasRelated></b>
...</codeblock><p>Note
                                that in this example I’ve formally defined the relationship
                                    <q>married-to</q> within a <q>kind-of</q> hierarchy to make my
                                intent a bit more explicit. In this context, the
                                    <xmlelement>hasRelated</xmlelement> relationship functions like an RDF
                                predicate in that it is making a formal assertion about two other
                                subjects. By taking this idea as far as you need you could clearly
                                use subject scheme maps to represent knowledge to pretty much any
                                level of detail. However, as DITA maps were not designed
                                specifically for that purpose, you would need to define markup
                                specializations and metadata conventions to fully represent all the
                                details that go into representing knowledge with appropriate
                                precision and clarity.</p></dd>
        </dlentry>
        </dl></p>
      <p>Subject scheme maps are maps, which means they can contain relationship tables. You would
        naturally expect to be able to also use relationship tables to establish relationships among
        subjects, and you can. The subject scheme map vocabulary includes a specialization of
          <xmlelement>reltable</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>subjectRelTable</xmlelement>, that is intended
        specifically to establish arbitrary <i>n</i>-ary relationships among subjects. There is
        nothing special about <xmlelement>subjectRelTable</xmlelement>, except that it uses the subject
        scheme map elements exclusively. See <xref keyref="relationship-tables"/> for a general discussion of relationship tables. See the <q>Classification
          elements</q> section in the <cite>DITA Language Reference</cite> for a detailed discussion
        of subject relationship tables.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
