<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Topic Structural Patterns</title>
  <shortdesc>The primary unit of information organization in DITA is the topic. A topic is a titled, potentially-hierarchical container of content and metadata.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm><xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> element</indexterm>
        <indexterm>topic<indexterm>structural patterns</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>structural patterns<indexterm>topic</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm/>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>Topics correspond to titled divisions in other document types, for example, chapter, section,
            subsection in more traditional documentation document types.</p>
    <p>A topic must have a title—that<indexterm>title<indexterm>hierarchies
      of</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>title<indexterm>required by
      topics</indexterm></indexterm> is the only required content of a topic.
      That’s why I stress the titled aspect of topics. Topics are the only
      hierarchical titled construct in DITA. That means that if you want to
      create a titled hierarchy in a publication you must do it with topics. Any
      other way of creating a hierarchy of titled things is, by definition,
      wrong. This is why
      <xmlelement>section</xmlelement><indexterm><xmlelement>section</xmlelement></indexterm><indexterm>section<indexterm>titles
      for</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>title<indexterm>of
      sections</indexterm></indexterm> cannot nest.</p>
    <p>There are other titled elements in DITA: <xmlelement>section</xmlelement>,
      <xmlelement>fig</xmlelement>, and <xmlelement>table</xmlelement> all allow
      <xmlelement>title</xmlelement>. (Lists<indexterm>lists<indexterm>titles
      for</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>title<indexterm>of
      lists</indexterm></indexterm> allow
      <xmlatt>spectitle</xmlatt><indexterm><xmlatt>spectitle</xmlatt></indexterm>
      but not <xmlelement>title</xmlelement>.) But they are not hierarchical, meaning
      they are not intended to be nested. Lists can nest but using nested lists
      simply to get a hierarchy of titles would be misuse of the markup. Figures
      and tables cannot directly nest and should not be nested even though the
      schema cannot prevent their nesting.</p>
    <p>You might be saying <q>but I can have a hierarchy of topicheads—those are titled and they
        create a hierarchy.</q> Yes and no. Yes, you can create the hierarchy, but topicheads are
      really just a shortcut for topicrefs to title-only topics. So I maintain that such a hierarchy
      is, in fact, a hierarchy of topics. That is, there is no functional difference between a
      hierarchy of topicheads and the equivalent hierarchy of topicrefs to title-only topics. In
      fact, DITA 1.2 makes it clear that authors can indicate that processors explicitly treat
      specific topicheads this way by specifying specific <xmlatt>chunk</xmlatt> values on
      topicheads.</p>
    <p>Topics must have titles and may contain any of the following substructures after the title, in this order:<ol>
      <li><xmlelement>titlealts</xmlelement>. Contains alternative navigation or search titles for the topic.</li>
      <li><xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement> or <xmlelement>abstract</xmlelement>.
                            <p><xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement> contains a short description of the
                        topic, in general what would be the first sentence or two of the first
                        paragraph of the topic.</p><p><xmlelement>abstract</xmlelement> contains one or
                        more block-level elements that serve as the abstract of the topic and may
                        also contain a short description element.</p></li>
      <li><xmlelement>prolog</xmlelement>. Contains the metadata for the topic as a whole, including
          authorship information, classifying metadata, keywords, and index entries.</li>
      <li><xmlelement>body</xmlelement>. Contains the <i>non-hierarchical</i> content of the topic, that
                    is, the paragraphs and such that occur before any nested topics. By definition,
                    any titled elements, such as <xmlelement>section</xmlelement>, that occur within
                        <xmlelement>body</xmlelement> do not affect or contribute to the hierarchy of
                    titles the topic participates in. <p>In particular, <xmlelement>section</xmlelement>
                        elements should not be reflected in tables of contents and similar
                        navigation structures, and the formatting of <xmlelement>section</xmlelement>
                        titles should be the same regardless of the hierarchical level of the topic
                        that contains it. For example, in HTML, <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> titles
                      should always map to the same <codeph>&lt;h<varname>n</varname>&gt;</codeph>
                        element or to an HTML <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> value that will result in
                        consistent styling for all <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> titles.</p></li>
      <li><xmlelement>related-links</xmlelement>. Contains links to other resources (topics, publications, or non-DITA resources) to which this topic is related in some way. Usually intended to be generated from relationships established in maps or by other means.</li>
      <li><xmlelement>topic</xmlelement>. A topic may contain nested topics. Nested topics form a
          hierarchy of titles. There should be no functional difference between a hierarchy of
          topics created using nested <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement> elements and one created by
          directly nesting topics within a single XML document. However, even though there is
          absolutely no requirement in the DITA standard for each topic to be in its own XML
          document, some processors may treat them differently.</li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>Every topic, no matter how specialized, must reflect this pattern. Specialized topics may
      omit anything except the title and may require anything that is optional, but they may not add
      things or change the order of things. Likewise, except for nested topics, none of the child
      elements of <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> are repeatable, so you may not have a specialized topic
      that has multiple bodies or multiple abstracts, for example.</p>
    <p>If you need to have multiple distinct containers within any of the children of <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> you have several choices:<ul
      id="ul_lpm_mbo_mb">
      <li>Within <xmlelement>title</xmlelement> or <xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement> use <xmlelement>ph</xmlelement> to contain distinct text. For example, to have two different title values with different conditional attributes, you would use <xmlelement>ph</xmlelement> like so:<codeblock>&lt;title
 ><b>&lt;ph audience="beginner"></b>DITA is Fun!&lt;/ph
 ><b>&lt;ph audience="expert"></b>Getting Started with DITA&lt;/ph
>&lt;/title></codeblock></li>
      <li>Within <xmlelement>abstract</xmlelement> use multiple <xmlelement>p</xmlelement> elements.</li>
      <li>Within <xmlelement>prolog</xmlelement> use <xmlelement>data</xmlelement> to create groups of
            <xmlelement>data</xmlelement> elements.</li>
        <li>Within <xmlelement>metadata</xmlelement> within <xmlelement>prolog</xmlelement> use multiple
            <xmlelement>data</xmlelement> elements or multiple <xmlelement>keywords</xmlelement> elements.</li>
      <li>Within <xmlelement>body</xmlelement> use <xmlelement>bodydiv</xmlelement> to create separate, untitled groups of elements.</li>
      <li>Within <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> within <xmlelement>body</xmlelement> use <xmlelement>sectiondiv</xmlelement> to create separate, untitled groups of elements. See <xref
        href="sections-and-divs.xml#topic-id"
        format="dita"/>.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>There are many schools of thought about the <q>right</q> rhetorical use of topics. The
      discussion here is concerned only with the markup rules. </p>
    <p>What is appropriate rhetorically depends entirely on the nature of the information and the
      purpose of the publications that use it. Whether you use a strict minimalist and modular
      approach or treat DITA as though it were a markup language for narrative documents is entirely
      a matter of local policy. The DITA standard does not require the former nor disallow the
      latter. Depending on the circumstances, topics consisting of nothing but titles are just as
      sensible and correct as topics with deeply nested subtopics in a single document. There is no
      DITA-defined requirement that each topic be a separate XML document, although that is a fairly
      typical practice.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
