<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Topic Constraint Module Step 2: Declare The <xmlatt>domains</xmlatt> Attribute Text Entity</title>
  <body>
    <p>Like vocabulary modules, constraint modules must be declared in the <xmlatt>domains</xmlatt> attribute of each top-level map or topic file that uses the constraint.</p>
    <p>Constraint modules are indicated by names of the form <q><varname>moduleName</varname>-c,</q>
            for example, <q>highlightOnlyTopic-c.</q> As for vocabulary modules, you declare a text
            entity that holds the <xmlatt>domains</xmlatt> attribute contribution. This entity is
            named <q><varname>tagname</varname>-constraints,</q> reflecting the fact that there can
            be at most one constraint module for a given element type in a given document type
            shell.</p>
    <p>For the highlight-only constraint module, add the declaration shown to the
                <filepath>highlightOnlyTopicConstraint.mod</filepath>
            file:<codeblock>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
&lt;!-- ======================================
     Constraint Domain: Paragraphs with
     only highlight domain elements.
     
     Copyright (c) 2011 Your Name Here
     
     ====================================== -->

<b>&lt;!ENTITY topic-constraints "(topic highlightOnlyTopic-c)" ></b>
     
&lt;!-- ============ End of constraint module --></codeblock></p>
    <bodydiv
      outputclass="what-about">
      <p
        outputclass="what-about-question">What do you do if you have multiple constraint modules for a given element type that you want to use together? </p>
      <p>In that case you must create a new constraint module that combines the multiple constraint
                modules. For example, if someone gave you another topic constraint module that
                constrained a different element type, you would combine those declarations with the
                declarations in the highlight-only topic constraint module.</p>
      <p>When the two constraints constrain different element types, then combining them is easy:
                just copy all the declarations from one constraint module into the other and save
                the result as a new file with a new module name.</p>
      <p>If the constraints constrain the same element types, then you must work out how the
                constraints should be combined in order to create a new constraint module.</p>
    </bodydiv>
  </body>
</topic>
