<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Configuring and Extending the DITA Open Toolkit</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>Open Toolkit<indexterm>extending</indexterm><indexterm>configuring</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>tools, open-source<indexterm>DITA Open Toolkit</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>The DITA Open Toolkit serves as the primary reference implementation of DITA processing (it does not address editing or component management). Even if your users will be using a system that does not involve the Open Toolkit you still need to use it yourself if only for testing of new markup designs.</p>
    <p>But most DITA users will be using systems that integrate or use the Open Toolkit in one way or another. Therefore, as a DITA Practitioner you must have at least some familiarity with the Toolkit. But it is likely that a large part of your task as a system developer or maintainer will be to develop and maintain components of the Toolkit itself.</p>
    <p>This chapter is intended to give you a general understanding of the Open Tookit: how it works, how to run it, how to configure it. It is not a tutorial on how to extend or customize specific transformation types. See <cite>[Reference to Leigh's book]</cite> for more detailed discussion of how to customize and extend the Open Toolkit.</p>
  </body>
  <topic
    id="ss1">
    <title>The Architecture of the Open Toolkit</title>
    <shortdesc>The Open Toolkit is a sequence of independent processors applied in a (logical) pipeline that serve to perform both generic and ouput-specific processing on DITA documents. The Toolkit enables extension through a general plugin mechanism.</shortdesc>
    <topic
      id="ss11">
      <title>Major Components of the Open Toolkit</title>
      <body>
        <p>FIXME: Write this section.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic
      id="ss12">
      <title>Understanding The Toolkit's Extension and Integration Facility</title>
      <shortdesc>The Toolkit enables plugins through an integration facility that manages dependencies among plugins and automates the literal integration of new components with existing components.</shortdesc>
      <body>
        <p>FIXME: Write this section</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic
      id="ss13">
      <title>Understanding the Toolkit's General-Purpose Preprocessing Features</title>
      <body>
        <p>FIXME: Write this section.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic
    id="subsection_lwe_zag_id">
    <title>Configuring Open Toolkit Plugins</title>
    <shortdesc>This section describes how to define and configure Open Toolkit plugins.</shortdesc>
  </topic>
  <topic
    id="ss2">
    <title>Plugins for Vocabulary and Constraint Modules ("doctype plugins")</title>
    <shortdesc>Because the toolkit manages a master entity resolution catalog, packaging your vocabulary modules as Toolkit plugins makes deploying custom vocabulary and constraint modules easy and convenient.</shortdesc>
    <body>
      <p>FIXME: Write this section.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic
    id="ss3">
    <title>Plugins That Extend Other Transformation Types</title>
    <shortdesc>Most Toolkit transformation types enable unilateral extension by other plugins.</shortdesc>
    <body>
      <p>FIXME: Write this section.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic
    id="ss4">
    <title>Plugins That Provide New Transformation Types</title>
    <shortdesc>You can extend the Toolkit by implementing new transformation types.</shortdesc>
    <body>
      <p>FIXME: Write this section.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic
    id="ss5">
    <title>Implementing Map-Driven XSLT Processing</title>
    <shortdesc>Using XSLT 2 and taking advantage of the Toolkit's preprocessing, it is relatively easy to implement sophisticated map-driven processing.</shortdesc>
    <body>
      <p>FIXME: Write this section. Use the example of a process that produces a report of all the graphics used in a map and which topics use them.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
