<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Map Specialization Tutorial</title>
  <shortdesc>Goal: Define a new map type that represents an FAQ publication.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>tutorial<indexterm>map specialization</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>specialization<indexterm>of maps</indexterm><indexterm>tutorials<indexterm>map</indexterm></indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>tutorials<indexterm>structural specialization<indexterm>map</indexterm></indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>FAQ<indexterm>map type for</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>Having defined a new topic type for FAQ questions (<xref
      href="../topic-specialization/topic-specialization-tutorial.xml#topic-specialization-tutorial"
      format="dita"/>), we can now define a corresponding map type for creating complete FAQ sets.</p>
    <p>New map types are used to either represent specific types of publications (what most people
            would call a <q>document type</q> in the generic sense, not the XML sense) or to
            represent specific combinations of topic types. For example, a common pattern is to
            combine a task with associated concept and reference topics into a single unit. It could
            be useful to define a separate map type that codifies this structure<fn><xref
                    href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/xml/library/x-dita7/" format="html"
                    scope="external">Design patterns for information architecture with DITA map
                    domains</xref>, Erik Hennum, Don Day, John Hunt, and Dave Schell, September
                2004, <xref href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/xml/library/x-dita7/"
                    format="html" scope="external"
                    >http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/xml/library/x-dita7/</xref>. </fn></p>
    <p>For this tutorial, we want to define frequently asked question publications that consist of
            FAQ question topics.</p>
    <p>While you could do this by defining a new map type that defined topicref types specifically
            for organizing FAQ entries, in practice it is usually better to define new topicref
            types as map domains so they can be used in any map type. If you still want a specific
            map type you can define a map type that depends on the new map domain in order to define
            appropriately-constrained content models.</p>
    <p>The Learning and Training learningMapDomain and learningMap modules are a good example of this approach. The learningMap domain lets you use learning-specific topicrefs in any map type while the learningMap gives you a ready-to-use map specifically for learning content. The DITA for Publishers vocabulary takes the same approach with the publication map domains and pubmap map types.</p>
    <p>Thus, this tutorial defines two vocabulary modules:<ul
      id="ul_c6875872-d469-4d13-aa23-590a3a717f23">
      <li>An FAQ map domain that defines new topic types for organizing sets of FAQ entries</li>
      <li>An FAQ map type that uses the map domain to define a map that is exclusively an FAQ set.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>To implement the domain and the map type that uses it, we could start by defining the map
            domain and then defining the map type that uses it. However, the principle of
            test-driven development suggests that we start with the map type and work toward
            implementing the map domain. </p>
  </body>
</topic>
