<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="class-attributes">
  <title>Specialization Hierarchy and the <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> Attribute</title>
  <prolog>
    <author>W. Eliot Kimber</author>
    <copyright>
      <copyryear year="2007"/>
      <copyrholder>W. Eliot Kimber</copyrholder>
    </copyright>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>In DITA, a given specialized element may be specialized from elements that
        are themselves specializations of more general elements, forming a 
        specialization hierarchy. Syntactically, this hierarchy is expressed 
        as a sequence of module/type name pairs as the value of the global <xmlatt>class</xmlatt>
        attribute. In DITA-based document types, all element types must have
        a <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> attribute and must be ultimately specialized 
        from one of the base DITA-defined types.</p>
    <p>The value of the <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> attribute is a blank-delimited 
          sequence of module/element name pairs, preceded by a "-" or "+" and followed
        by a trailing blank character:
        <pre>
&lt;!ATTRIBUTE foo
    <b>class="+ topic/ph mydomain/foo "</b>
&gt;
&lt;!ATTRIBUTE bar
    <b>class="- topic/p concept/p mytopic/my-p "</b>
&gt;</pre>
    </p>
    <p>The leading "+" or "-" and the trailing blank ensure that processors can 
    reliably match on the module/name pairs.</p>
    <p>A leading "-" is used for topic or map specialization modules, a "+" is
        used for domain specialization modules.</p>
    <p>When a specialized type specializes a type that is not specialized by 
    intermediate specializations, the intermediate specializations must still
    be listed. In the second example, the topic specialization module "mytopic"
    specializes the <xmlelement>p</xmlelement> element, which is defined in the base topic
    module. Even though the <xmlelement>p</xmlelement> element is not further specialized
    by the concept module, it is listed in the class value. This makes
    it easy for processors to know exactly what the module hierarchy
    is for any specialized element should that information be useful.</p>
    <p>All DITA-aware processing should be defined in terms
            of the <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> attribute values rather than tag names.
        For example, in an XSLT match
        statement you would do this:
        <pre>
&lt;xsl:template match="*[contains(@class, <b>' mydomain/foo '</b>)]"&gt;</pre>
    </p>
    <p>The leading and trailing spaces in the match string ensure that you only match
        the specific string you want and not one that happens to also match if you 
        omitted the spaces. For example, if you defined a module named "mytopic" which
        declared the element "p-norm", a match string of "topic/p" would match both
        "topic/p" and "mytopic/p-norm", while a match string of " topic/p " would
        only match "topic/p".</p>
    <p>The <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> attribute allows processors to process elements
        in terms of any element type in its specialization hierarchy. This means that
        all specialized elements, when processed by specialization-aware processors,
        will always get the default behavior for their base types. This means that
        you can declare specialized element types without necessarily having to 
        do any additional implementation work to support the processing of those elements.
        That is, documents with specialized elements should "just work" when processed
        by generic DITA-aware processors (e.g., the DITA Open Toolkit). Of course,
        not all tools that claim to support DITA are specialization aware so your
        mileage may vary. Certainly the DITA Open Toolkit is fully specialization
        aware.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
