<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="domains-and-topic-types">
  <title>Domains and Topic Types</title>
  <prolog>
    <author>W. Eliot Kimber</author>
    <copyright>
      <copyryear year="2007"/>
      <copyrholder>W. Eliot Kimber</copyrholder>
    </copyright>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>DITA recognizes a general fact about document types for technical documentation, namely
        that there are two distinct classifications of elements: document-level structures and
        paragraph-and-phrase-level elements (or sometimes, "blocks and phrases").</p>
    <p>Document-level structures define the organizational and hierarchical structure of
        entire documents, i.e., book goes to chapter, chapter goes to title plus subsections,
        subsections go to title plus paragraphs, etc. Different types of documents will have 
        different structural and organizational rules and requirements.</p>
    <p>Block-level elements are the elements that go in the bodies of topics. 
          These are elements that more or less can occur wherever paragraphs
        can occur. They may also define more complex structures within the topic body (tables, 
        lists, etc.).</p>
    <p>Phrase-level elements are the elements that go in paragraphs (or more generally,
        into "blocks") and are used to either identify mentions of specific things (terms,
        programming keywords, etc.), create links (cross-references, etc.), or produce
        some sort of formatting effect (bold, italic, etc.). The set of phrase-level elements
        you need is usually independent of the higher-level document structures. That is,
        whether you're writing a service manual or a novel, you probably need the same
        basic set of phrase-level elements.</p>
    <p>In DITA, this distinction is formalized into topic types and domains (leaving aside maps
        for the moment, which do not directly contain any content).</p>
    <p>In DITA, <term>topics</term> are the top-level unit of document structure. 
          All DITA content is contained within one or more topics. It is
        the different topic types that define specific document-level structures.</p>
    <p>In DITA, <term>domains</term> define sets of elements that are specific to particular
          subject area or specific application or type of thing to be documented. For example,
          the base DITA domains include the base "highlight" and "utility" domains, which are
          very generic and will be useful for almost any DITA document, as well as the 
          subject-specific domains "programming", "user interface", and "software", which
          provide phrase-level elements for talking about programming language constructs,
          user interface components, and software components, respectively.</p>
    <p>Domains may be used with any topic type.</p>
    <p>In terms of the DITA specialization architecture, topics and domains form two
        distinct axese or dimensions of element types that can be combined together to 
        form different concrete document types (<term>shell document types</term>).</p>
    <p>For example, if you are writing documentation for a software program, you probably don't
        need a specialization of the concept topic type but you probably do need to
        use the programming domain within those concept topics. But if you are writing
        the reference documentation for Java classes, you might want to have a specialization
        of the reference topic type that is specific to Java classes and that also uses
        the programming domain.</p>
    <p>In essence, domains can be "mixed in" to any topic types to provide phrase-level
        elements specific to the subject (or "information domain") you're writing about.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
