<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="types-of-specialization">
  <title>The Types of Specialization</title>
  <prolog>
    <author>W. Eliot Kimber</author>
    <copyright>
      <copyryear year="2007"/>
      <copyrholder>W. Eliot Kimber</copyrholder>
    </copyright>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>The DITA architecture defines three types of specialization:
          <ul>
        <li>Structural specialization (topics and maps)</li>
        <li>Domain specialization</li>
        <li>Domain attribute specialization</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>Structural specializations declare new top-level topic types and map types. You use structural 
          specializations to define entirely new document structures. With structural specializations,
    you can specialize any base element type, including <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> and <xmlelement>map</xmlelement>,
    as well as elements in any topic or map specialization.</p>
    <p>Domain specializations define new elements that can be used within any topic or map types. Note that
        the map-specific elements <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>topichead</xmlelement>, and 
          <xmlelement>topicgroup</xmlelement> are defined as domain elements, even though you might expect
        them to be part of the base map type. Thus, defining specializations of <xmlelement>topicref</xmlelement>
          or <xmlelement>topichead</xmlelement> is domain specialization, not map specialization. Using domain
      specializations, you can specialize any base DITA element that is an allowed descendant of <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement>
      or <xmlelement>map</xmlelement> or any element in any other domain module.
        </p>
    <p>Domain attribute specializations define new <i>global</i> base attributes or new <i>global</i> property (conditional processing)
        attributes. You use attribute specializations most often to define new property attributes that
        reflect conditions specific to your documents and business processes.</p>
    <p>While the basic syntactic mechanisms are the same for all the types of specialization, domain 
        specializations are easier to define and integrate than structural specializations, simply because
    they can be as simple as specializing to create a single new element type, while topic and map specializations require you
    to specialize a number of element types, account for more complex content models,
      and generally require more up-front design effort than the typical domain specialization.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
