<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="chapter-id">
  <title>Introduction to the Configuration and Extension Tutorials</title>
  <shortdesc>This section provides tutorial examples for creating DITA configuration and extension
    components, with a focus on the mechanics, not the concepts.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>DITA defines a set of DTD and XSD coding requirements that all conforming vocabulary modules
      should follow. These requirements serve several important purposes:<ul>
        <li>Consistency of implementation across modules</li>
        <li>Smooth interchange of knowledge</li>
        <li>Smooth interchange of vocabulary components</li>
        <li>Ease of implementation</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>Some of the DITA-imposed requirements come from the syntax and semantics of DTDs and XSDs,
      others are simply arbitrary decisions that had to be made and, having been made, make
      replication easy.</p>
    <p>In short, once you learn the basic rules for how to organize the components of a vocabulary
      module, constraint module, or document type shell, you will understand the markup details of
      any conforming DITA module. You will also be able to quickly create new components because
      this is largely an exercise in copying, pasting, renaming, and deleting what you don't
      need.</p>
    <p>You don't have to worry about how you'll structure and organize your DTD declarations or
      schema components. You won't have to work out clever schemes for modularity or
      conditionality.</p>
    <p>You do need to have a basic understanding of either DTD or XSD syntax, depending on which you
      choose for your vocabulary modules. These tutorials tell you exactly what to type, so you can
      do them even if you don't have a working understanding of DTD or XSD syntax, but you will
      eventually need to know why you're doing what you're doing.</p>
    <p>You should also, at some point, read the <q>Configuration, specialization, and
        constraints</q> section of the <cite>DITA Architectural Specification</cite>, which defines
      the implementation requirements reflected in these tutorials.</p>
    <p>These tutorials are not intended to give you a deep conceptual understanding of how
      vocabulary modules work, they're intended to make it possible for you to create your own
      before you fully understand why they work they way they do. One of the cool parts of DITA is
      that you can do that. </p>
    <p>If you follow these tutorials you should be able apply the processes demonstrated to your own
      configuration and extension requirements, assuming you've already worked out the markup
      design. A lot of specializations simply add new mention elements (specializations of
        <xmlelement>keyword</xmlelement> or <xmlelement>term</xmlelement>) or metadata elements. The easiest
      specialization to implement is an attribute domain that adds a new <xmlatt>props</xmlatt>
        specialization.<draft-comment>In the last paragraph, the first sentence is a nice seque to
        what follows, but the last two sentences seem out of place. I suggest you drop them. They
        don't add anything you haven't said elsewhere.</draft-comment></p>
  </body>
</topic>
