<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="ss6">
  <title>The Cost of Interchange Enablement and the Overall Value of DITA</title>
  <body>
    <p>There is of course no free lunch. DITA's interchange features do have a cost, namely the imposition of some general constraints and rules that are necessary to ensure the system works.</p>
    <p>In particular, a given DITA element must be at least as constrained as its immediate base
      type. This means, for example, that if the base type requires element <xmlelement>A</xmlelement>
      followed by element <xmlelement>B</xmlelement>, then any specialization of the base type must
      provide <xmlelement>A</xmlelement> or a specialization of <xmlelement>A</xmlelement> and must require it
      to be followed by <xmlelement>B</xmlelement> or a specialization of <xmlelement>B</xmlelement>.</p>
    <p>For example, because the content model for <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> requires
        <xmlelement>title</xmlelement>, all specialized topic types must also require
        <xmlelement>title</xmlelement>, or a specialization of <xmlelement>title</xmlelement>, and must require
      the title element to be the first child of the topic element.</p>
    <p>This means that markup designers do not have completely free reign to structure new markup
      designs. It also means that it will not always be possible to make an existing non-DITA
      vocabulary into a DITA vocabulary simply by adding the appropriate <xmlatt>class</xmlatt>
      attributes, because the existing vocabulary may not align structurally with the appropriate
      base DITA type.</p>
    <p>For example, the general DocBook model for titled divisions does not include an element type
      that corresponds to the DITA <xmlelement>body</xmlelement> element, which DITA requires to hold the
      direct content of topics. Thus DocBook divisions are not structurally compatible with DITA
      topics.</p>
    <p>The <q>at least as constrained</q> requirement also means that elements designed to be the
      basis for further specialization need to allow appropriate options in their own content models
      so they don't prevent reasonable specialized designs. This is why the content models for most
      of the topic elements are so loose: they have to allow a wide range of possible
      specializations. It is important to remember that the base standard types were <i>not</i>
      intended to be directly used for authoring. They were intended to be specialized or
      constrained as appropriate for specific authoring use cases. </p>
    <p>For example, while <xmlelement>body</xmlelement> within <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> allows an unconstrained mix of block elements and <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> elements, <xmlelement>conbody</xmlelement> within <xmlelement>concept</xmlelement> only allows block elements before any <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> elements. But another specialization of <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> might need to continue to allow a mix of block elements and <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> elements, so the constraint in <xmlelement>conbody</xmlelement> would be inappropriate in <xmlelement>body</xmlelement> because it would prevent other legitimate ways of organizing topic content in other specializations. </p>
    <p>It's also important to remember that DITA, while developed originally for technical
      documentation, is not specific to technical documentation and, therefore, should not reflect
      markup design decisions that reflect editorial practice specific to technical documentation.
      DITA is a completely general XML application framework and, therefore, must accommodate all
      legitimate requirements within the general constraints of enabling interchange and
      interoperation. </p>
    <p>To experienced XML practitioners the <q>at least as constrained</q> requirement may seem
      particularly onerous, or at least annoying, and it can be frustrating to realize that the way
      you would have designed a particular bit of markup in the past simply cannot work in a DITA
      context. It means that you cannot always create a blindly-literal mapping from legacy non-XML
      structures into DITA structures. You will have to work out some amount of structural
      reordering, and you will need to retrain the people transitioning from the old system to the
      new. It means you will have to learn the basic DITA structural patterns to translate
      requirements into conforming DITA markup designs.</p>
    <p>However, the important question is not about cost but about value.</p>
    <p>The value of DITA is that it <i>dramatically</i> lowers the overall cost of system
      implementation, use, and maintenance while increasing the inherent value of content by
      enabling blind interchange over the broadest possible scope. This lower overall cost far
      outweighs the direct cost of specialization, while the increase in value of DITA-based content
      increases the value of the overall system. Even if a DITA-based implementation were no less
      expensive to initially implement than the equivalent non-DITA-based system, it would still
      have greater value because the content will have greater value and the ongoing cost of
      ownership will be lower. In fact, even if initial DITA implementation were more expensive than
      non-DITA options, the added long-term value would still justify the DITA-based solution. But
      DITA-based systems are demonstrably less expensive to acquire and implement than any possible
      non-DITA solution that satisfies the same set of requirements.</p>
    <p>That is, by accepting a few constraints on your freedom to define arbitrary markup structures
      and by taking the effort to learn the basics of DITA, you can implement very sophisticated XML
      systems with lower startup and ownership costs than any non-DITA solution that satisfies the
      same requirements.</p>
    <p>Part of the point of these tutorials, and of <cite>DITA for Practitioners</cite> in general,
      is to make the necessary knowledge available so that the cost of learning what you need to
      know is also lowered. </p>
    <p>So while there is a cost to the specialization feature in terms of design constraints,
      increased complexity for specialization-aware processors, and the need for practitioners to
      learn new skills and concepts, the value returned from the investment of those costs is
      remarkable. And the value will continue to increase as network effects serve to make more and
      more DITA-aware knowledge and processing available, which means it's available to all. That
      suggests that an investment in DITA-based systems is the safest XML system investment you can
      make today.</p>
    <p>As a practitioner, I would refuse to do a from-scratch XML implementation that was not
      DITA-based because it would be a disservice to the client to do anything else, and because
      anything else would be more expensive, both in the short term and the long term, than a
      DITA-based solution. The only non-DITA-based systems I work on any more are legacy systems
      that, for business reasons, cannot be (immediately) replaced with DITA-based equivalents. And
      it is painful for me to do so, because everything that DITA makes easy is hard in these
      systems.</p>
    <p>Hopefully I've made my point, but in case I haven't, here's my position in a
        nutshell:<lq>DITA is a compelling technology not because it does cool stuff (although it
        does) but because, through the specialization feature, it <i>dramatically</i> lowers the
        initial and recurring costs of doing <i>anything</i> with XML for documents intended
        primarily for human consumption. Thus, even XML applications with the most basic
        requirements will benefit from a DITA-based solution simply because they will be cheaper,
        probably much cheaper, than any other XML-based alternative. And when you realize that you
        actually do need some of the really cool stuff DITA does, it's there waiting for
      you.</lq></p>
  </body>
</topic>
