<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>DTD or XSD?</title>
  <shortdesc>DITA vocabulary modules can be implemented using DTDs or XML schema documents (XSD). Which should you use?</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>DTD</indexterm>
        <indexterm>XSD</indexterm>
        <indexterm>redefine<indexterm>feature of XSD</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>override<indexterm>feature of XSD 1.1</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>At the time of writing, most DITA users use DTD-based vocabulary modules. However, you can use XSD-based modules if you want to or must in order to accommodate the tools you're using or the demands of a particular user community. For example, the Syntext Serna editor only uses XSDs to drive in-editor tag awareness (it can also use DTDs for validation, but not for in-editor tag awareness).</p>
    <p>Which raises the question: should I use DTDs, XSDs, or both?</p>
    <p>The short answer is <q>use DTDs unless you absolutely have to use XSDs</q> for now. This
      answer will hopefully change in the future.</p>
    <p>The reason for choosing DTDs is simple: DITA's XSDs currently depend on the redefine feature
      of XSD. Unfortunately, the definition of redefine in the XSD 1.0 specifications is ambiguous
      to the point that different conforming XSD processors will produce different results for the
      same set of XSD documents. For this reason, the redefine feature is deprecated in XSD 1.1 (at
      Candidate Recommendation stage at the time of writing). Unfortunately, as currently
      formulated, DITA's XSDs depend on one particular interpretation of redefine, the one
      implemented by the Xerces 2.x parser.</p>
    <p>This means that some conforming XSD processors consider DITA XSDs invalid and will not
      process them. This means, in turn, that you cannot reliably interchange XSD-based vocabulary
      modules and document type shells unless all of the interchange partners are using compatible
      XSD processors.</p>
    <p>However, because the Xerces parser does the right thing, and because so many tools use the
      Xerces parser (or can use it), including the Open Toolkit, and because all the major
      commercial DITA-aware editors support DITA XSDs, you can create environments where XSD-based
      DITA documents can be processed reliably. However, a schema-aware XML processor that is not
      specifically DITA-aware, may not be able to process XSD-based DITA documents.</p>
    <p>I find this frustrating because, except for the redefine issue, I prefer XSD over DTDs for
      the following reasons:<ol>
        <li>XSDs are fully namespace aware and namespaces are good.</li>
        <li>XSDs are more expressive than DTDs.</li>
        <li>Because they are XML documents, you can embed complete XML-based documentation in your
          XSD in a way you cannot in DTDs.</li>
        <li>As XML documents, XSDs are more convenient to process than DTDs (however, there are DTD
          parsers that make processing DTDs almost as convenient as XSDs)</li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>DITA 1.x can't use namespaces, which eliminates the namespace advantage of XSDs (you could
      use namespace-based XSDs to create document type modules that are functionally equivalent to
      DITA's modularity features. However, DITA's modularity features do not use namespaces).</p>
    <p>The XSD 1.1 specification defines a new feature, <q>override,</q> that is intended to
      functionally replace the redefine feature and provide a more flexible extension mechanism, one
      that is a better match to what DITA needs. If the override feature works as we want it to (the
      DITA TC has provided input about DITA's requirements to the XSD Working Group) and it is
      implemented by XSD-aware processors, then it will be possible to rework the DITA XSDs to use
      override rather than redefine, at which point XSDs will become a better choice for vocabulary
      module implementation.</p>
    <p>Until that time, however, the easiest and safest route is to stick with DTD-based shells and vocabulary modules.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
