<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="understanding-specialization">
  <title>Understanding Configuration and Specialization</title>
  <shortdesc>Before you can design and implement your own configurations and specializations you
    must have a basic understanding of configuration and specialization.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>DITA is designed to let you design new markup and new document types in a way that allows any
      general-purpose DITA processor to usefully process documents that use the new markup. This in
      turn enables blind interchange of DITA documents, because DITA users knows they can use and
      process, at least minimally, any conforming DITA document they get from any source. In
      particular, in the context of a map, you can combine topics of any type and get usable, if not
      optimal, results from any general-purpose DITA processor.<fn>I have to say <q>general
          purpose</q> processor because it's possible to have conforming DITA processors that only
        understand specific markup vocabularies and are not specialization aware. Such processors
        are probably rare, but they are explicitly allowed by the DITA 1.2 conformance clause. Most
        DITA-aware tools you will find are both general-purpose and specialization-aware, meaning
        that they can handle, to at least some minimal degree, all conforming DITA documents,
        specialized or not. </fn></p>
    <p>The specialization feature of DITA, the ability to have your own markup design while still
      ensuring blind interchange of your content with other DITA users, is unique among all
      currently-existing standard XML applications (and most, if not all, private XML applications). </p>
    <p>Specialization is the one truly unique and distinguishing aspect of DITA. No other aspect of
      DITA is exclusive to DITA. All of DITA's modularity features—maps, topics, key-based
      addressing, etc.—can either be found to one degree or another in other XML applications or
      could be added to those applications without too much trouble. This is not to discount the
      value of these features of DITA—they represent deep thought and years of practical experience
      and are quite valuable in themselves—but they are not distinguishing in the way that
      specialization is.</p>
    <p>Even if you have no use for any aspect of DITA having to do with modularity or reuse, you
      still have a use for specialization simply because it enables reliable interchange in a way
      that no other XML application does. Even if your only interchange partner is your future self,
      DITA still offers dramatic and compelling advantages.</p>
    <p>In short, one can see DITA as an architecture for the management of XML vocabularies. </p>
    <p>These tutorials show you how to apply the architecture to specific types of requirements.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
