<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="ss1">
  <title>XML Vocabularies and their Management</title>
  <body>
    <p>In general XML parlance a <q>vocabulary</q> is a set of element types and attributes designed
      to be used together for some purpose. A given vocabulary may be <q>encompassing,</q> meaning
      that it is intended to be used as the main or only vocabulary for a given document, or
        <q>enabling,</q> meaning it is intended to be integrated into and used with encompassing
      vocabularies.</p>
    <p>Examples of encompassing vocabularies are DocBook, XHTML, and JATS (nee NLM). Examples of enabling vocabularies are MathML and Dublin Core metadata.</p>
    <p>An historical challenge with managing XML (and SGML) vocabularies has been that, while it's
      easy to define enabling vocabularies like MathML and possible to define <q>extensible</q>
      encompassing vocabularies like DocBook, there has been no standard, defined mechanism for
      managing how encompassing and enabling vocabularies should be combined to ensure
      understandability and interchange.<fn>The HyTime standard, ISO/IEC 10744, provided a mechanism
        for vocabulary management, but it was not widely adopted before XML made it obsolete. You
        can view DITA's specialization feature as the XML reincarnation of the architectural form
        facility of HyTime. DITA's specialization feature was directly influenced by HyTime and the
        way we applied it within IBM to the IBMIDDoc SGML application.</fn></p>
    <p>Before DITA, all mechanisms for combining or extending vocabularies were entirely
      syntactic—they provided no way to examine a <i>document</i> and know how that document's
      vocabulary related with any other vocabulary. Therefore, there was no way you could, for sure,
      whether your processing environment could handle that document, or if you could share content
      from that document with your documents.<draft-comment>Actually, DocBook is pretty clear that
        if you extend DocBook, the result is no longer DocBook. therefore, it's not quite true to
        say that you "nominally" have a DocBook document. I've edited this a bit to avoid that
        point.</draft-comment></p>
    <p>For example, DocBook supports extension by providing the syntactic hooks
      needed to locally modify the content model. This allows you to define your
      own element and attribute types. However, once you have done that, you no
      longer have DocBook. In fact, the DocBook Definitive Guide specifically
      says, in bold type, <q>If You Change DocBook, It's Not DocBook
      Anymore!</q> There is no formal way, <i>in the markup</i>, to tell a
      processor or an observer how your new element types relate to any known
      element types (that is, to the element types defined in the DocBook
      standard). <fn>Norm Walsh has, informally, shown how this could be done (<xref
      href="http://norman.walsh.name/2005/10/21/dita"
      scope="external"
      format="html">DITA for DocBook</xref>), but there is no formal,
      standards-based implementation.</fn></p>
    <p>In particular, there are no DocBook-defined constraints on <i>how</i> to extend DocBook,
      which means that a general-purpose processor cannot <q>fall back,</q> like DITA can, to a
      usable default when it encounters an unknown element or attribute.<draft-comment>I'm not sure
        the following is necessarily true. After all, DITA uses DTDs as a syntactic tool, and isn't
        the mechanism that allows DITA processors to identify and handle specializations a syntactic
        device, too? <p>It seems like the strength of your point isn't that syntactic tools are
          incapable of managing XML vocabularies, but rather that the methods used in previous
          schemas have not succeeded in making extension and customization
        manageable.</p></draft-comment></p>
    <p>That is, using only the syntactic tools provided by DTDs or XSD schemas (or any other available form of XML document constraint, such as RelaxNG) extension and customization of XML vocabularies is inherently <i>unmanageable</i> because there is no machine-processable mechanism for communicating or understanding the relationship between any two vocabularies.</p>
    <p>If customization is not manageable then the only way to ensure interchange is to disallow
      customization. This was the approach taken by <q>interchange</q> document types, such as ATA
      2100. But of course invariant vocabularies suffer a number of serious and fatal problems. They
      tend to become very large because they must reflect a union of the requirements of all current
      and expected interchange partners. They tend to not satisfy key requirements of individual
      interchange partners because you can never put everything in or because local requirements are
      at odds with interchange requirements (for example, markup that is specific to a given
      company's internal business processes, which might be trade secrets). I think it's fair to say
      that, as an industry, we've conclusively proved over the last 20 years or so that monolithic
      interchange document types do not work. </p>
  </body>
</topic>
