<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-specialization-step-1">
  <title>Topic Specialization Step 1: Design The Topic Element Types</title>
  <body>
    <p>For topic specialization you have to think about several things in designing your specialization: <ul>
      <li>What should the new topic element type name be?</li>
      <li>What should be allowed within the topic body?</li>
      <li>Should the topic allow any nested topics?</li>
      <li>Does the topic require specialized topic-level metadata?</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>Of course, to answer these questions, you have to first understand the requirements, both for
    the information content and the information presentation and processing.</p>
    <p>For this tutorial, our task is to create a specialization of <xmlelement>concept</xmlelement>
    that supports the requirements of FAQ information, that is, questions and answers.</p>
    <note>If you just want to know what the mechanics are and don't really care about how
    we arrived at the design used in the rest of the tutorial, you can skip on to step
    2 at this point. But once you've worked through the tutorial I'd urge you to come back
    here and read this step all the way through.</note>
    <p>I chose FAQs as the subject of the tutorial because they are familiar to most Web users (and
            now even non-Web users), they are relatively simple (at least on their face) but not so
            trivial as to be boring, and they have some potential sophistications that could make
            for interesting exploration beyond the immediate task of <q>what are the mechanics of
                defining and implementing a new topic type?</q> In addition, there are any number of
            useful and reasonable ways that FAQs could be constructed using DITA; this tutorial
            presents only one, and not necessarily the best one.</p>
    <p>For this tutorial I have decided that the each question should be a separate topic, rather
            than having one topic that contains multiple question/answer pairs. I have found that
            making <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> the primary unit of organization and granularity works
            well, even if it leads to topics that some people might initially or intuitively think
            are too small. But I wouldn't go to the mat to defend this design decision, and I don't
            claim it's necessarily the best. It has a logic I can defend, but that's as far as I'll
            go.</p>
    <p>As you work through the tutorial, take the time to ask yourself how you would have done it
            and why a different way would or wouldn't be better for some reason. This type of
            analytical thought is all part of understanding your requirements and mapping them to
            implementations to create the best possible solution.</p>
    <p>For this tutorial, let's define an FAQ as a set of one or more question and answer pairs,
            where the question is a relatively short statement and the answer may be as short or
            long as needed. We would like the markup to reflect this essential nature, that is,
            there should be something named something like <q>question</q> and something named
            something like <q>answer.</q> There are no particular requirements for the contents of
            answers themselves. We would like the rendering to clearly identify the question and
            answer, for example, <q>Q. Question statement,</q>
            <q>A. Answer response.</q> The default topic presentation would <i>not</i> be sufficient
            in this case.</p>
    <p>Note that these requirements are pretty simple. In any sort of engineering activity, it is
            best to start off as simply as you can and use iterative refinement to satisfy new
            requirements as you discover them. In the world of agile methods this is known as <q>the
                simplest thing that could possibly work.</q>
        </p>
    <p>This approach does several things: it lets you get something working quickly, it gives you
            immediate practical experience that will feed back into the design and implementation,
            and it avoids designing and implementing things you don't need. When designing XML
            markup it is quite easy to over-design and build complex markup structures that nobody
            actually wants, needs, or perhaps, can understand how to use. I've certainly done my
            share of this in the past.</p>
        <p>I now find it much more effective to start small and build up as needed. Often this
            refinement process happens over the course of a few hours as I implement a new document
            type or specialization and start testing it with real data, but sometimes it happens
            over weeks or months as the new markup design is tested by its target users. In any
            case, for this tutorial, we will start small and, once we have something working that
            minimally meets our requirements, we can start thinking about other things we might
            need.</p>
    <p>Another characteristic of agile development methods is <q>test-driven development,</q> that
            is, using test cases to drive the implementation, rather than implementing first and
            testing later. The basic idea is that you write the test case first, which will of
            course initially fail (because there's no code yet), and then you do the implementation
            until the test case passes, at which point you know you're done. The test cases reflect
            the requirements as you understand them, and if the requirements change, you update the
            test case to reflect your new understanding.</p> 
    <p>For markup design, this means you first create document instances and then implement the DTD
            or schema that will validate those instances. When the instances are valid, you know
            you're done (as long as your instances reflect all the important cases the schema needs
            to support). This is in contrast to simply going from requirements straight to markup
            declarations, and then only creating instances after the fact, which is the way we had
            to do it back in SGML days. One of the nice things about XML is that you can have
            documents with no document type, so you can start with instances and add DTDs or schemas
            later. </p>
    <p>Names are always important and in this case there is a slight problem with the name to use
            for the topic element itself, namely <q>faq,</q> which would be the obvious choice. The
            problem is that the term "FAQ" can be read as either singular or plural (a set of
            questions) but here we want a single topic to reflect a single question/answer pair. The
            name <q>question-and-answer</q> might work, except that could also imply a testing
            environment rather than an FAQ environment. Thus, I have arrived at the name
                <q>faq-question</q>&#x2014;it's technically redundant but fairly clear and not too
            long: <codeblock>
&lt;faq-question id="q1">
&lt;/faq-question></codeblock></p>
    <p>The topic title will be the question statement, and it's probably useful to specialize
                <xmlelement>title</xmlelement> to <xmlelement>faq-question-statement</xmlelement> to make that
            clear:
            <codeblock>
&lt;faq-question id="q1">
  &lt;faq-question-statement>Can I add attributes to specific element types?&lt;/faq-question-statement>
&lt;/faq-question> </codeblock></p>
    <p>In this case we don't have any particular requirements for the topic body content, so we
            could leave <xmlelement>body</xmlelement> unspecialized, but since the body will be the FAQ
            answer, it makes sense to rename <xmlelement>body</xmlelement> to
                <xmlelement>faq-answer</xmlelement>. </p>
    <p>Note that just <q>answer</q> is probably too generic. One challenge with DITA 1.x is that
            because you cannot use namespaces, all element types, including all specialized element
            types, must be unique. While you can't guarantee that your specialized types won't
            conflict with somebody else's, it helps if you use names that are specific to your
            content. This can sometimes lead to names that are longer or more cumbersome than they
            would need to be if we could use namespaces in DITA 1.x. A good example is the element
            types defined by the DITA 1.2 Learning and Training vocabulary modules, which all start
            with <q>lc</q> (for <q>learning content</q>), which functions as a sort of <q>namespace
                prefix</q> and helps ensure that no other vocabularies will have names that collide
            with the Learning and Training types.<draft-comment>It's not clear if lc is a good
                example of things being more cumbersome or a good example of how to use prefixes.
                Unless you really consider the lc prefix to be too cumbersome, I'd say something
                like, "An example that isn't too cumbersome is the ..."</draft-comment></p>
    <p>So our topic body should look like this: <codeblock>
&lt;faq-question id="question-id">
  &lt;faq-question-statement>Can I add attributes to specific element types?&lt;/faq-question-statement>
  &lt;faq-answer >
    &lt;p>No, you can only define global attributes, specialized either from &amp;lt;base&amp;gt;
    or @props.&lt;/p>
  &lt;/faq-answer>
&lt;/faq-question></codeblock></p>
    <p>This design should be sufficient to get us going. Note that we are deferring all issues of how to organize the FAQ questions into FAQs using maps, where we know we already have everything we need to create sets of questions and to do things like group questions into titled groups.</p>
  </body>  
</topic>
