<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-spec-step-4-1">
  <title>Topic Specialization Step 4-1: Create Initial Toolkit Plugin Components</title>
  <body>
    <p>Outside the toolkit, create the directory <filepath>org.example.faq-question.html</filepath>
            to contain your plugin. I use the convention of
                    <q><varname>moduleName</varname>.<varname>transtype</varname></q> for the plugin
            name, thus <q>faq-question.html</q> for the HTML plugin, <q>faq-question.fo</q> for the
            PDF plugin, etc.</p>
    <p>In the <filepath>org.example.faq-question.html</filepath> directory create the file <filepath>plugin.xml</filepath> with this content:<codeblock>&lt;!-- 
  Plugin descriptor for the FAQ question HTML extensions.
  -->
&lt;plugin id="org.example.faq-question.html">
  &lt;require plugin="org.example.faq-question.doctype"/> 
  &lt;feature extension="dita.xsl.xhtml" value="xsl/faq-question2html.xsl" type="file"/>  
&lt;/plugin></codeblock></p>
    <p>This descriptor names the plugin (<q>org.example.faq-question.html</q>), indicates that it is
            dependent on the FAQ question document type plugin, and binds the plugin's XSLT module
            to the extension point <q>dita.xsl.xhtml, </q>which is defined in the base DITA-to-HTML
            transformation type.</p>
    <p>The <xmlelement>require</xmlelement> element is not strictly required, but it makes it clearer that
            this module supports the FAQ question vocabulary module and is not, for example, a more
            general extension or override. Note also that the document type plugin does <i>not</i>
            state a dependency on the HTML plugin. This is because there may be users who want to
            use the vocabulary but not your particular implementation of the processing for it. Thus
            you should always have separate plugins for the vocabulary modules and their supporting
            processing so that users of your vocabulary modules can easily substitute their own
            processing if they want to.</p>
    <p>Create the directory <filepath>xsl</filepath> within the <filepath>org.example.faq-question.html</filepath> directory. In the <filepath>xsl</filepath> directory create the file <filepath>faq-question2html.xsl</filepath> with this content: <codeblock>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
&lt;xsl:stylesheet
  xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
  xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
  exclude-result-prefixes="xs"
  version="2.0">
  
  &lt;!-- ===========================================================
    HTML generation templates for the FAQ Question DITA topic
    specialization.
    
    Copyright (c) 2011 Your Name Here
    
    =========================================================== -->
    
    
&lt;/xsl:stylesheet> </codeblock></p>
    <p>At the moment this stylesheet does nothing.</p>
    <p>You can test the plugin by deploying it to your Toolkit and running the HTML transformation type against one of the FAQ question test documents. The processing should produce completely generic output but should not fail with any XSLT-related errors.</p>
    <p>Note that this XSLT module is an XSLT 2 module. As of version 1.4.3 of the Open Toolkit, the
            Toolkit uses the Saxon XSLT engine exclusively. Saxon implements XSLT 2, so it is safe
            to use XSLT 2 with the Toolkit. It doesn't matter that the base transformation modules
            are XSLT 1 modules.</p>
  </body>
</topic>  