<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-spec-step-4-4cont">
  <title>Topic Specialization Step 4-4 (continued): Implement Specialization-Specific XSLT Processing</title>
  <body>
    <p>Having reworked the markup design to provide a short answer and answer details, pop back up to step 4-4
    and continue implementing the XSLT processing.</p>
    <p>The first thing to do is update the existing templates to reflect our new element type names,
            which means changing the template for <xmlelement>faq-answer</xmlelement> to match on
                <q>faq-answer-details</q> instead of <q>faq-answer</q>:
            <codeblock>
  &lt;xsl:template match="*[contains(@class, <b>' faq-question/faq-answer-details '</b>)]">
</codeblock></p>
    <p>Now the challenge is to modify the code within this template to give us the result we want. Modify the template as follows: <ol
      id="ol_8d223a01-6b4c-4d40-b14a-2330e6fd1529">
      <li>Delete all the comments between the call-template to <q>start-revtag</q> and the
                    apply-templates for <q>topic/abstract.</q></li>
      <li>Because we have removed <xmlelement>abstract</xmlelement> from the content model for
                        <xmlelement>faq-question</xmlelement>, you can delete the apply-templates
                    instruction that matches on <q>topic/abstract.</q> Having the instruction there
                    wouldn't hurt anything (there will never be an abstract to match on), but it
                    might confuse somebody who knows the content model for
                        <xmlelement>faq-question</xmlelement>. However, since somebody who knows the
                    content model for topic might expect there to be a match on
                        <xmlelement>abstract</xmlelement>, it's probably a good idea to provide a comment
                    to the effect that <xmlelement>faq-question</xmlelement> doesn't allow
                        <xmlelement>abstract</xmlelement>.</li>
      <li>Put a <xmlelement>div</xmlelement> with a <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> attribute value of
                        <q>faq-answer-details</q> around the last <q>apply-templates</q> call: <codeblock>
  <b>&lt;div class="faq-answer-details"></b>
    &lt;xsl:apply-templates/>
  <b>&lt;/div></b></codeblock>
                    <p>This <xmlelement>div</xmlelement> clearly separates the answer details from the
                        short answer and the <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> value provides a hook that can
                        be used in CSS styles or JavaScript to add additional formatting or behavior
                        to the answer details.</p></li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>The reworked template should look like this (changed bits are shown in bold):<codeblock>  &lt;xsl:template match="*[contains(@class, ' faq-question/<b>faq-answer-details</b> ')]">
    &lt;xsl:variable name="flagrules">
      &lt;xsl:call-template name="getrules"/>
    &lt;/xsl:variable>
    &lt;div>
      &lt;xsl:call-template name="commonattributes"/>
      &lt;xsl:call-template name="gen-style">
        &lt;xsl:with-param name="flagrules" select="$flagrules">&lt;/xsl:with-param>
      &lt;/xsl:call-template>
      &lt;xsl:call-template name="setidaname"/>
      &lt;xsl:call-template name="start-flagit">
        &lt;xsl:with-param name="flagrules" select="$flagrules">&lt;/xsl:with-param>     
      &lt;/xsl:call-template>
      &lt;xsl:call-template name="start-revflag">
        &lt;xsl:with-param name="flagrules" select="$flagrules"/>  
      &lt;/xsl:call-template>
      <b>&lt;!-- Abstract not allowed in faq-question topic type --> </b>     
      &lt;!-- get the shortdesc para -->
      &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="preceding-sibling::*[contains(@class,' topic/shortdesc ')]" mode="outofline"/>
      
      &lt;!-- Insert pre-req links - after shortdesc - unless there is a prereq section about -->
      &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="following-sibling::*[contains(@class,' topic/related-links ')]" mode="prereqs"/>
      
      <b>&lt;div class="faq-answer-details">
        &lt;xsl:apply-templates/>
      &lt;/div></b>
      &lt;xsl:call-template name="end-revflag">
        &lt;xsl:with-param name="flagrules" select="$flagrules"/>  
      &lt;/xsl:call-template>
      &lt;xsl:call-template name="end-flagit">
        &lt;xsl:with-param name="flagrules" select="$flagrules">&lt;/xsl:with-param> 
      &lt;/xsl:call-template>
    &lt;/div>&lt;xsl:value-of select="$newline"/>
  &lt;/xsl:template>
</codeblock></p>
    <p>Without having tested it yet, the template now looks like it should be right: it's not getting the
    abstract, it is processing the short description (our new <xmlelement>faq-short-answer</xmlelement>) and the
    rest of the processing should be appropriate.</p>
    <p>Redeploy the Toolkit plugin and run the transform against your sample FAQ question. You should get the same output you got before since all we really did was change the template match value and cut away stuff we didn't need.</p>
    <p>The next step in the implementation is to handle the <xmlelement>faq-short-answer</xmlelement> element. </p>
    <p>The formatting specification says to output <q>A. </q> followed by the answer text. To do
            this we need a template that matches on <q> faq-question/faq-short-answer </q>. Note
            that even though <xmlelement>faq-short-answer</xmlelement> is specialized from
                <xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement>, it would not make sense to simply override the
            processing for <xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement>, as that would change the formatting for all
            other topic types.</p>
    <p>Create the following template: <codeblock>
  &lt;xsl:template match="*[contains(@class, ' faq-question/faq-short-answer ')]" mode="outofline">
    &lt;div class="faq-short-answer">
      &lt;span class="faq-short-answer-a">A. &lt;/span>
      &lt;xsl:apply-templates/>
    &lt;/div>
  &lt;/xsl:template> 
</codeblock></p>
    <p>Note the <xmlatt>mode</xmlatt> attribute with the value <q>outofline.</q> This is necessary
            because the short description is being processed out of its normal source order, that is
            from within the processing for the topic body (to which <xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement> is
            a sibling) rather than from with the processing of <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> (of which it
            is a child). The base DITA stylesheets provide a generic way to handle this using the
            mode <q>outofline</q> for all templates that handle elements processed out of their
            normal document order. You can see that the mode is used on the apply templates in the
            template for <xmlelement>faq-question</xmlelement>:
            <codeblock>
  &lt;xsl:template match="*[contains(@class, ' faq-question/faq-answer-details ')]" priority="10">
    &lt;div>
       
      ...

      &lt;!-- get the shortdesc para -->
      <b>&lt;xsl:apply-templates select="preceding-sibling::*[contains(@class,' topic/shortdesc ')]"
        mode="outofline"/></b>

      ...

    &lt;/div>
    &lt;xsl:value-of select="$newline"/>
  &lt;/xsl:template>
</codeblock></p>
    <p>If you didn't specify the corresponding mode on the match template for
                <xmlelement>faq-short-answer</xmlelement>, you would get the answer text twice, once from
            base outofline mode template that matches on <q> topic/shortdesc </q> and once for the
            default mode template that matches on <q> faq-question/faq-short-answer </q>.</p>
    <p>This template will put out <q>A. </q> before the short description. The
                <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> values are there to support styling the result using CSS.</p>
    <p>Redeploy the Toolkit plugin, run the sample FAQ answer through the Toolkit, and inspect the
            results. You should now see the <q>A. </q> before the short answer text (the first
            paragraph of the result). This means that the XSLT is done. The next step is to create
            or update the applicable CSS stylesheet to add the appropriate styling to the HTML
            pages. </p>
  </body>
</topic>  