<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-specialization-step-2-2">
  <title>Step 2-2. Create New Document Type Shell DTD</title>
  <body>
    <p>In the base DITA distribution, find the file <filepath>concept.dtd</filepath>, copy it into
            the <filepath>faq-question/dtd</filepath> directory, and rename it
                <filepath>faq-question.dtd</filepath> (in the sample materials this file is named
                <filepath>faq-question-v1.dtd</filepath>).</p>
    <p>Edit this file as follows: <ul>
      <li>Delete the header comments and replace them with comments that indicate this document type
                    shell DTD is owned by you and is specific to the FAQ question module.</li>
      <li>Remove any references to any domain modules and entity files you don't need. Which ones
                    you need is entirely your decision&#x2014;if the FAQ is about a software product
                    you may, in fact, need the software and UI domains. For simplicity you can leave
                    all those declarations alone for now and worry about them later (or let the
                    users of your module worry about it). In the tutorial materials I've used only
                    the highlight and utility domains within this shell.</li>
      <li>Find the parameter entity named <parameterentity>concept-info-types</parameterentity> and rename it to
                        <parameterentity>faq-question-info-types</parameterentity>. Set its replacement text to
                        <q>no-topic-nesting,</q> instead of <q>%info-types;.</q><p>The
                            <xmlelement>no-topic-nesting</xmlelement> element is one of the DITA
                            <q>specialization</q> element types that exist to work around
                        limitations in DTD syntax. In particular, if you have a content model
                        declared like so: <codeblock> (%some-parameter-entity;)</codeblock> You
                        cannot simply set <parameterentity>some-parameter-entity</parameterentity> to an empty
                        string, because the resolved result would be: <codeblock>()</codeblock>which
                        is not valid.</p><p>The solution is to define an empty element type that
                        acts as a placeholder, thus <xmlelement>no-topic-nesting</xmlelement>.</p></li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>Try validating or opening the test document again. This time, instead of getting an error
            like <q>DTD not found,</q> you should get errors like <q>element type 'faq-question' not
                declared,</q> indicating that the validator found the DTD, but could not find the
            declarations for the FAQ-specific element types, which of course we haven't created yet.
            But we're making progress.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
