<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-specialization-tutorial">
  <title>Topic Specialization Tutorial</title>
  <shortdesc>Goal: Define a new structural specialization of the base <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> element type that supports the creation of FAQ (frequently asked question) topics.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>structural vocabulary module<indexterm>topic specialization tutorial</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>topic type<indexterm>specialization tutorial</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>tutorials<indexterm>topic specialization</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>tutorials<indexterm>structural specialization<indexterm>topic</indexterm></indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>FAQ<indexterm>topic type for</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
   <p>Topic specialization generally requires defining a number of new element types at different
            levels in the element hierarchy, as opposed to domain specialization, which can be as
            simple as defining a few new phrase-level element types.</p>
    <p>The main reason to create structural specializations is to provide more-specific markup that
            reflects your local business requirements or the nature of your information. For most
            technical documentation applications, the value in specializing reference and task topic
            types is usually pretty obvious. Information types work best when they directly reflect
            the details of the things being documented, the editorial rules for how tasks should be
            structured, and the needs of other information systems that use the information (for
            example, interactive task support systems).</p>
    <note type="tip">DITA 1.2 introduces a new configuration feature, constraints, which allows you
            to modify content models without doing specialization. This allows you to reserve
            specialization for those requirements that truly require new markup. Before DITA 1.2 you
            had to use specialization just to define more-constrained versions of base content
            models, even when you weren't changing the meaning of the markup itself. With DITA 1.2,
            this is no longer necessary. See <xref
                href="../constraint-module/creating-constraint-module.xml#topic-id" format="dita"
            />.</note>
    <p>For reference information, it is usually useful to define specialized reference topic types
            that directly reflect the objects being documented. For example, if you're documenting
            sprockets it probably makes sense to have a specialization of <q>reference</q> called
                <q>sprocket</q> or <q>sprocket-definition</q> that has specialized
                <xmlelement>section</xmlelement> elements that reflect the specific sets of properties or
            characteristics that sprockets have (tooth properties, shaft properties, material
            information, manufacturing notes, etc.).</p>
    <p>For tasks, you may have specific editorial rules for how tasks should be constructed, rules
            that are more constraining than the base DITA rules for tasks (which are already pretty
            constraining). <fn>DITA 1.2 defines a more generic base task type, which provides more
                opportunity to create specialized tasks that are different from the more-constrained
                DITA 1.1 <xmlelement>task</xmlelement>. </fn></p>
    <p>Because conceptual information is, by its nature, more generic, there is usually less need to
            specialize from <xmlelement>concept</xmlelement>. For example, the topics for this tutorial
            are all generic concepts (although they use a specialized domain for identifying
            mentions of XML constructs). However, there are still many good reasons to specialize
            concept topic types.</p>
    <p>One strong reason to specialize from <xmlelement>concept</xmlelement> is to create element types
            that reflect specific levels in a governing organizational taxonomy when that taxonomy
            is an integral and invariant aspect of the information. Another reason would be to
            provide different more-specific concept element types that are familiar to your authors
            or that reflect a particular editorial style for presenting conceptual information. For
            example, in the case of this tutorial, the FAQ topic type is based on concept but has
            been specialized to provide a clear <q>short answer/long answer</q> distinction and to
            disallow base types that we don't want to allow in FAQ topics (abstract in this case).
            In addition, having a specialized type for FAQ lets us apply FAQ-specific styling to the
            topics for presentation.</p>
    <p>Note that specializing <xmlelement>concept</xmlelement> to reflect specific hierarchical levels
            within a traditional document, e.g., chapter, section, subsection, is normally not a
            good idea, because it binds a given topic to a specific level, making it harder to
            re-use or re-organize the topic in other contexts. Instead, if you want markup that
            directly reflects specific hierarchical levels, you should use map specializations, such
            as the standard <xmlelement>bookmap</xmlelement> or the DITA for Publishers publication map
            domain. </p>
    <p>The only exception to this rule I can think of is when you have an editorial policy that
            requires title-only topics (that is, topics with no body) to satisfy specific levels in
            a governing hierarchy (that is, a governing, invariant, taxonomy). In that case, it can
            make sense to define specializations of <xmlelement>concept</xmlelement> or
                <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> whose names reflect the taxonomy or hierarchy level and
            that don't allow either <xmlelement>body</xmlelement> or nested topics (meaning that they only
            serve to be used from maps within a hierarchy of topic references). However, the value
            of this type of topic is dubious given that <xmlelement>topichead</xmlelement> elements within
            a map are sufficient to establish the hierarchy and provide the necessary
                titles.<fn>DITA 1.2 also clarifies the fact that topicheads can processed as though
                they referred to title-only topics.</fn></p>
    <p>Note that you are not required to specialize from <xmlelement>concept</xmlelement>,
                <xmlelement>task</xmlelement>, or <xmlelement>reference</xmlelement>. You can specialize
            directly from <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement> or from a more-specialized topic type. The
            concept/task/reference model makes sense in the context of technical documentation,
            where it reflects well-established writing practice. But it is not always sensible for
            other uses of DITA. For example, in the context of Publishing, most content either does
            not naturally map to one of those three types, or those distinctions simply aren't
            relevant (e.g., within a novel). In that case it can make sense to specialize directly
            from <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement>. </p>
    <p>For example, the DITA for Publishers vocabulary includes the topic types
                <xmlelement>article</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>chapter</xmlelement>, <xmlelement>part</xmlelement>,
                <xmlelement>subsection</xmlelement>, and <xmlelement>sidebar</xmlelement>, all specialized
            directly from <xmlelement>topic</xmlelement>, because they are intended to represent content
            at its most generic. The topic types simply provide a more obvious mapping to the basic
            document components Publishers would expect to see in any Publishing XML application.
            These topic types also reflect the simplest topic specialization, one that changes only
            the topic root element, leaving all other elements unchanged. For DITA for Publishers
            this reflects the need to distinguish chapters from articles as business objects, and
            people expect to find these topic types in a publishing vocabulary.</p>
  </body>
  
</topic>  
