<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-specialization-step-2-3">
  <title>Step 2-3. Create New .mod File and Integrate Into Shell</title>
  <body>
    <p>Find the file <filepath>concept.mod</filepath> in the regular DITA DTD distribution and copy
            it to <filepath>faq-question.mod</filepath> in your
                <filepath>faq-questions/dtd</filepath> directory.</p>
    <p>Edit this file as follows: <ul>
      <li>Delete the header comments and replace them with comments that indicate this module DTD is
                    owned by you and contains the DTD declarations for the FAQ question module.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>Now edit the <filepath>faq-question.dtd</filepath> file (the document type shell DTD) and integrate the module as follows: <ol>
      <li>Find the declaration for the <parameterentity>concept-typemod</parameterentity> entity declaration.</li>
      <li><i>After</i> this declaration, add the following declaration and reference to the
                    faq-question topic type module:
                    <codeblock>
&lt;!ENTITY % faq-question-typemod 
  SYSTEM "faq-question.mod"                                                        
 >                                                     
%faq-question-typemod; </codeblock></li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>The topic element integration section of the <filepath>faq-question.dtd</filepath> shell
            should now look like this:
            <codeblock>
&lt;!-- ============================================================= -->
&lt;!--                    TOPIC ELEMENT INTEGRATION                  -->
&lt;!-- ============================================================= -->

&lt;!--                    Embed topic to get generic elements        -->
&lt;!ENTITY % topic-type   PUBLIC 
"-//OASIS//ELEMENTS DITA Topic//EN" 
"topic.mod"                                                          >
%topic-type;


&lt;!--                    Embed concept to get specific elements     -->
&lt;!ENTITY % concept-typemod 
                        PUBLIC 
"-//OASIS//ELEMENTS DITA Concept//EN" 
"concept.mod"                                                        >                                                     
%concept-typemod;

<b>&lt;!ENTITY % faq-question-typemod 
  SYSTEM "faq-question.mod"                                                        
 >                                                     
%faq-question-typemod;</b>
</codeblock></p>
    <p>Note that I didn't bother to define either a public identifier or a URN for the
                <parameterentity>faq-question-typemod</parameterentity> parameter entity. This is to keep things
            simple. Later, once we've got everything working, we can replace the relative URL with a
            URN and set up the necessary catalog mappings.</p>
    <p>Trying validating your test document again. Now you should get errors to the effect that the
                <q>concept</q> element type is declared multiple times, as well as the same messages
            about the FAQ-specific element types not being declared. This indicates that we've got
            the module integrated with the shell correctly.</p>
    <note>You may be now be thinking that I'm going about this in the wrong order&#x2014;shouldn't I
            declare the element types for the module first and then integrate them? The method in
            this madness is that by starting from the back and working forward, we know what isn't
            done yet (by the failures reported when we validate our test) and we'll know for sure
            when we're done (because the failures will go away) and, most important, we'll know that
            when the failures do go away, it's because everything really is hooked up correctly and
            not for some other hard-to-debug reason, like we forgot to hook in a particular module.
            Essentially, we start with where we want to end up and then work backwards until we get
            there.</note>
  </body>
</topic>
