<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-spec-step-4-5">
  <title>Topic Specialization Step 4-5: Refine Markup Design for FAQ Question</title>
  <body>
    <p>As a result of our initial output processing implementation effort we've realized that we
            should require the <xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement> element to be the required first
            paragraph of a potentially longer answer. We will also disallow the
                <xmlelement>abstract</xmlelement> element because it's not relevant to what we're trying
            to do.</p>
    <p>This change also requires us to rethink our element type names. If the short description is
            going to act as the first paragraph of the answer, then <q>shortdesc</q> is probably not
            the best name. By the same token, the name <q>faq-answer</q> is probably not the best
            name for the topic body. Better names are probably <q>faq-short-answer</q> for the short
            description and <q>faq-answer-details</q> for the topic body.</p>
    <p>To implement this new design, first modify the test document to use this new markup: <codeblock>
&lt;faq-question id="question-id">
  &lt;faq-question-statement>Can I add attributes to specific element types?&lt;/faq-question-statement>
  &lt;faq-short-answer>No, you can only define global attributes, specialized either from @base
    or @props.&lt;/faq-short-answer>
  &lt;faq-answer-details>
    &lt;p>As of DITA 1.2, there is no mechanism for defining new attributes for specific element types.
    The problem is that there is no DITA-defined syntax for declaring a given attribute as being
    an attribute that should be recognized as such by a DITA-aware processor and not just some
    random attribute that was allowed in error (as the DITA architecture otherwise does not 
    allow non-DITA-defined attributes.&lt;/p>
    &lt;p>Providing this ability is a booked feature request for DITA.&lt;/p>
  &lt;/faq-answer-details>
&lt;/faq-question>
</codeblock></p>
    <p>Verify that the document is no longer valid.</p>
    <p>Edit faq-question.mod and do the following: <ol>
      <li>Modify the content model for <xmlelement>faq-question</xmlelement> as follows: <ol>
        <li>Remove <q>| %abstract;</q></li>
        <li>Change <q>%shortdesc;</q> to <q>%faq-short-answer;</q></li>
        <li>Remove the <q>?</q> following the group containing <q>%faq-short-answer;</q> to make it
                            required.</li>
        <li>Change <q>%faq-answer;</q> to <q>%faq-answer-details;</q></li>
        </ol><p>The resulting declaration should look like this:<codeblock>&lt;!ENTITY % faq-question.content
 "
  ((%faq-question-statement;), 
   (%titlealts;)?,
   (%faq-short-answer;), 
   (%prolog;)?, 
   (%faq-answer-details;)?, 
   (%related-links;)?,
   (%faq-question-info-types;)* )                   
"> </codeblock></p></li>
      <li>Find the declaration of the <parameterentity>faq-answer</parameterentity> parameter entity and change its
                    name and value to <q>faq-answer-details.</q></li>
      <li>Create a new element name parameter entity declaration for <xmlelement>faq-answer-details</xmlelement>.</li>
      <li>Find the element and attribute declarations for <xmlelement>faq-answer</xmlelement> and change
                    the element type name to <q>faq-answer-details.</q><p>The new declarations
                        should look like
                        this:<codeblock>&lt;!--                    LONG NAME: FAQ answer details -->
&lt;!ENTITY % faq-answer-details.content
"
  ((%body.cnt;)*, 
   (%section;|
    %example;)* 
  )     
">
&lt;!ENTITY % faq-answer-details.attributes
'
             %id-atts;
             %localization-atts;
             outputclass 
                        CDATA                            #IMPLIED    
'>
&lt;!ELEMENT faq-answer-details %faq-answer-details.content; >
&lt;!ATTLIST faq-answer-details %faq-answer-details.attributes; > 
</codeblock></p></li>
      <li>In the DITA-supplied <filepath>commonElements.mod</filepath> file, find the element type
                    declaration for <xmlelement>shortdesc</xmlelement>. Copy it and paste it after the
                    element type and attribute declaration for <xmlelement>faq-question</xmlelement>. (I
                    like to list element type declarations more or less in the order they occur in
                    the document's structural hierarchy.)</li>
      <li>Change <q>shortdesc</q> to <q>faq-short-answer</q> in the declarations you just
                        copied.<p>The resulting declaration should look like
                        this:<codeblock>&lt;!--                    LONG NAME: FAQ short answer               -->
&lt;!ENTITY % faq-short-answer.content 
"
  (%title.cnt; |
   %draft-comment;)*  
">
&lt;!ENTITY % faq-short-answer.attributes
'  %univ-atts;
   outputclass 
      CDATA #IMPLIED    
'>
&lt;!ELEMENT faq-short-answer %faq-short-answer.content; >
&lt;!ATTLIST faq-short-answer %faq-short-answer.attributes; > 
</codeblock></p></li>
      <li>Find the <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> attribute declarations at the end of the .mod file and edit them as follows: <ol>
        <li>In the attribute declaration for <xmlelement>faq-answer</xmlelement>, change both occurrences
                            of <q>faq-answer</q> to <q>faq-answer-details.</q></li>
        <li>Copy the declaration for <xmlelement>faq-answer-details</xmlelement> and change
                                <q>faq-answer-details</q> to <q>faq-short-answer.</q></li>
        <li>In the <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> attribute declaration for what is now
                                <xmlelement>faq-short-answer</xmlelement>, change <q>topic/body</q> to
                                <q>topic/shortdesc.</q> Change <q> concept/conbody </q> to <q>
                                concept/shortdesc </q> (all the levels of the specialization
                            hierarchy must be accounted for in the <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> attributes
                            even if the element type name is not changed). </li>
        </ol></li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>The class declarations should now look like this: <codeblock>
&lt;!ATTLIST faq-question        %global-atts;  class CDATA "- topic/topic     concept/concept   faq-question/faq-question ">
&lt;!ATTLIST faq-short-answer    %global-atts;  class CDATA "- topic/shortdesc concept/shortdesc faq-question/faq-short-answer ">
&lt;!ATTLIST faq-answer-details  %global-atts;  class CDATA "- topic/body      concept/conbody   faq-question/faq-answer-details ">
&lt;!ATTLIST question-statement  %global-atts;  class CDATA "- topic/title     concept/title     faq-question/faq-question-statement "></codeblock></p>
    <p>Redeploy the faq-question Toolkit plugin and try validating the updated test document. It should validate.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
