<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-specialization-step-2-1">
  <title>Step 2-1. Create Test Case Document Instance</title>
  <body>
    <p>In your working area create a directory named <filepath>faq-question</filepath> and under
            that create the directory <filepath>dtd</filepath>. This will hold all the DTD-related
            materials for the topic specialization. You should create this directory outside the
            scope of the DITA Open Toolkit. (In the tutorial materials there are two directories,
                <filepath>faq-question-v1</filepath> and <filepath>faq-question</filepath>. The
                <filepath>faq-question-v1</filepath> directory contains the first iteration of the
            module, the <filepath>faq-question</filepath> directory contains the final, refined
            version.)</p>
    <p>In the faq-question directory, create the file <filepath>faq-question-test-01.xml</filepath>
            with this content:
            <codeblock>
&lt;?xml version="1.0"?>          
&lt;!DOCTYPE faq-question SYSTEM "dtd/faq-question.dtd">          
&lt;faq-question id="question-id">
  &lt;faq-question-statement>Can I add attributes to specific element types?&lt;/faq-question-statement>
  &lt;faq-answer >
    &lt;p>No, you can only define global attributes, specialized either from &amp;lt;base&amp;gt;
    or @props.&lt;/p>
  &lt;/faq-answer>
&lt;/faq-question></codeblock></p>
    <p>Note that the SYSTEM ID of the DTD is a local, relative URL. This is to keep things simple
            for testing purposes and to avoid the added complexity of mapping PUBLIC or SYSTEM IDs
            through catalogs. Later we will set up the necessary catalog entries so documents can
            use an absolute URI for the faq-question shell DTD.</p>
    <p>Open this document in an XML-aware editor. It should either fail to open with a <q>can't find
                the DTD</q> message or open but say that it can't be validated. Now our goal is to
            make this file validate.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
