<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-specialization-step-3">
  <title>Topic Specialization Step 3. Package the Modules as a Toolkit Plugin</title>
  <body>
    <p>Now that the declarations are complete and validated, we need to package the declarations for use in documents. The best way to do this is to package it as an Open Toolkit plugin. Making it into a plugin does two things:<ul
      id="ul_ee6a74ab-053c-486d-992d-65b9c4dafe3f">
      <li>Provides entity resolution catalogs for mapping public identifiers to the various files.</li>
      <li>Makes it easy to deploy the vocabulary modules to Toolkit instances, which in turn makes the modules automatically available to tools that use the Toolkit to access vocabulary modules.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>To set up the plugin, follow these steps:<ol
      id="ol_369edde5-9a45-421f-b22b-aa07bbb861b6">
      <li>In the <filepath>faq-question</filepath> directory create a file named
                        <filepath>plugin.xml</filepath> with this
                        content:<codeblock>&lt;plugin id="org.example.faq-question.doctype">
  &lt;feature extension="dita.specialization.catalog.relative" value="catalog.xml" type="file"/>
&lt;/plugin></codeblock><note>This
                        defines a plugin with just this module. In practice you would normally
                        package all the related document type shells, vocabulary modules, and
                        constraint modules together as a single Toolkit plugin. See <xref
                            href="../../packaging-vocabulary-as-plugins.xml#topic-id" format="dita"
                        />.</note></li>
      <li>In the <filepath>faq-question</filepath> directory create a file named <filepath>catalog.xml</filepath> with this content:<codeblock>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
&lt;catalog xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:entity:xmlns:xml:catalog" prefer="public">
  
  &lt;nextCatalog catalog="dtd/catalog.xml"/>
  
&lt;/catalog></codeblock></li>
      <li>In the <filepath>faq-question/dtd</filepath> directory create a file named
                        <filepath>catalog.xml</filepath> with this
                        content:<codeblock>&lt;catalog xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:entity:xmlns:xml:catalog" prefer="public">
  
  &lt;public publicId="urn:pubid:example.org:doctypes:dita:modules:entities:faq-question"
    uri="faq-question.ent"
  />
  
  &lt;public publicId="urn:pubid:example.org:doctypes:dita:modules:faq-question"
    uri="faq-question.mod"
    />
  
  &lt;public publicId="urn:pubid:example.org:doctypes:dita:faq-question"
    uri="faq-question.dtd"
    />

&lt;/catalog></codeblock><note>In
                        practice you would replace <q>example.org</q> with your own domain name or
                        its universally-unique equivalent in the URNs.</note></li>
      <li>Edit the file <filepath>faq-question/dtd/faq-question.dtd</filepath> and update the entity declarations for the .ent and .mod files to use the URNs defined in the catalog file:<codeblock>...

&lt;!ENTITY % faq-question-dec     
  PUBLIC "<b>urn:pubid:example.org:doctypes:dita:modules:entities:faq-question-v1</b>" 
         "faq-question-v1.ent"
>%faq-question-dec;
     
...

&lt;!ENTITY % faq-question-typemod 
  PUBLIC "<b>urn:pubid:example.org:doctypes:dita:modules:faq-question-v1</b>" "faq-question-v1.mod"                                                        
 >                                                     
%faq-question-typemod;

...</codeblock><note type="tip">Common mistake: Using the .mod file's URN for the .ent file or visa versa.<p>This
                            is an easy mistake to make and a hard one to catch because the URNs are
                            so similar. One symptom of this is that the shell that's in the same
                            directory as the modules works, because it's system IDs are resolvable,
                            but a different shell that uses the same modules fails because the URNs
                            are wrong and the system IDs are not resolvable. That is one reason to
                            make sure that system IDs are not resolvable-it helps reveal this
                            sort of error.</p><p>Making this mistake can lead to baffling validation
                            errors from XML parsers, such as duplicate element type declarations or
                            other DTD syntax errors. Whenever you get those kinds of errors, the
                            first thing to check is the public IDs of the module entity declarations
                            in the shell document types.</p></note></li>
      <li>Copy the test document to create a new test document,
                        <filepath>faq-question-test-02.xml</filepath>, and modify its DOCTYPE
                    declaration so it uses the URN of the .dtd file and a bogus system identifier
                    (so the parser has to use the public ID to resolve the reference to the DTD
                        file<fn>Pedantically, the reference to the external parameter entity
                        declaration
                        set.</fn>):<codeblock>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?>          
&lt;!DOCTYPE faq-question 
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:example.org:doctypes:dita:modules:faq-question" 
         "bogus"
>          
&lt;faq-question id="question-id">
  &lt;faq-question-statement>Can I add attributes to specific element types?&lt;/faq-question-statement>
  &lt;faq-answer >
    &lt;p>No, you can only define global attributes, specialized either from @ase
    or @props.&lt;/p>
  &lt;/faq-answer>
&lt;/faq-question></codeblock><p>Edit
                        this document: it should not validate because you haven't deployed the
                        plugin to your Open Toolkit yet.</p></li>
      <li>Deploy the plugin to your Open Toolkit by copying the <filepath>faq-question</filepath>
                    directory to the <filepath>plugins</filepath> directory of your Open
                        Toolkit.<p>Run the <filepath>integrator.xml</filepath> Ant task to integrate
                        the
                        plugin:<codeblock>c:\DITA-OT > ant -f integrator.xml</codeblock></p><p>This
                        adds a reference to the <filepath>faq-question/catalog.xml</filepath> file
                        into the Toolkit's master entity resolution catalog,
                            <filepath>catalog-dita.xml</filepath>.</p></li>
      <li>Configure your editor or validation tool to use the catalog
                        <filepath>catalog-dita_template.xml</filepath> and verify that
                        <filepath>faq-question-test-02.xml</filepath> validates.<p>If you are using
                        OxygenXML and you deployed the plugin to Oxygen's Toolkit, then you should
                        just need perform the <q>Reset cache and validate</q> action. With other
                        editors or validators you may need to explicitly configure the use of the
                            <filepath>catalog-dita.xml</filepath> catalog.</p></li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>Your new topic type is now ready to use.</p>
  </body>
</topic>  
