<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd"> 
<topic id="topic-spec-step-4-6">
  <title>Topic Specialization Step 4-6: Implement CSS Styles</title>
  <body>
    <p>The DITA Open Toolkit provides a general framework for using CSS stylesheets with the HTML
            generated from topics. It provides the <filepath>commonltr.css</filepath>
                and"<filepath>commonrtl.css</filepath> styles, which are used by default for all
            generated HTML. You can also supply your own custom CSS and specify it as part of the
            HTML generation process.</p>
    <p>In the tutorial materials there is <filepath>faq-question_html.css</filepath> in the
                <filepath>html/css</filepath> directory. For your own environment you can create a
            new CSS stylesheet. You should store and manage it outside the scope of the DITA Open
            Toolkit. The Toolkit processing can automatically copy it to the output location for
            you. Or, if you are publishing your topics to a larger website, the CSS styles may be
            managed separately, in which case you just specify the name and path of the CSS but turn
            off the copying. This is all explained reasonably well in the Open Toolkit
            documentation. </p>
    <p>For this tutorial, create a new CSS file called <filepath>faq-question.css</filepath> and
            give it this initial content:
            <codeblock>
/*

  CSS for FAQ questions
  
  Copyright (c) 2011 Your Name Here

 */
 

</codeblock></p>
    <p>To use your custom CSS stylesheet you supply the full path of the CSS file, wherever you've
            put it, with the <q>/css</q> parameter of the HTML transformation type and specify
                <q>/csscopy</q> as <q>yes.</q><draft-comment>Where do you set /css and /csscopy? It
                looks like they would be set in your build.xml file using args.css and args.copycss,
                which I would state if that's the case. Also, is /csscopy correct, given that your
                build.xml file has args.copycss?</draft-comment></p>
    <p>The main thing this CSS needs to do is make the <q>A. </q> before the short answer big and
            bold to match the <q>Q. </q> for the question statement. Do this like so:
            <codeblock>
*[class = 'faq-short-answer-a'] {
  font-family: sans-serif;
  font-size: 16pt;
  font-weight: bold;
}
</codeblock></p>
    <p>You can test this by either re-running the toolkit or, once you've run it once, so that the
            CSS stylesheet is referenced from the HTML, you can just manually copy the changed CSS
            to the output directory and see how it looks. You might also find it easiest to develop
            the CSS style in place and then once you're happy with the result, copy it back to the
            original location. Just be careful not to run the toolkit in the meantime or you'll
            overwrite your changes (doh!).</p>
    <p>This style specification gives the result we specified, but it doesn't look quite right: the
                <q>A. </q> is now too big relative to the text of the answer. I don't pretend to
            have any skill at graphic design but my response to this is to make the short answer
            text bigger:
            <codeblock>
*[class = 'faq-short-answer'] {
  font-family: sans-serif;
  font-size: 14pt;
}
</codeblock></p>
    <p>Note that we are setting the <xmlatt>class</xmlatt> value on the <xmlelement>div</xmlelement> that
            you put around the short answer.</p>
    <p>Test your styles until you're satisfied with the visual result. If you want to get really sophisticated,
    you can add JavaScript to show or hide the answer details, but that's beyond the scope of this tutorial.</p>
    <p>That's it, you're done.</p>
  </body>
</topic>  